<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</title>
<link>https://infomgnt.org/</link>
<atom:link href="https://infomgnt.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.555</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Interviews on Shadow Libraries and AI in Publishing</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In April, two members of our research group were featured in interviews:</p>
<p>Dorothea Strecker, who has been studying shadow libraries for many years, was interviewed by the Norwegian newspaper Klassekampen <span class="citation" data-cites="stormyren_larsen_disse_2025">(Stormyren Larsen and Ugelstad Aas 2025)</span>. The interview was prompted by the investigation “The Unbelievable Scale of AI’s Pirated-Books Problem” published in The Atlantic <span class="citation" data-cites="reisner_unbelievable_2025">(Reisner 2025)</span>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/infomgnt_interview.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Heinz Pampel was interviewed for the @mediasres program on Deutschlandfunk <span class="citation" data-cites="deutschlandfunkde_eigene_2025">(deutschlandfunk.de 2025)</span>. The topic was the AI strategies of academic publishers. The interview was triggered by Politico’s announcement of a Policy Intelligence Assistant <span class="citation" data-cites="cooke_politico_2025">(Cooke 2025)</span>. We’re pleased about the interest in our research!</p>
<p>Further information about our research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-cooke_politico_2025" class="csl-entry">
Cooke, Melissa. 2025. <span>“<span>POLITICO</span> <span>Unveils</span> <span>Policy</span> <span>Intelligence</span> <span>Assistant</span>: <span>An</span> <span>AI</span> <span>Powered</span> <span>Suite</span> for <span>Policy</span> <span>Professionals</span>.”</span> <em>POLITICO</em>. <a href="https://politi.co/4is1z5g">https://politi.co/4is1z5g</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-deutschlandfunkde_eigene_2025" class="csl-entry">
deutschlandfunk.de. 2025. <span>“Eigene <span>KI</span>-<span>Assistenten</span> Und <span>Chatbots</span>: <span>Medienhäuser</span> Starten Neue <span>Anwendungen</span>.”</span> <em>Deutschlandfunk</em>. <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunk.de/eigene-ki-assistenten-und-chatbots-medienhaeuser-starten-neue-anwendungen-100.html">https://www.deutschlandfunk.de/eigene-ki-assistenten-und-chatbots-medienhaeuser-starten-neue-anwendungen-100.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-reisner_unbelievable_2025" class="csl-entry">
Reisner, Alex. 2025. <span>“The <span>Unbelievable</span> <span>Scale</span> of <span>AI</span>’s <span>Pirated</span>-<span>Books</span> <span>Problem</span>.”</span> <em>The Atlantic</em>. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2025/03/libgen-meta-openai/682093/">https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2025/03/libgen-meta-openai/682093/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-stormyren_larsen_disse_2025" class="csl-entry">
Stormyren Larsen, Selma, and Endre Ugelstad Ugelstad Aas. 2025. <span>“Disse Kan Leses Gratis.”</span> <em>Klassekampen.no</em>. <a href="https://klassekampen.no/artikkel/2025-03-27/disse-kan-leses-gratis">https://klassekampen.no/artikkel/2025-03-27/disse-kan-leses-gratis</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Interviews on {Shadow} {Libraries} and {AI} in {Publishing}},
  date = {2025-04-22},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/dp96r-bxb36},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Interviews on Shadow
Libraries and AI in Publishing.”</span> April 22, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/dp96r-bxb36">https://doi.org/10.59350/dp96r-bxb36</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/infomgnt_interview.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access Repositories in Germany</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Mattihas</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Funded by the Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF), our research project Pro OAR DE investigates current challenges in operating institutional repositories (IR) in Germany. Since completing our initial research phase—which included a systematic review and an interview study with IR managers at academic institutions—we have organized four networking forums since November 2024. In this blog post, we provide an overview of these four events.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/Blogpost_image.JPG" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our inaugural networking forum on <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-preprints">“Institutional Repositories and Preprints”</a>, held on November 19, 2024, attracted 64 participants across Germany. Following an introductory presentation by the project team, <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7060-3670">Lea-Maria Ferguson</a> (Helmholtz Open Science Office) highlighted challenges in quality assurance, standardization, and workflows from submission to maintenance and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9846-5516">Alexander Wagner</a> (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY) then focused on technical and practical aspects of integrating preprints into institutional repositories and illustrated how preprints are handled at DESY, a Helmholtz Center. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14185122">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>Our second networking forum,“Institutional Repositories and FIS/CRIS”, took place on December 11, 2024, and drew 103 participants. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9846-5516">Daniel Beucke</a> (Göttingen State and University Library) shared practical experiences integrating repositories with research information systems, highlighting challenges in interoperability and emphasizing the importance of networking, standards and persistent identifiers. <a href="https://orcid.org/0009-0004-2098-8076">Malte Kramer</a> (CRIS.NRW, University of Münster) introduced the CRIS.NRW initiative from the federal state of North Rhine-Westphalia, highlighting the interaction between institutional repositories and research information systems while stressing the necessity of compatible input workflows and identifier systems for successful integration. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14440151">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>The third networking forum on <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-zweitveroeffentlichung/prooarde-zweitveroeffentlichung/">“Institutional Repositories and Zweitveröffentlichung (self-archiving)”</a> took place on January 13, 2025, with 125 participants in attendance. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5994-0820">Sonja Härkönen</a> from the University of Augsburg presented her library’s service-oriented approach to self-archiving based on sustainable and user-friendly workflows, addressing communication challenges with researchers and emphasizing the collaborative role of the open-access.network’s Focus Group on Self-Archiving. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7279-2962">Tomasz Stompor</a> (Cooperative Library Network Berlin-Brandenburg) introduced DeepGreen as a central data hub for automated delivery of publications to repositories, outlining its evolution from a DFG project to an established service. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725628">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>On March 10, 2025, the fourth networking forum on <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-monitoring">“On monitoring and reporting with institutional repositories”</a> was held with 100 participants. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6083-9348">Dirk Pieper</a> and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5959-4999">Julia Bartlewski</a> (University of Bielefeld, openCost) introduced the openCost metadata schema as a standardized exchange format for publication costs and demonstrated its integration within their institutional repository as part of implementing an information budget.</p>
<p><a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8503-1740">Colin Sippl</a> and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7462-3847">Gernot Deinzer</a> (University of Regensburg), who presented their institution’s experience with integrating publication cost management into their repository, were showing the historical development from 2011 to their current system that handles both article-level costs and publishing agreements. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15056242">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>The insights and discussions from these networking forums, combined with the themed breakout groups held during each event, will form the foundation for developing topic-specific guidelines for open access and IR professionals throughout Germany.</p>
<p>Through these collaborative events, we have created opportunities for the open access community to collectively address key challenges in managing and evolving institutional repositories, identify practical solutions, and strengthen professional exchange across Germany’s IR landscape.</p>
<p>For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our official <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-matthias_pro_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Dirk Pieper, Julia Bartlewski, Colin Sippl, and Gernot Deinzer. 2025. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Publikations</span>- Und <span>Kostenmonitoring</span> Mit Institutionellen <span>Repositorien</span>,”</span> March. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.15056242">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.15056242</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024-1" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Daniel Beucke, and Malte Kramer. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>FIS</span>/<span>CRIS</span>,”</span> December. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14440152">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14440152</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_vernetzungsforum_2025" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Sonja Härkönen, and Tomasz Stompor. 2025. <span>“Vernetzungsforum: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>Zweitveröffentlichung</span>,”</span> January. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725629">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725629</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Alexander Wagner, Lea-Maria Ferguson, and Marcel Meistring. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>Preprints</span>,”</span> November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14185123">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14185123</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Mattihas, Lisa and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {Networking for the {Advancement} of {Institutional} {Open}
    {Access} {Repositories} in {Germany}},
  date = {2025-04-22},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/s3ddy-gdm33},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Lisa Mattihas, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access
Repositories in Germany.”</span> April 22, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/s3ddy-gdm33">https://doi.org/10.59350/s3ddy-gdm33</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/Blogpost_image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Is the German Scientific Landscape a Strong Driver for Open Science?</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Catalina Bohórquez Díaz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sharleen Frankenstein</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Henriette Humprecht</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zuhal Nur Kocabiyik</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jannik Kuhs-Ohmann</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Max Liebel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sofie-Lilly Prinada</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Patricia Rocha Dias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hendrik Zimnol</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background</h2>
<p>As part of the project module <em>Open Science as a Field of Action for Scientific Institutions</em>, students from the Institute for Library and Information Science at Humboldt University zu Berlin (HU), under the supervision of Prof.&nbsp;Dr.&nbsp;Heinz Pampel, organized an event. During the winter semester of 2024/25, the students examined strategies on how scientific institutions shape and promote the topic of Open Science.</p>
<p>To conclude their work, the project course hosted the event <em>“Is the German Scientific Landscape a Strong Driver for Open Science? – Open Science as a Field of Action for Scientific Institutions”</em> on February 4, 2025, at the Einstein Center Digital Future (ECDF) in Berlin.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/PSE_Blogpost_image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="presentations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presentations">Presentations</h2>
<p>Open Science refers to efforts to implement various approaches to an open scientific practice <span class="citation" data-cites="unesco2021">(UNESCO 2021)</span>, aiming to promote transparent and inclusive science.</p>
<p>At the beginning of the event, three invited speakers – Dr.&nbsp;Lisa Kressin from the Leibniz Association, Dr.&nbsp;Stefan Skupien from the Berlin University Alliance (BUA), and Marcel Meistring from the Helmholtz Centre for Geosciences (GFZ) – presented different approaches taken by libraries and research institutions regarding Open Science.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Lisa Kressin (Leibniz Association) began her presentation by discussing the crucial role of infrastructures in promoting Open Science. She also emphasized the significance of self-governance in science for the development of Open Science. According to Kressin, Open Science must be developed in close collaboration with the scientific community rather than being purely politically motivated. However, she acknowledged that political engagement remains essential to advancing Open Science. She highlighted the potential of Open Science in strengthening research quality and reinforcing scientific transparency.</p>
<p>Furthermore, she addressed the challenges of Open Science in practice. Due to varying knowledge cultures, it is impossible to impose uniform expectations on all stakeholders. She advocated for a practical approach to Open Science and stressed that funding remains a pressing issue. Kressin saw great potential in networking among scientific organizations to advance Open Science.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Stefan Skupien (BUA) also highlighted the importance of Open Science networks and collaboration, as many Open Science challenges require cooperative solutions. He underscored the potential of Open Science for research and introduced measures implemented by the BUA to promote it. Besides infrastructure development, Skupien focused on Open Science education and monitoring Open Science practices. These topics are also supported by the BUA through Open Science Fellowships.</p>
<p>Another initiative he mentioned was the establishment of <em>Open Science Ambassadors</em>, who serve as multipliers, spreading Open Science practices within the scientific community. He pointed out that the importance of Open Science varies across faculties within the BUA institutions. Therefore, the BUA aims to establish a reflective and discipline-specific approach to Open Science practices.</p>
<p>In the final presentation, Marcel Meistring from the GFZ Helmholtz Centre for Geosciences emphasized the importance of extensive consulting, research-support services, and support offerings in the field of publishing research results and research data management. He provided insights into the Open Science policy of the Helmholtz Association and the Open Science-related guidelines of the GFZ. He stressed that such policies serve as crucial guidelines in establishing an Open Science culture within scientific institutions.</p>
<p>Additionally, he explained the relevance of adhering to standards and utilizing persistent identifiers (PIDs) for providing, archiving, storing, publishing, and linking texts, research data, and research software. The use of standards and PIDs is crucial for the efficient implementation of Open Science. Meistring also presented current efforts by the Helmholtz Association to develop new quality indicators for research data and software publications. The goal is to adopt a broader perspective on research performance, recognizing published research data and software as valuable research outputs based on specific quality criteria.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>Following the presentations, the speakers engaged in a panel discussion, addressing questions regarding the further development of Open Science and potential fields of action, with additional contributions and questions from the audience. The discussion highlighted the necessity of further advancing Open Science in Germany. The panelists supported additional cross-organizational projects similar to the DEAL initiative.</p>
<p>As repeatedly emphasized in the presentations, intensified collaboration among various Open Science stakeholders is essential to effectively address challenges. However, difficulties arise due to funding constraints and a lack of institutional initiative. The monitoring of Open Science practices was identified as a crucial field of action for advancing Open Science. Additionally, promoting information literacy was deemed essential for the positive development of Open Science.</p>
<p>The discussion also touched upon the integration of Open Science principles into university curricula across all disciplines so that future researchers develop awareness of Open Science’s opportunities and challenges. In this context, the BUA Ambassadors initiative was praised for facilitating communication and exchange across different scientific domains, from which other institutions could also benefit.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In summary, although Open Science has been a relevant topic in Germany for several years, the scientific community still does not allocate it sufficient attention and significance. Enhanced training in the form of workshops and advisory services on Open Science, as well as adequate resources, are crucial for further advancing Open Science in Germany. In this regard, sustainable funding, stronger collaboration among stakeholders, increased resource allocation in infrastructures, and greater public involvement are needed.</p>
<p>Given the budgetary and geopolitical challenges for open and networked science, the speakers expressed some concerns about future developments. Nevertheless, they emphasized the importance of embedding and promoting Open Science in a cooperative and international context to align its progress with UNESCO recommendations.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-deutsche_unesco-kommission_open_2020" class="csl-entry">
Deutsche UNESCO-Kommission, ed. 2020. <em>Open Science: <span>Perspektiven</span> Aus <span>Deutschland</span> Auf Die <span>Erarbeitung</span> Der Geplanten <span>Empfehlung</span> Der <span>UNESCO</span> = <span>UNESCO</span> Recommendation in <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span></em>. Berlin: Deutsche UNESCO-Kommission e.V.
</div>
<div id="ref-unesco2021" class="csl-entry">
UNESCO. 2021. <span>“UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.54677/MNMH8546">https://doi.org/10.54677/MNMH8546</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{catalina bohórquez díaz2025,
  author = {Catalina Bohórquez Díaz, Laura and Frankenstein, Sharleen
    and Humprecht, Henriette and Onzie Khamis, Christopher and Nur
    Kocabiyik, Zuhal and Kuhs-Ohmann, Jannik and Liebel, Max and
    Prinada, Sofie-Lilly and Rocha Dias, Patricia and Zimnol, Hendrik},
  title = {Is the {German} {Scientific} {Landscape} a {Strong} {Driver}
    for {Open} {Science?}},
  date = {2025-04-17},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/vc1ht-2mz23},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-catalina bohórquez díaz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Catalina Bohórquez Díaz, Laura, Sharleen Frankenstein, Henriette
Humprecht, Christopher Onzie Khamis, Zuhal Nur Kocabiyik, Jannik
Kuhs-Ohmann, Max Liebel, Sofie-Lilly Prinada, Patricia Rocha Dias, and
Hendrik Zimnol. 2025. <span>“Is the German Scientific Landscape a Strong
Driver for Open Science?”</span> April 17, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/vc1ht-2mz23">https://doi.org/10.59350/vc1ht-2mz23</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/PSE_Blogpost_image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar zur Erfassung von Publikationskosten</title>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Karin Ilg</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Am 28.03.2025 veranstaltete das Projekt OA Datenpraxis <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_datenpraxis_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span> das erste Webinar zum Thema ”Erfassung von Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland”. In dem Webinar wurden Ergebnisse einer Umfrage vorgestellt, die im Jahr 2024 durchgeführt wurde. Die Umfrage, die im Dialog mit Vertreter<em>innen von <a href="https://deal-konsortium.de/">DEAL</a> entwickelt wurde, erhob, wie Daten zu Publikationskosten aktuell an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland erfasst werden. Adressiert wurden Vertreter</em>innen von Universitäten, Fachhochschulen, Instituten außeruniversitärer Forschungseinrichtungen sowie Ressortforschungseinrichtungen des Bundes. Von 583 eingeladenen Personen beteiligten sich 258 (44,3 %) an der Umfrage. Die Umfrage ist die erste umfassende Erhebung zur Erfassung von Publikationskosten in Deutschland. An der Veranstaltung nahmen erfreulicherweise über 200 Personen aus Wissenschaft, Verwaltung, Informationsinfrastruktur und Forschungsförderung teil.</p>
<p>In diesem Beitrag werden kurz einige zentrale Punkte der Veranstaltung zusammengefasst: Ergebnisse der Umfrage, Fragen aus dem Kreis der Teilnehmenden, sowie einige Diskussionspunkte aus der abschließenden Paneldiskussion.</p>
<section id="ergebnisse-der-umfrage" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ergebnisse-der-umfrage">Ergebnisse der Umfrage</h2>
<p>Nach der Begrüßung und Einführung wurden zentrale Ergebnisse der Studie vorgestellt: Während die systematische Erfassung von Publikationen und Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen durchaus verbreitet ist, haben viele Einrichtungen diese noch nicht fest etabliert und nutzen zudem das Potenzial dieser Daten noch nicht voll aus. Für die Finanzierung von Open-Access-Publikationen stellen Publikationsfonds eine tragende Säule dar. Die Etablierung von Informationsbudgets dagegen befindet sich noch in der Aufbauphase. Zur Förderung der Open-Access-Transformation sollte die Finanzierung weiter untersucht werden. Diese und weitere Ergebnisse können den Vortragsfolien <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_oa_2025">(Strecker, Pampel, and Höfting 2025)</span> entnommen werden. Eine Publikation dazu ist in Vorbereitung.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="fragen-der-teilnehmenden" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fragen-der-teilnehmenden">Fragen der Teilnehmenden</h2>
<p>Im Anschluss an die Ergebnispräsentation hatten die Teilnehmer:innen des Webinars die Gelegenheit, Nachfragen zu stellen. Interesse weckten beispielsweise die für das Monitoring in den Einrichtungen genutzten Tools und die Verwendung der Daten für die strategische Planung. Kritisch diskutiert wurde die Belastbarkeit von bestehenden Datensammlungen zu Open Access. Mehrere Fragen adressierten die Notwendigkeit von Standardisierung in diesem Bereich.</p>
</section>
<section id="paneldiskussion-mit-mitgliedern-der-deal-gruppe" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paneldiskussion-mit-mitgliedern-der-deal-gruppe">Paneldiskussion mit Mitgliedern der DEAL-Gruppe</h2>
<p>An der Paneldiskussion nahm seitens der DEAL-Gruppe Karin Ilg (Hochschule Bielefeld) teil (weitere Mitglieder der DEAL-Gruppe mussten ihre Teilnahme kurzfristig absagen) . und teilte ihre Perspektive auf die Ergebnisse. Sie hob positiv hervor, dass einige Einrichtungen trotz schwieriger Rahmenbedingungen – wie der teilweise dezentralen Erfassung durch mehrere Abteilungen in verschiedenen Systemen – bereits einen systematischen Überblick über ihre Publikationskosten erreicht haben. Gleichzeitig betonte sie, dass flächendeckende Monitoringaktivitäten noch fehlten. In dieser Phase der Open-Access-Transformation sei eine aktivere Rolle der Leitungsebenen sowie eine stärkere Vernetzung zwischen Einrichtungen erforderlich. Auf die Herausforderungen bei der Etablierung von Informationsbudgets angesprochen verwies sie auf erhebliche Hürden, stellte aber auch die strukturbildenden Effekte von Programmen wie <a href="https://www.dfg.de/de/foerderung/foerdermoeglichkeiten/programme/infrastruktur/lis/lis-foerderangebote/open-access-publikationskosten">Open-Access-Publikationskosten</a> der DFG und von DEAL heraus. Die communitybasierte Entwicklung einheitlicher Standards der Datenerfassung stelle einen dringenden Handlungsbedarf dar.</p>
</section>
<section id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis">Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.oadatenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a> ist ein gemeinsames DFG-Projekt des <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de">Instituts für Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a>, des <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> und der <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de">Niedersächsischen Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen</a>.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis finden Sie auf der <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/events.html">Webseite</a> des Projektes. Weitere Informationen zu unserer Arbeit am Lehrstuhl Information Management finden Sie auf unserer <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">offiziellen Webseite</a>.</p>
<p>Dieser Text - mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Teilen - ist lizenziert unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_datenpraxis_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Najko Jahn, Roland Bertelmann, Wolfram Horstmann, Laura Rothfritz, Lea Maria Ferguson, Birgit Schmidt, and Anna Stisser. 2024. <span>“Datenpraxis Zur <span>Gestaltung</span> Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Transformation</span> - <span>Analyse</span>, <span>Empfehlung</span>, <span>Training</span> &amp; <span>Vernetzung</span> (<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span>).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10794298">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10794298</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_oa_2025" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea, Heinz Pampel, and Jonas Höfting. 2025. <span>“<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span> <span>Webinar</span>: <span>Erfassung</span> von <span>Publikationskosten</span> an Wissenschaftlichen <span>Einrichtungen</span> in <span>Deutschland</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15076512">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15076512</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{höfting2025,
  author = {Höfting, Jonas and Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz and
    Ilg, Karin},
  title = {Rückblick: {OA} {Datenpraxis} {Webinar} Zur {Erfassung} von
    {Publikationskosten}},
  date = {2025-04-14},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/c7d5j-rw005},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-höfting2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Höfting, Jonas, Dorothea Strecker, Heinz Pampel, and Karin Ilg. 2025.
<span>“Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar Zur Erfassung von
Publikationskosten.”</span> April 14, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/c7d5j-rw005">https://doi.org/10.59350/c7d5j-rw005</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Information Management Research Group at the BID Kongress 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-14-the-information-management-research-group-at-the-bid-kongress/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are pleased to announce that the projects <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/index.html">OA Datenpraxis</a> and <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> of the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement">Information Management Research Group</a> from the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de">Berlin School of Library and Information Science</a> at the <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/de">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a> will be represented at this year’s BID Congress. Furthermore, Heinz Pampel will be involved in several other events during the BID Congress.</p>
<section id="oa-datenpraxis" class="level1">
<h1>OA Datenpraxis</h1>
<p>The Hands-on Lab titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/sessions/79">Open-Access-Monitoring-Dashboards mit Quarto</a>’ will take place on June 24th from 16:00–18:00 in Salon London. <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/kontakt/personen-a-z/personendetails/person/sophia-doerner/">Sophia Dörner</a> will give a practical introduction to the development of a simple dashboard for the (open access) publication output of research institutions using Quarto, an open-source publication system. Previous knowledge of the R programming language or Quarto is not required, but helpful. Please bring a laptop and create a <a href="https://posit.cloud/plans/free">Posit Cloud account</a> in advance.</p>
<p>The lecture titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/presentations/273">Recording of publication costs at scientific institutions in Germany</a>’ will take place on June 27th from 11 to 11:30 in the Focke-Wulf Saal. Dorothea Strecker, Heinz Pampel and Jonas Höfting will present the results of a survey conducted in 2024 as part of the OA Datenpraxis project. The survey investigated how data on publication costs are currently recorded at scientific institutions in Germany. Representatives of universities, universities of applied sciences, institutes of non-university research organisations (Fraunhofer Society, Helmholtz Association, Leibniz Association and Max Planck Society) and federal departmental research institutions were addressed.</p>
</section>
<section id="infra-wiss-blogs" class="level1">
<h1>Infra Wiss Blogs</h1>
<p>The lecture titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/presentations/307">Mapping German scholarly blogs - results and impulses</a>’ will take place on June 26th from 11 to 11:30 in Hall 4.1/Room II. Catharina Ochsner, Heinz Pampel and Jonas Höfting from the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement">Chair of Information Management</a> of the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de">Institute of Library and Information Science</a> at <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/de">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a> (HU Berlin), will present the results of a data collection of over 800 German scholarly blogs, which were analysed for infrastructural aspects. In addition, impulses will be given for academic libraries to make a contribution to ensuring the long-term accessibility of blogs.</p>
<p>The Hands-on Lab titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/sessions/84">Libraries as operating and preserving institutions for scholarly blogs</a>’ will also take place on June 26th from 2 to 4 pm in the Salon Oslo. In the hands-on lab, participants will discuss the role of libraries in the development, dissemination and preservation of scholarly blogs under the organisation and moderation of experts from the scholarly blog landscape. Aspects of technology, organisation and framework conditions for safeguarding blogs will be discussed in round tables. The Hands-on Lab will be led by <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/teaminfomanagement">Catharina Ochsner</a> (HU Berlin) and supported by <a href="https://heinzpampel.de/">Heinz Pampel</a> (HU Berlin), <a href="https://verfassungsblog.de/author/elena-di-rosa/">Elena Di Rosa</a> (<a href="https://verfassungsblog.de/">Verfassungsblog</a>), <a href="https://front-matter.io/team">Martin Fenner</a> (<a href="https://front-matter.%20io/">Front Matter</a>), Sven Ködel (<a href="https://www.dhi-paris.fr/home.html">German Historical Institute Paris</a>), <a href="https://www.gesis.org/institut/ueber-uns/mitarbeitendenverzeichnis/person/Charmaine.Voigt">Charmaine Voigt</a> (<a href="https://www.gesis.org/home">GESIS: Leibniz Institute for Social Sciences</a>) and <a href="https://www.dnb.de/SharedDocs/Kontaktdaten/DE/wolderingBritta.html">Britta Woldering</a> from the <a href="https://www.dnb.de/DE/Home/home_node.html">German National Library</a>. To register for the workshop, please send an E-Mail to Catharina Ochsner.</p>
</section>
<section id="other-work" class="level1">
<h1>Other Work</h1>
<p>Furthermore Heinz Pampel will be part of two lectures and a Hands-on-Lab. Together with <a href="https://vivo.tib.eu/fis/display/n0000-0001-5322-0478">Judith Luwdig</a> (<a href="https://www.tib.eu/de/">Technische Informationsbibliothek Hannover</a>) and <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/zb/kontakt/zb-leitung">Bernhard Mittermaier</a> (<a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de">Research Center Jülich</a>) Prof.&nbsp;Pampel will give a talk on ‘AI clauses in licence agreements’. The talk will take place on thursday June, 26th between 10 and 10:30 am in the Hanse Saal. Additionally Prof.&nbsp;Pampel will be part of the lecture ‘Strategic approaches to intensify the OA transformation: perspectives for science organisations’ alongside <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/team-und-kontakt/">Lea Maria Ferguson</a> (<a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a>), <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/team-und-kontakt/">Marc Lange</a> (<a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a>), <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/zb/kontakt/zb-leitung">Bernhard Mittermaier</a> (<a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de">Research Center Jülich</a>) and <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/team-und-kontakt/">Meistring</a> (<a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a>). The talk will take place on June 26th from 9 to 9:30 am in Room 5 in hall 4.1. Lastly Prof.&nbsp;Pampel will lead the Hands-on Lab ‘Sustainably financing open access infrastructures’ at the 26th of June from 4:30 to 6 pm in the Salon London. Together with <a href="https://www.zbw.eu/de/ueber-zbw/profil/mitarbeiterprofile/profil-olaf-siegert">Olaf Siegert</a> (<a href="https://www.zbw.eu/de/">ZBW - Leibniz Information Centre for Economics</a>), <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/zb/kontakt/zb-leitung">Bernhard Mittermaier</a> (<a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de">Research Center Jülich</a>), <a href="https://www.dfg.de/de/ueber-uns/geschaeftsstelle/personen/michael-geuenich-165456">Michael Geuenich</a> (<a href="(https://www.dfg.de/de)">German Research Foundation</a>), <a href="https://www.zib.de/members/rusch">Beate Rusch</a> (<a href="https://www.zib.de/index.php/">Zuse Institute Berlin</a>) and Silke Weisheit (<a href="https://www.uni-regensburg.de/bibliothek/startseite/index.html">University Library Regensburg</a>) the participants will discuss developments and practical reports on sustainable Open Access financing. To register for the workshop, please send an E-Mail to Heinz Pampel.</p>
<p>We look forward to seeing you at this year’s BID Congress and to discuss our projects with you. If you have any questions regarding the BID Congress or the events, please do not hesitate to contact Dorothea Strecker and Catharina Ochsner.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {The {Information} {Management} {Research} {Group} at the
    {BID} {Kongress} 2025},
  date = {2025-03-14},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/txet3-efm12},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, Dorothea Strecker, and Heinz Pampel. 2025.
<span>“The Information Management Research Group at the BID Kongress
2025.”</span> March 14, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/txet3-efm12">https://doi.org/10.59350/txet3-efm12</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-14-the-information-management-research-group-at-the-bid-kongress/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-14-the-information-management-research-group-at-the-bid-kongress/BID.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OA Datenpraxis Webinar: Erfassung von Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Wir laden Sie herzlich zur Veranstaltung “OA Datenpraxis Webinar: Erfassung von Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland” ein, die am 28.03.2025 von 10:00 bis 11:00 CET über Zoom stattfindet.</p>
<p>In dem Webinar werden Ergebnisse einer Umfrage <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_datenpraxis_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span> vorgestellt, die im Rahmen des von der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) geförderten Projekts OA Datenpraxis <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_survey_2024">(Strecker and Pampel 2024)</span> im Jahr 2024 durchgeführt wurde.</p>
<p>Die Umfrage, die im Dialog mit Vertreter:innen der DEAL-Untergruppe “Kommunikation” entwickelt wurde, erhob, wie Daten zu Publikationskosten aktuell an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland erfasst werden. Adressiert wurden Vertreter*innen von Universitäten, Fachhochschulen, Instituten außeruniversitärer Forschungseinrichtungen sowie Ressortforschungseinrichtungen des Bundes. Von 583 eingeladenen Personen beteiligten sich 258 (44,3 %) an der Umfrage. Die Umfrage ist die erste umfassende Erhebung zur Erfassung von Publikationskosten in Deutschland.</p>
<p>Dieses Webinar richtet sich an Professionals, die sich für Open-Access-Monitoring, insbesondere die Erfassung von Open-Access-Publikationskosten, interessieren.</p>
<section id="programm" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="programm">Programm</h2>
<p>Nach einer Präsentation der Umfrageergebnisse haben Teilnehmende die Möglichkeit, Fragen zur Umfrage zu stellen. Anschließend werden einige zentrale Aspekte der Erfassung von Publikationskosten in einer Paneldiskussion mit Mitgliedern der DEAL-Gruppe erörtert.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Begrüßung durch Heinz Pampel (5 Minuten)</p></li>
<li><p>Vorstellung der Umfrageergebnisse durch Dorothea Strecker (30 Minuten)</p></li>
<li><p>Q &amp; A zur Umfrage (10 Minuten)</p></li>
<li><p>Paneldiskussion mit Mitgliedern der DEAL-Gruppe (15 Minuten)</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="anmeldung" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="anmeldung">Anmeldung</h2>
<p>Eine Anmeldung zum Webinar ist über den folgenden Link möglich: <a href="https://hu-berlin.zoom-x.de/webinar/register/WN_pKTlDzjsQwC7QspLxwMHCg">Link zur Anmeldung</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/logo_oa_datenpraxis(1).png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis">Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.oadatenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a> ist ein gemeinsames DFG-Projekt des <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de">Instituts für Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a>, des <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> und der <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de">Niedersächsischen Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen</a>.</p>
<p>Aktuelle Veranstaltungen von OA Datenpraxis finden Sie auf der <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/events.html">Projektwebseite</a>.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen zum Lehrstuhl Information Management finden Sie auf unserer <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">offiziellen Webseite</a>.</p>
<p>Dieser Text - mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Teilen - ist lizenziert unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_datenpraxis_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Najko Jahn, Roland Bertelmann, Wolfram Horstmann, Laura Rothfritz, Lea Maria Ferguson, Birgit Schmidt, and Anna Stisser. 2024. <span>“Datenpraxis Zur <span>Gestaltung</span> Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Transformation</span> - <span>Analyse</span>, <span>Empfehlung</span>, <span>Training</span> &amp; <span>Vernetzung</span> (<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span>).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_survey_2024" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“Survey Announcement: <span>Recording</span> Publication Costs at Research Performing Institutions in <span>Germany</span>.”</span> <em>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/9z58m-vwv42">https://doi.org/10.59350/9z58m-vwv42</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz and Höfting, Jonas},
  title = {OA {Datenpraxis} {Webinar:} {Erfassung} von
    {Publikationskosten} an Wissenschaftlichen {Einrichtungen} in
    {Deutschland}},
  date = {2025-03-07},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/wnnk6-rzr69},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, Heinz Pampel, and Jonas Höfting. 2025. <span>“OA
Datenpraxis Webinar: Erfassung von Publikationskosten an
Wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland.”</span> March 7, 2025.
<a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/wnnk6-rzr69">https://doi.org/10.59350/wnnk6-rzr69</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/logo_oa_datenpraxis(1).png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Critical Data Discourses: A Lecture Series on the Ethics of Research Data</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Katrin Frisch</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a time when research data is increasingly at the heart of research integrity, discussions about data sharing, openness, and reusability have gained prominence. Yet, the ethical complexities surrounding research data—who collects it, how it is used, and whose interests it serves—are often sidelined. The <a href="https://critical-data-discourse.quarto.pub/">Critical Data Discourses</a> lecture series seeks to shift the focus from purely technical concerns to broader ethical, social, and political reflections on data.</p>
<p>Discussions about data in research are often dominated by principles like FAIR <span class="citation" data-cites="wilkinsonFAIRGuidingPrinciples2016">(Wilkinson et al. 2016)</span>, which aim to standardize and optimize the findability, accessibility, interoperability and reusability of research data. While these principles are important, they do not fully capture the ethical dimensions of data collection and use. Questions of fairness, responsibility, power dynamics, and care work in data practices are not covered by these principles.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/poster.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>At the same time, international discussions have introduced complementary frameworks, such as the CARE principles <span class="citation" data-cites="Carroll-2020">(Carroll et al. 2020)</span>—developed from Indigenous governance perspectives—which emphasize the social and relational aspects of data. These principles highlight how data is not just a neutral resource but deeply intertwined with historical, social, and ethical considerations.</p>
<p>With this lecture series, we aim to bring together data professionals and critical scholars to examine the evolving landscape of data ethics and adjacent questions about data politics and data justice. Through a series of expert talks, we are exploring issues that are often missing from mainstream research data discussions, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>The ethics of data collection and the ethical considerations behind it</li>
<li>The role of domain-specific ethical considerations in fields like humanities, medicine, and AI research</li>
<li>The limitations of existing data frameworks and their unintended consequences</li>
<li>Data gaps and missing data—what is left out of research and why</li>
<li>The influence of AI and automation on knowledge production and discrimination</li>
<li>The impact of historical injustices on contemporary data practices</li>
</ul>
<p>Our motivation for organizing this series stems from a shared interest in rethinking data practices beyond efficiency and compliance, and centering on issues of ethics, justice, transparency, and responsibility. More information is available <a href="https://critical-data-discourse.quarto.pub/">on our website</a>.</p>
<p>After a successful launch with over 100 participants in our first session, we are excited to continue the discussions in our upcoming talks on data ethics, AI, and power structures in research data.</p>
<p>Here is a look at what’s next (in German):</p>
<section id="session-3-04.03.2025-14-16-uhr-ethik-des-sammelns" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-3-04.03.2025-14-16-uhr-ethik-des-sammelns">Session 3: 04.03.2025, 14-16 Uhr Ethik des Sammelns</h3>
<p>The Dark Side of DNA: Exposing the Ethical Lapses That Threaten Human Genetics</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Yves Moreau, University of Leuven, Belgium</em></p>
<p>Unborn digital. Challenges in data publications on collections of human embryos and fetuses</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Michael Markert, FAU Erlangen-Nürnberg</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/56827" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/56827</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-4-20.03.2025-14-16-uhr-fachspezifische-datenethik" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-4-20.03.2025-14-16-uhr-fachspezifische-datenethik">Session 4: 20.03.2025, 14-16 Uhr Fachspezifische Datenethik</h3>
<p>Ethische Kontrollinstanzen für die Literaturwissenschaft? Über Freiheit und Verantwortung im literaturwissenschaftlichen Datenumgang</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Katharina Fürholzer, Universität Koblenz</em></p>
<p>Ethische Aspekte der Nutzung generativer KI in der Wissenschaft – ein medizinethischer Blickwinkel</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Theresa Willem, TU München &amp; Helmholtz Zentrum München - Deutsches Forschungszentrum für Gesundheit und Umwelt</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/85362" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/85362</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-5-03.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-gaps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-5-03.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-gaps">Session 5: 03.04.2025 14-16 Uhr Data Gaps</h3>
<p>Die Polizeiliche Kriminalstatistik (PKS) – belastbare Grundlage für gesellschaftspolitische Debatten oder verzerrtes Datensammelsammelsurium?</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Martin Thüne, FHVD - Fachbereich Polizei</em></p>
<p>Datenbank zu Rechtsterrorismus: Schwierigkeiten und Chancen bei der Datenerhebung.</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Thilo Manemann, Center for Monitoring, Analyse und Strategie</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/37719" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/37719</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-6-10.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-agency-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-6-10.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-agency-ai">Session 6: 10.04.2025, 14-16 Uhr Data Agency &amp; AI</h3>
<p>Die neue Unsichtbarkeit von Frauen: Von synthetischen Bildern und ethischen Folgen</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Eugenia Stamboliev, Universität Wien</em></p>
<p>More or less discrimination? Psychological (and other) AIs in personnel selection</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Helena Mihaljević, Hochschule für Technik und Wirtschaft, Berlin</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/64446" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/64446</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-7-29.04.2025-14-16-uhr-abschlussveranstaltung" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-7-29.04.2025-14-16-uhr-abschlussveranstaltung">Session 7: 29.04.2025, 14-16 Uhr Abschlussveranstaltung</h3>
<p>Menschenrechtsbasierter Zugang zu Daten: der Monitor Gewalt gegen Frauen - Indikatoren, Arbeit mit administrativen Daten und ethische Implikationen</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Jolanda Krok, Miriam Schroer-Hippel, Lilly-Allegra Hikisch</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/74686" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/74686</a></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Carroll-2020" class="csl-entry">
Carroll, Stephanie Russo, Ibrahim Garba, Oscar L. Figueroa-Rodríguez, Jarita Holbrook, Raymond Lovett, Simeon Materechera, Mark Parsons, et al. 2020. <span>“The <span>CARE</span> Principles for Indigenous Data Governance.”</span> <em>Data Science Journal</em>, November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2020-043">https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2020-043</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wilkinsonFAIRGuidingPrinciples2016" class="csl-entry">
Wilkinson, Mark D., Michel Dumontier, IJsbrand Jan Aalbersberg, Gabrielle Appleton, Myles Axton, Arie Baak, Niklas Blomberg, et al. 2016. <span>“The <span>FAIR Guiding Principles</span> for Scientific Data Management and Stewardship.”</span> <em>Scientific Data</em> 3 (March): 160018.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2025,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura and Frisch, Katrin},
  title = {Critical {Data} {Discourses:} {A} {Lecture} {Series} on the
    {Ethics} of {Research} {Data}},
  date = {2025-02-21},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/6dp70-2j455},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura, and Katrin Frisch. 2025. <span>“Critical Data
Discourses: A Lecture Series on the Ethics of Research Data .”</span>
February 21, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/6dp70-2j455">https://doi.org/10.59350/6dp70-2j455</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/pic.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Promoting Open Science at the Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin as BUA Open Science Ambassadors</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/bua_logo.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The Ambassadors for Open Science program of the <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/index.html">Berlin University Alliance, BUA</a> aims to promote the knowledge and application of Open Science in various subjects. As Open Science experts and enthusiasts, the ambassadors show researchers, students and decision-makers at their institution how they can benefit from and make use of Open Science infrastructure <span class="citation" data-cites="berlin_university_alliance_auftakt_2024">(Alliance 2024a)</span>.</p>
<p>We are pleased to announce that <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/index.html">Dorothea Strecker</a> and <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Catharina Ochsner</a> from the Berlin School of Library and Information Science will serve as the Open Science ambassadors for the <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/en/institutions/faculties-and-departments/fac-arts-humanities/standardseite">Faculty of Arts and Humanities</a> at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin (HU) until 31 July 2025.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/core/index.html">Center for Open and Responsible Research (CORe)</a> of the Berlin University Alliance (BUA) supports the ambassadors with financial resources for training and networking activities or for the organization of further education events for research colleagues, decision-makers and students <span class="citation" data-cites="berlin_university_alliance_open_2024">(Alliance 2024b)</span>. We will announce future activities on our <a href="https://infomgnt.org/">lab blog</a> and our <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events">official website</a>. We are looking forward to hosting events as part of the Open Science ambassador program and to facilitate the adoption of Open Science practices at the HU.</p>
<p>If you have questions or wishes you can reach us via e-mail under dorothea.strecker@hu-berlin.de or catharina.ochsner@hu-berlin.de. More detailed information on the Ambassadors for Open Science program can be found <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/os-botschafter-innen/index.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-berlin_university_alliance_auftakt_2024" class="csl-entry">
Alliance, Berlin University. 2024a. <span>“Auftakt Für Neu Ernannte <span>BUA</span> <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span> <span>Ambassadors</span>.”</span> <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/items/2024/240924-open-science-ambassadors.html">https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/items/2024/240924-open-science-ambassadors.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-berlin_university_alliance_open_2024" class="csl-entry">
———. 2024b. <span>“Die <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span> <span>Botschafter</span> Der <span>Berlin</span> <span>University</span> <span>Alliance</span>.”</span> <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/os-botschafter-innen/index.html">https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/os-botschafter-innen/index.html</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Strecker, Dorothea},
  title = {Promoting {Open} {Science} at the {Humboldt-Universität} Zu
    {Berlin} as {BUA} {Open} {Science} {Ambassadors}},
  date = {2025-02-05},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/ja4m1-92098},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Dorothea Strecker. 2025. <span>“Promoting Open
Science at the Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin as BUA Open Science
Ambassadors.”</span> February 5, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/ja4m1-92098">https://doi.org/10.59350/ja4m1-92098</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/Unbenannt.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="68" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What happens when public data infrastructures aren’t save? A look at past and current developments in the US</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-What-happens-when-public-data-infrastructures-arent-save/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In my PhD research, I look at DataRescue or Data Refuge movements, for example through the work of the <a href="https://envirodatagov.org/">Environmental Data and Governance Initiative</a> (EDGI) <span class="citation" data-cites="EnvironmentalDataGovernance">(<span>“Environmental <span>Data</span> &amp; <span>Governance Initiative</span>”</span> n.d.)</span> to understand how people respond when they fear data is at risk. I’m particularly interested in what these efforts reveal about how public data infrastructures actually work—not just as systems of information storage, but as objects of political struggle.</p>
<p>This research started quite some time ago with an overarching topic of trust and distrust in public data infrastructures <span class="citation" data-cites="rothfritzUnderstandingMistrustDistrust2024">(Rothfritz 2024a)</span>. I planned for the first iteration of the DataRescue movement to serve as a case study for this research <span class="citation" data-cites="rothfritzUnderstandingTrustDistrust2024">(Rothfritz 2024b)</span>. Of course, I did not anticipate that there would be another series of events which would lead to the loss of access to public information and data in the U.S. so soon.</p>
<section id="rescuing-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rescuing-data">Rescuing Data</h3>
<p>In 2016, a group of librarians, archivists, and environmental activists saw the writing on the wall: the incoming U.S. administration might threaten access to crucial federal climate data. What followed was a series of DataRescue events: community-led efforts to archive and preserve environmental datasets that many feared would be deleted, altered, or buried in bureaucratic obscurity <span class="citation" data-cites="janzMaintainingAccessPublic2017 currieBackupsFutureArchival2018">(Janz 2017; Currie and Paris 2018)</span></p>
<p>Fast forward to 2025. Another major political shift is unfolding in the U.S., and with it, new concerns about the integrity and accessibility of public data. This time around, large amounts of public federal information such as websites <span class="citation" data-cites="singerThousandsUSGovernment2025a">(Singer 2025)</span> and data <span class="citation" data-cites="koeblerArchivistsWorkIdentify2025a">(Koebler 2025)</span> are disappearing from public access again. The scale and breadth of which kind of information is disappearing is arguably larger though - it concerns not just environmental data and climate change mentions on websites, but also for example health data and information from the Centers for Disease and Control Prevention (CDC) <span class="citation" data-cites="sunCDCRemovesGender2025 coxLookFederalHealth2025">(Sun, Keating, and Nirappil 2025; Cox et al. 2025)</span>. Efforts seem to be more strategic and orchestrated.</p>
<p>The good news is that at least to a pretty far extent preparations were taking place before the Trump administration took office in January. For example, all federal websites were archived through the <a href="https://eotarchive.org">End-Of-Term Web Archive</a>, a project which routinely has been doing this for administration changes in the U.S. since 2008 <span class="citation" data-cites="EndTermWeb">(<span>“End of <span>Term Web Archive</span>”</span> n.d.)</span>. A dataset of CDC data uploaded before January 28th, 2025 <a href="https://archive.org/details/20250128-cdc-datasets">is available on the Internet Archive</a>. EDGI and the <a href="https://screening-tools.com">Public Environmental Data Project</a> have worked ahead to archive crucial environmental data <span class="citation" data-cites="edgiWhyEDGIArchiving2025">(EDGI 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>There are quite a few other initiatives taking place at the moment. A good overview resource is collected through IASSIST on this <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/15ZRxHqbhGDHCXo7Hqi_Vcy4Q50ZItLblIFaY3s7LBLw/edit?userstoinvite=spacific@gmail.com&amp;sharingaction=manageaccess&amp;role=writer&amp;tab=t.0">Google Doc</a>, which is constantly being updated.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-this-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h3>
<p>Public data infrastructures—the systems that store and provide access to government data—are often taken for granted. We assume that scientific reports, climate models, and environmental monitoring data will always be there when we need them. But these infrastructures are not just technical systems; they are deeply political. Decisions about what gets collected, what remains accessible, and what disappears are shaped by power, policy, and priorities.</p>
<p>The Data Rescue events of 2016–2017 brought together scientists, librarians, and civic tech communities to back up environmental datasets they feared could vanish under the Trump administration. At first glance, the movement looked like a technical project—downloading datasets, copying them to safer locations. But it was just as much an act of political resistance <span class="citation" data-cites="parisDatamirroringArchivalActivism2017">(Paris 2017)</span>.</p>
<p>Looking back, one of the most fascinating aspects of Data Rescue is that very little data actually disappeared. Yet the movement wasn’t a failure per se, even though most of the rescued data was not usable and the collection was far from complete <span class="citation" data-cites="lamdanLessonsDatarescueLimitations2017a">(Lamdan 2017)</span>. It revealed something crucial: it wasn’t just about saving data; it was about making government accountability visible <span class="citation" data-cites="dillonEnvironmentalDataJustice2017 dillonSituatingDataTrumpian2019">(Dillon et al. 2017, 2019)</span>. One theory might be that the fact that people felt the need to take matters into their own hands showed a loss of trust in official assurances represented by federal infrastructures.</p>
<p>Now, nearly a decade later, similar concerns are emerging. As the political landscape in the U.S. shifts once again. This time around,</p>
<p>I am currently speaking with people who were in one way or another involved in the first DataRescue events. Some of them have continued to monitor federal data policies and website changes over the years. Their work is a reminder that data loss isn’t always dramatic—sometimes, it’s a slow erosion of accessibility, funding cuts, or subtle changes to the language used in official reports.</p>
<p>If there’s one thing the past decade has taught us, it’s that data isn’t neutral and neither are the infrastructures they are connected to. Public data infrastructures are shaped by politics, and in turn, they shape what we know about the world. Understanding how these systems work—and how they can be protected—will be critical in the years ahead.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-CDCDatasetsUploaded" class="csl-entry">
<span>“<span>CDC</span> Datasets Uploaded Before <span>January</span> 28th, 2025 : <span>Centers</span> for <span>Disease Control</span> and <span>Prevention</span> : <span>Free Download</span>, <span>Borrow</span>, and <span>Streaming</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>Internet Archive</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://archive.org/details/20250128-cdc-datasets">https://archive.org/details/20250128-cdc-datasets</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-coxLookFederalHealth2025" class="csl-entry">
Cox, Cynthia, Matthew Rae, Jennifer Kates, Emma Wager, Jared Ortaliza, and Lindsey Dawson Published. 2025. <span>“A <span>Look</span> at <span>Federal Health Data Taken Offline</span>.”</span> <em>KFF</em>.
</div>
<div id="ref-currieBackupsFutureArchival2018" class="csl-entry">
Currie, Morgan E., and Britt S. Paris. 2018. <span>“Back-Ups for the Future: Archival Practices for Data Activism.”</span> <em>Archives and Manuscripts</em> 46 (2): 124–42. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/01576895.2018.1468273">https://doi.org/10.1080/01576895.2018.1468273</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-DataScreeningTools" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Data + <span>Screening Tools</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>Data + Screening Tools</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://screening-tools.com">https://screening-tools.com</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dillonSituatingDataTrumpian2019" class="csl-entry">
Dillon, Lindsey, Rebecca Lave, Becky Mansfield, Sara Wylie, Nicholas Shapiro, Anita Say Chan, and Michelle Murphy. 2019. <span>“Situating <span>Data</span> in a <span>Trumpian Era</span>: <span>The Environmental Data</span> and <span>Governance Initiative</span>.”</span> <em>Annals of the American Association of Geographers</em> 109 (2): 545–55. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/24694452.2018.1511410">https://doi.org/10.1080/24694452.2018.1511410</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dillonEnvironmentalDataJustice2017" class="csl-entry">
Dillon, Lindsey, Dawn Walker, Nicholas Shapiro, Vivian Underhill, Megan Martenyi, Sara Wylie, Rebecca Lave, Michelle Murphy, and Phil Brown. 2017. <span>“Environmental <span>Data Justice</span> and the <span>Trump Administration</span>: <span>Reflections</span> from the <span>Environmental Data</span> and <span>Governance Initiative</span>.”</span> <em>Environmental Justice</em> 10 (6): 186–92. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1089/env.2017.0020">https://doi.org/10.1089/env.2017.0020</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-edgiWhyEDGIArchiving2025" class="csl-entry">
EDGI. 2025. <span>“Why <span>EDGI</span> Is <span>Archiving Public Environmental Data</span>.”</span> <em>Environmental Data and Governance Initiative</em>. <a href="https://envirodatagov.org/why-edgi-is-archiving-public-environmental-data/">https://envirodatagov.org/why-edgi-is-archiving-public-environmental-data/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-EndTermWeb" class="csl-entry">
<span>“End of <span>Term Web Archive</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>End of Term Web Archive</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://eotarchive.org/">https://eotarchive.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-EnvironmentalDataGovernance" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Environmental <span>Data</span> &amp; <span>Governance Initiative</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>Environmental Data and Governance Initiative</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://envirodatagov.org/">https://envirodatagov.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-janzMaintainingAccessPublic2017" class="csl-entry">
Janz, Margaret Miller. 2017. <span>“Maintaining <span>Access</span> to <span>Public Data</span>: <span>Lessons</span> from <span>Data Refuge</span>.”</span> <em>Against the Grain</em> 29 (6). <a href="https://doi.org/10.7771/2380-176X.7875">https://doi.org/10.7771/2380-176X.7875</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-koeblerArchivistsWorkIdentify2025a" class="csl-entry">
Koebler, Jason. 2025. <span>“Archivists <span>Work</span> to <span>Identify</span> and <span>Save</span> the <span>Thousands</span> of <span>Datasets Disappearing From Data</span>.gov.”</span> <em>404 Media</em>. <a href="https://www.404media.co/archivists-work-to-identify-and-save-the-thousands-of-datasets-disappearing-from-data-gov/">https://www.404media.co/archivists-work-to-identify-and-save-the-thousands-of-datasets-disappearing-from-data-gov/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-lamdanLessonsDatarescueLimitations2017a" class="csl-entry">
Lamdan, Sarah. 2017. <span>“Lessons from <span>Datarescue</span>: <span>The Limitations</span> of <span>Grassroots Climate Change Data Preservation</span> and the <span>Need</span> for <span>Federal Records Law Reform Essay</span>.”</span> <em>University of Pennsylvania Law Review Online</em> 166: 231–48.
</div>
<div id="ref-parisDatamirroringArchivalActivism2017" class="csl-entry">
Paris, Britt. 2017. <span>“Data-Mirroring as Archival Activism.”</span> <em>Datapower Conference Proceedings</em>, 1.2.4–4. <a href="https://doi.org/10.22215/datapower.v2017i0.22">https://doi.org/10.22215/datapower.v2017i0.22</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rothfritzUnderstandingMistrustDistrust2024" class="csl-entry">
Rothfritz, Laura. 2024a. <span>“Understanding Mistrust and Distrust in Public Data Infrastructures.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10663566">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10663566</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rothfritzUnderstandingTrustDistrust2024" class="csl-entry">
———. 2024b. <span>“Understanding Trust and Distrust in Public Data Infrastructures as Socio-Technical Systems.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11142410">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11142410</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-singerThousandsUSGovernment2025a" class="csl-entry">
Singer, Ethan. 2025. <span>“Thousands of <span>U</span>.<span>S</span>. <span>Government Web Pages Have Been Taken Down Since Friday</span> - <span>The New York Times</span>.”</span> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/02/upshot/trump-government-websites-missing-pages.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/02/upshot/trump-government-websites-missing-pages.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-sunCDCRemovesGender2025" class="csl-entry">
Sun, Lena H., Dan Keating, and Fenit Nirappil. 2025. <span>“<span>CDC</span> Removes Gender, Equity References in Public Health Material.”</span> <em>Washington Post</em>, February.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2025,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura},
  title = {What Happens When Public Data Infrastructures Aren’t Save?
    {A} Look at Past and Current Developments in the {US}},
  date = {2025-02-05},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura. 2025. <span>“What Happens When Public Data
Infrastructures Aren’t Save? A Look at Past and Current Developments in
the US.”</span> February 5, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70">https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-What-happens-when-public-data-infrastructures-arent-save/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-What-happens-when-public-data-infrastructures-arent-save/datarescue.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Perspective on Future Infrastructure for Scholarly Blogs in Germany</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-10-perspective-on-future-infrastructure-on-scholarly-blogs-in-germany/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On December 6th, 2024, we hosted the first workshop of our project <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner_research_2024">(Ochsner and Pampel 2024)</span>, funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG). The aim of the workshop was to bring together scholarly bloggers and experts from information infrastructure institutions, so they could exchange experiences, wishes and challenges concerning scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>In the following, we give a brief overview of the workshop, the talks and discussions, and outline how we will continue our work following the results of the workshop. Following the welcome address, we presented the initial results of a survey of German scholarly blogs that we conducted as a part of the Infra Wiss Blogs project. Afterward, the workshop was enriched by multiple presentations around the topic of scholarly blogs and their long term accessibility.</p>
<p><a href="https://blogs.helmholtz.de/augenspiegel/author/henning/">Henning Krause</a> from the Helmholtz Association began with an overview of the Helmholtz Blogs, the blog portal of Germany’s largest research organization. He talked about challenges and opportunities with science communication, using blogs as an example.</p>
<p>This talk was followed by a presentation from Martin Fenner from <a href="https://front-matter.io/">Front Matter</a>, on the topic of long term accessibility of scholarly blogs and the the <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org/">Rogue Scholar blog archive</a>.</p>
<p>Lastly, these presentations were followed by two inputs from practitioners within the field by <a href="https://www.gesis.org/institut/ueber-uns/mitarbeitendenverzeichnis/person/Charmaine.Voigt">Charmaine Voigt</a> from GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences, and <a href="https://www.dnb.de/SharedDocs/Kontaktdaten/DE/wolderingBritta.html">Britta Woldering</a> from the German National Library. Charmaine Voigt presented the results of a survey on science blogs and podcasts at scientific institutions in Germany in the GESIS Wi⁴impact project. Britta Woldering introduced the work of the German National Library (DNB) in the field of web archiving and described the DNB’s approach to handling blogs for the permanent accessibility of digital content.</p>
<p>The available presentations of the speakers were published on Zenodo and can be found below:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Fenner, M. (2024, December 6). Ansätze zur Sicherung der dauerhaften Zugänglichkeit von Wissenschaftsblogs. Infra Wiss Blogs Vernetzungsworkshop 2024, Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060</a></p></li>
<li><p>Voigt, C., &amp; Kuhle, B. (2024, December 6). Wi4impact: Befragung von Produzierenden deutscher Wissenschaftsblogs (und -podcasts). Infra Wiss Blogs Vernetzungsworkshop 2024, Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474</a></p></li>
<li><p>Woldering, B. (2024, December 6). Webarchivierung an der deutschen Nationalbibliothek. Infra Wiss Blogs Vernetzungsworkshop 2024, Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>The presentations and the results of the survey of German scholarly blogs were then discussed by the workshop organizers, the participants, and the speakers. To structure the discussion, we prepared a set of questions on the topic, e.g.&nbsp;“How can bloggers, libraries and archives work together to create standardized metadata and procedures for long-term accessibility for academic blogs?”. The main topic of discussion was how scholarly bloggers and infrastructure institutions can work together, to ensure the long term access of scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>The following challenges were identified concerning the standardization of scholarly blogs and their long term accessibility:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Insufficient provision of metadata</li>
<li>Insufficient licensing information</li>
<li>Dynamic contents, such as pictures or videos, comments, link rot pose technical and legal challenges</li>
<li>Bloggers’ lack of knowledge about the technical and legal requirements to ensure long term accessibility</li>
<li>Blogs and other knowledge transfer and science communication activities are usually not adequately recognized in the scientific reputation system and the evaluation of research performance</li>
</ol>
<p>The following strategies to enhance long term accessibility of scholarly blogs were proposed during the discussion:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>(Re-)using standardized formats (such as XML or JSON) that are already being used by blogs for the long term archiving</li>
<li>Including licensing information into metadata. Recommended for use is the CC BY license</li>
<li>Legal challenges of archiving comments could be solved through legal notice</li>
<li>Libraries as educational institutions can help educate bloggers on blog requirements</li>
<li>Universities and other research performing organizations can support bloggers through offering platforms or better maintaining existing ones and by recognizing blogging as part of knowledge transfer and science communication</li>
</ol>
<p>The discussion illustrated the diversity of the stakeholders. All participants agreed that there is a further need for stronger networking and collaboration on the topic. The participants also emphasized the need for support from universities and research institutions, as well as funding bodies, for their blogging researchers.</p>
<p>The workshop enabled us to bring together diverse perspectives from people involved in blogs, infrastructure, and science communication. We learned a lot and received numerous suggestions for the project. We thank all the speakers and participants for their contributions and the open discussions.</p>
<p>Building on the results of the survey of German blogs, we will start conducting in-depth interviews with scholarly bloggers to investigate the infrastructural challenges of scholarly blogs and possible solutions.</p>
<p>Additionally, We are currently working on publishing the results of our survey on German scholarly blogs. We will communicate the publication of the article through our <a href="https://www.listserv.dfn.de/sympa/info/infra-wiss-blogs">mailing list</a>. The subscription is possible <a href="https://www.listserv.dfn.de/sympa/info/infra-wiss-blogs">here</a>.</p>
<p>A German version of this blog post is available on the blog dedicated to the Infra Wiss Blog project and can be found <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-fenner_ansatze_2024" class="csl-entry">
Fenner, Martin. 2024. <span>“Ansätze Zur <span>Sicherung</span> Der Dauerhaften <span>Zugänglichkeit</span> von <span>Wissenschaftsblogs</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ochsner_research_2024" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“Research <span>Group</span> <span>Information</span> <span>Management</span> @ <span>Humboldt</span>-<span>Universität</span> Zu <span>Berlin</span> - <span>Project</span> Launch: <span>Infra</span> <span>Wiss</span> <span>Blogs</span> - <span>Ensuring</span> <span>Permanent</span> <span>Access</span> to <span>Scholarly</span> <span>Blogs</span>.”</span> <a href="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-05-project-launch-infra-wiss-blogs/Index.html">https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-05-project-launch-infra-wiss-blogs/Index.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-voigt_wiimpact_2024" class="csl-entry">
Voigt, Charmaine, and Birte Kuhle. 2024. <span>“Wi⁴impact: <span>Befragung</span> von <span>Produzierenden</span> Deutscher <span>Wissenschaftsblogs</span> (Und -Podcasts).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-woldering_webarchivierung_2024" class="csl-entry">
Woldering, Britta. 2024. <span>“Webarchivierung an Der Deutschen <span>Nationalbibliothek</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Höfting, Jonas and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Perspective on {Future} {Infrastructure} for {Scholarly}
    {Blogs} in {Germany}},
  date = {2025-01-10},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/4fc41-6n753},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, Jonas Höfting, and Heinz Pampel. 2025.
<span>“Perspective on Future Infrastructure for Scholarly Blogs in
Germany.”</span> January 10, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/4fc41-6n753">https://doi.org/10.59350/4fc41-6n753</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-10-perspective-on-future-infrastructure-on-scholarly-blogs-in-germany/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-10-perspective-on-future-infrastructure-on-scholarly-blogs-in-germany/IMG_5273.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Workshop ‘The state and prospects of open access reporting’ at Open-Access-Tage</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-09-workshop-the-state-and-prospects-of-open-access-reporting/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>At last year’s Open-Access-Tage, <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en/">OA Datenpraxis</a> held a workshop together with the <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/en/zb/open-science/open-access/open-access-monitor-1">Open Access Monitor</a> at Forschungszentrum Jülich as well as the state-wide Open Access initiatives of Berlin (<a href="https://www.open-access-berlin.de">Open Access Büro Berlin</a>) and Brandenburg (<a href="https://open-access-brandenburg.de/en/">Vernetzungs- und Kompetenzstelle Open Access Brandenburg</a>). The workshop ‘The state and prospects of open access reporting’ outlined different approaches - qualitative and quantitative - to Open Access reporting and provided insights into examples for reporting procedures. Participants discussed opportunities and challenges of these reporting approaches in small groups before the results were briefly presented in plenary. The presentation slides have been published on Zenodo.</p>
<p>Barbers, I., Kindling, M., Stadler, H., Strecker, D., Kaden, B., Mittermaier, B., &amp; Pampel, H. (2024, September 10). Stand und Perspektive des Open-Access-Reportings. Open-Access-Tage 2024, Köln. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942</a></p>
<p>Recently, a new report documenting a workshop held by OA Datenpraxis and <a href="">Transform2Open</a> at the 25th annual meeting of DINI (Deutsche Initiative für Netzwerkinformation e. V.) was published. Participants discussed how the costs of providing access to scientific information can be made more transparent.</p>
<p>Ferguson, L. M., Pampel, H., Strecker, D., &amp; Meistring, M. (2025). Transparenz in der Wissenschaft: Strategien für offene Informationsversorgung. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423</a></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-barbers_stand_2024" class="csl-entry">
Barbers, Irene, Maxi Kindling, Heike Stadler, and Dorothea Strecker. 2024. <span>“Stand Und <span>Perspektive</span> Des <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Reportings</span>.”</span> Köln. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ferguson_transparenz_2025" class="csl-entry">
Ferguson, Lea Maria, Heinz Pampel, Dorothea Strecker, and Marcel Meistring. 2025. <span>“Transparenz in Der <span>Wissenschaft</span>: <span>Strategien</span> Für Offene <span>Informationsversorgung</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Workshop “{The} State and Prospects of Open Access Reporting”
    at {Open-Access-Tage}},
  date = {2025-01-09},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/r84e3-7s790},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Workshop <span>‘The
State and Prospects of Open Access Reporting’</span> at
Open-Access-Tage.”</span> January 9, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/r84e3-7s790">https://doi.org/10.59350/r84e3-7s790</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-09-workshop-the-state-and-prospects-of-open-access-reporting/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-09-workshop-the-state-and-prospects-of-open-access-reporting/OAT.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="80" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Open Access Award from Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin for Our Team!</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-12-04-Open-Access-Award-from-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-for-Our-Team/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are thrilled to announce that our group at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science has been honored with the <a href="https://www.ub.hu-berlin.de/de/forschen-publizieren/open-access/preis">Open Access Award 2024</a> of Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. This recognition, valued at €5,000, underscores our commitment to advancing Open Access in research, education, and knowledge transfer.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-12-04-Open-Access-Award-from-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-for-Our-Team/Open_Access_Award.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The Open Access Award is presented annually by the university and its library to recognize outstanding contributions to the promotion of Open Access. It serves both as an acknowledgment of past achievements and as a motivation to continue driving Open Science initiatives.</p>
<p>Official news about the award can be found on the university library’s <a href="https://blogs.hu-berlin.de/wir_bewegen_buecher/2024/11/29/der-open-access-preis-der-hu-geht-2024-an-den-lehrstuhl-information-management-des-ibi/">website</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="riesenweber_open-access-preis_nodate">(Riesenweber n.d.)</span>.</p>
<p>This award highlights the importance of teamwork and collaboration in advancing Open Science research. A heartfelt thank you to our incredible <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/teaminfomanagement">team</a>—Jonas Höfting, Christopher Onzie Khamis, Pia Kretschmar (currently at CERN), Max Liebel, Catharina Ochsner, Laura Rothfritz, Dorothea Strecker, and Marcel Wrzesinski. We sincerely thank Humboldt-Universität for the festive award ceremony, held as part of the <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/de/ueberblick/menschen/ehrungen/humboldtpreis/standardseite">Humboldt-Preis</a> presentation, and for this honor. We look forward to advancing Open Science together.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-riesenweber_open-access-preis_nodate" class="csl-entry">
Riesenweber, Christina. n.d. <span>“Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Preis</span> Der <span>HU</span> Geht 2024 an Den <span>Lehrstuhl</span> <span>Information</span> <span>Management</span> Des <span>IBI</span> <span></span> <span>UB</span> <span>Blog</span>.”</span> <em>UB Blog</em>. Accessed November 29, 2024. <a href="https://blogs.hu-berlin.de/wir_bewegen_buecher/2024/11/29/der-open-access-preis-der-hu-geht-2024-an-den-lehrstuhl-information-management-des-ibi/">https://blogs.hu-berlin.de/wir_bewegen_buecher/2024/11/29/der-open-access-preis-der-hu-geht-2024-an-den-lehrstuhl-information-management-des-ibi/</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Open {Access} {Award} from {Humboldt-Universität} Zu {Berlin}
    for {Our} {Team!}},
  date = {2024-12-04},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/gsmp2-vqp56},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2024. <span>“Open Access Award from Humboldt-Universität
Zu Berlin for Our Team!”</span> December 4, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/gsmp2-vqp56">https://doi.org/10.59350/gsmp2-vqp56</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-12-04-Open-Access-Award-from-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-for-Our-Team/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-12-04-Open-Access-Award-from-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-for-Our-Team/Open_Access_Award.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New preprint on Transformative Agreements</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-11-18-New-Preprint-on-Transformative-Agreements/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In recent years, <a href="https://esac-initiative.org/about/transformative-agreements/">transformative agreements</a> (TAs) have become a go-to strategy for publishers and research performing organizations aiming to open up access to research <span class="citation" data-cites="farleyTransformativeAgreementsSix2021">(Farley et al. 2021)</span>. These agreements promise to bridge traditional subscription-based journal models to an Open Access (OA) future <span class="citation" data-cites="borregoTransformativeAgreementsThey2021">(Borrego, Anglada, and Abadal 2021)</span>. But are they delivering on that promise? In this new pre-print, my colleagues <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/wbschmal">W. Benedikt Schmal</a>, <a href="https://pulse49.com/about-ulrich-herb/">Ulrich Herb</a> and I did a thorough analysis of 1,075 TAs in order to get the most complete picture possible with the available data.</p>
<p>Rothfritz, L., Schmal, W. B., &amp; Herb, U. (2024). Trapped in Transformative Agreements? A Multifaceted Analysis of &gt;1,000 Contracts. arXiv. <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/ARXIV.2409.20224" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.48550/ARXIV.2409.20224</a></p>
<section id="what-we-did-a-blend-of-data-crunching-and-thematic-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-did-a-blend-of-data-crunching-and-thematic-analysis">What We Did: A Blend of Data Crunching and Thematic Analysis</h3>
<p>To understand TAs better, we gathered data from a unique source: the <a href="https://esac-initiative.org/">ESAC Initiative</a>, which tracks over 1,000 transformative agreements. This data, alongside additional contract details we scraped, allowed us to go beyond basic summaries. We analyzed both numbers and narratives, mixing quantitative approaches like regression analysis with qualitative coding of free-text answers collected by ESAC through their <a href="https://esac-initiative.org/about/transformative-agreements/share/">registry form</a>. This dual approach helped us capture not only the frequency and size of agreements but also the subjective experiences libraries shared.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-findings-are-libraries-trapped" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-findings-are-libraries-trapped">Key Findings: Are Libraries Trapped?</h3>
<p>One of our core findings is that TAs may not just be a stepping stone toward full OA but could be trapping libraries in hybrid models indefinitely. Here’s what stood out:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Dominance of Big Publishers: We found that a small number of publishers, mainly Elsevier, Springer Nature, and Wiley, dominate these agreements. These “Big 3” often secure longer contracts with more favorable terms for themselves, locking libraries into longer commitments and substantial costs.</p></li>
<li><p>Rising Costs, Limited Flexibility: While TAs have led to more OA articles, they don’t always reduce costs for libraries. In fact, we discovered that the larger the initial TA contract, the more likely it is to be renewed, creating a cycle of dependency. Libraries often face increased administrative burdens and costs without the savings they expected.</p></li>
<li><p>Capped vs.&nbsp;Uncapped Contracts: Contracts come in two flavors—capped (with a limit on the number of OA articles) and uncapped. Uncapped contracts are generally preferred, as they reduce the risk of libraries exceeding their article limit and facing additional charges. However, even uncapped contracts often exclude fully OA journals, limiting the growth of the OA movement.</p></li>
<li><p>Workflow Wins and Woes: One bright spot is that many libraries reported improvements in their workflows under TAs, especially where automated tools like CCC RightsLink and others and real-time dashboards were used. Yet, issues remain—many libraries still struggle with complex, manual workflows and limited monitoring capabilities.</p></li>
<li><p>Mixed Feelings on Sustainability: Libraries are split on the sustainability of TAs. While some view them as a positive, affordable transition tool, others worry about long-term financial strain, especially as publishers maintain their market power and high fees.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts-a-double-edged-sword" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts-a-double-edged-sword">Final Thoughts: A Double-Edged Sword?</h3>
<p>Our analysis suggests that while TAs have increased the number of OA articles, they might also be cementing the dominance of large publishers and creating financial traps for libraries. Rather than acting as a bridge to a fully OA landscape, TAs may become a permanent fixture, with academic institutions continually caught in a cycle of payments and negotiations <span class="citation" data-cites="fenterItNotTransformation2022 jahnHowOpenAre2024 schmalHowTransformativeAre2024">(Fenter 2022; Jahn 2024; Schmal 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>It will be interesting to see how the scientific community and libraries, in their negotiations with publishers, achieve progress in contract development and how these will fit into the future Open Access mix, including strategies for community-led publishing. A particularly noteworthy case is Sweden, where the Bibsam Consortium <a href="https://www.su.se/english/news/open-access-need-to-move-away-from-transformative-agreements-1.683787">recommends to no longer sign any TAs for hybrid journals</a>.</p>
<p>Replication code, scripts, and data used for this study are publicly available on Zenodo: <a href="[https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.13453629">https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.13453629</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-borregoTransformativeAgreementsThey2021" class="csl-entry">
Borrego, Ángel, Lluís Anglada, and Ernest Abadal. 2021. <span>“Transformative Agreements: <span>Do</span> They Pave the Way to Open Access?”</span> <em>Learned Publishing</em> 34 (2): 216–32. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/leap.1347">https://doi.org/10.1002/leap.1347</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-farleyTransformativeAgreementsSix2021" class="csl-entry">
Farley, Ashley, Allison Langham-Putrow, Elisabeth Shook, Leila Belle Sterman, and Megan Wacha. 2021. <span>“Transformative Agreements: <span>Six</span> Myths, Busted.”</span> <em>College &amp; Research Libraries News</em>, July. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5860/crln.82.7.298">https://doi.org/10.5860/crln.82.7.298</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-fenterItNotTransformation2022" class="csl-entry">
Fenter, Frederick. 2022. <span>“It Is Not Transformation If Nothing Changes.”</span> Frontiers.
</div>
<div id="ref-jahnHowOpenAre2024" class="csl-entry">
Jahn, Najko. 2024. <span>“How Open Are Hybrid Journals Included in Transformative Agreements?”</span> arXiv. <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2402.18255">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2402.18255</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-schmalHowTransformativeAre2024" class="csl-entry">
Schmal, W. Benedikt. 2024. <span>“How Transformative Are Transformative Agreements? <span>Evidence</span> from <span>Germany</span> Across Disciplines.”</span> <em>Scientometrics</em> 129 (3): 1863–89. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192-024-04955-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192-024-04955-y</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2024,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura},
  title = {New Preprint on {Transformative} {Agreements}},
  date = {2024-11-18},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/fe9s4-8a179},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura. 2024. <span>“New Preprint on Transformative
Agreements.”</span> November 18, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/fe9s4-8a179">https://doi.org/10.59350/fe9s4-8a179</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-11-18-New-Preprint-on-Transformative-Agreements/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-11-18-New-Preprint-on-Transformative-Agreements/screenshot.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="107" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Interview on Deutschlandfunk about the Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-11-18-Interview-on-Deutschlandfunk-about-the-Wayback-Machine-of-the-Internet-Archive/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently had the opportunity to speak on <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunk.de/computer-und-kommunikation-9-11-2024-komplette-sendung-dlf-3c985bf4-100.html">Deutschlandfunk</a> about the Wayback Machine from the Internet Archive. The occasion was the recent cyberattack on the Internet Archive <span class="citation" data-cites="schraer_cyber_2023">(Schräer 2023)</span>. The Wayback Machine plays a crucial role in preserving websites and providing access to our digital past—for researchers, journalists, and the interested public alike.</p>
<p>The preservation of other types of digital information is also important, for example the data researchers base their findings on. Together with colleagues, our team at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, examined the ongoing operation of research data repositories. These repositories are of great importance to the scientific community, as they preserve data and facilitate data exchange among researchers. In our sample of 3,000 research data repositories, we found last year that repository shutdowns are not uncommon: 6% of the repositories we examined were no longer online at the time of our study <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_disappearing_2023">(Strecker et al. 2023)</span>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-11-18-Interview-on-Deutschlandfunk-about-the-Wayback-Machine-of-the-Internet-Archive/wayback-machine.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>These findings, and the recent incident threatening the Wayback Machine, show that maintaining our digital heritage requires robust information infrastructures. Information Science research can contribute towards this goal by investigating threats to the availability of information resources.</p>
<p>As part of the <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> project funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG), we are currently working on assessing and ensuring the permanent accessibility of scholarly blogs <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_kooperative_2024 ochsner_infra_2024">(Pampel and Rothfritz 2024; Ochsner 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>Another part of the <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunk.de/computer-und-kommunikation-9-11-2024-komplette-sendung-dlf-3c985bf4-100.html">Deutschlandfunk program</a> discusses the current copyright proceedings surrounding the Internet Archive. Enjoy listening!</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-ochsner_infra_2024" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina. 2024. <span>“Infra <span>Wiss</span> <span>Blogs</span>: <span>Projektvorstellung</span>.”</span> Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12799719">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12799719</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel_kooperative_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, and Laura Rothfritz. 2024. <span>“Kooperative <span>Informationsinfrastruktur</span> Für Wissenschaftliche <span>Blogs</span> (<span>Infra</span> <span>Wiss</span> <span>Blogs</span>),”</span> August. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-schraer_cyber_2023" class="csl-entry">
Schräer, Frank. 2023. <span>“Cyber Attack on <span>Internet</span> <span>Archive</span> Apparently Carried Out by <span>Russian</span> Hackers <span></span> Heise Online.”</span> <em>Heise.de</em>, October. <a href="https://www.heise.de/en/news/Cyber-attack-on-Internet-Archive-apparently-carried-out-by-Russian-hackers-9983840.html">https://www.heise.de/en/news/Cyber-attack-on-Internet-Archive-apparently-carried-out-by-Russian-hackers-9983840.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_disappearing_2023" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea, Heinz Pampel, Rouven Schabinger, and Nina Leonie Weisweiler. 2023. <span>“Disappearing Repositories: <span>Taking</span> an Infrastructure Perspective on the Long-Term Availability of Research Data.”</span> <em>Quantitative Science Studies</em> 4 (4): 1–18. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/qss_a_00277">https://doi.org/10.1162/qss_a_00277</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Interview on {Deutschlandfunk} about the {Wayback} {Machine}
    of the {Internet} {Archive}},
  date = {2024-11-17},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/b8n21-pda75},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2024. <span>“Interview on Deutschlandfunk about the
Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive.”</span> November 17, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/b8n21-pda75">https://doi.org/10.59350/b8n21-pda75</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-11-18-Interview-on-Deutschlandfunk-about-the-Wayback-Machine-of-the-Internet-Archive/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-11-18-Interview-on-Deutschlandfunk-about-the-Wayback-Machine-of-the-Internet-Archive/wayback-machine.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Our Contribution to Open Access Week 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-21-Our-Contribution-to-Open-Acces-Week-2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week marks the fifteenth annual International <a href="https://www.openaccessweek.org/">Open Access Week</a>. Since 2010, the week has provided a platform to discuss the state and challenges of open access to scientific knowledge. While the early years focused on access to scientific articles <span class="citation" data-cites="noauthor_open_2024">(<span>“Open <span>Access</span> <span>Week</span>”</span> 2024)</span>, this year’s activities increasingly address other aspects of Open Science.</p>
<p>Universities, research labs, and libraries worldwide are participating in the week with various activities. For Germany, a list of events can be found on the website <a href="https://open-access.network/services/news/artikel/open-access-week-2024">open-access.network</a>. Since 2012, a theme has been chosen for the week each year. This year’s theme is “Community over Commercialization” <span class="citation" data-cites="open_access_week_theme_nodate">(Week n.d.)</span>.</p>
<p>Our research group is also participating in this year’s Open Access Week. On Monday, October 21, 2024, from 2:00 PM to 3:30 PM (CET), we are organizing a panel in collaboration with the <a href="https://www.open-access-berlin.de/">Open-Access-Büro Berlin</a> titled “Open Access Monitoring – Opportunities and Challenges for Open Science.” The event will be held online in German. Registration is available on the Open-Access-Büro Berlin <a href="https://blogs.fu-berlin.de/open-access-berlin/2024/08/02/quo-vadis-4-auftaktveranstaltung/">website</a>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-21-Our-Contribution-to-Open-Acces-Week-2024/oaweek2024.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Abstract <span class="citation" data-cites="kindling_21_2024">(Kindling and Pampel 2024, translation by me)</span></p>
<p>To track the progress of the transformation to Open Access, indicators such as publication numbers or publication costs are often considered. Open data plays a key role in this. With <a href="https://openalex.org/">OpenAlex</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="priem_openalex_2022">(Priem, Piwowar, and Orr 2022)</span> and the accompanying <a href="https://barcelona-declaration.org/">Barcelona Declaration on Open Research Information</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="noauthor_barcelona_nodate">(<span>“Barcelona <span>Declaration</span> on <span>Open</span> <span>Research</span> <span>Information</span>”</span> n.d.)</span>, the Open Access community is well on its way to ensuring that monitoring is not left solely to commercial providers. At the same time, new challenges arise in monitoring, such as considering more advanced principles of Open Science in the context of community-led Open Access publishing or including other publication formats and practices. These questions include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>How can we track the growing number of community-led initiatives and their publication and funding models without simply counting the quantitative output of journals and articles?</p></li>
<li><p>How can institutions make their efforts to build open publication infrastructures more visible?</p></li>
<li><p>How can the implementation of strategies be made visible not only in terms of outcomes at a given point in time but also in terms of process?</p></li>
<li><p>How much influence do the things we measure and define have on the path we take in the Open Access transformation?</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I look forward to moderating the discussions with Irene Barbers (Forschungszentrum Jülich), Najko Jahn (University of Göttingen), Jochen Johannsen (RWTH Aachen), and Maxi Kindling (Open-Access-Büro Berlin).</p>
<p>The event is also part of the <a href="URL">“Quo Vadis Open Science in Berlin and Brandenburg 2024/25”</a> series, which addresses the state and perspectives of Open Science in Berlin and Brandenburg.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-noauthor_barcelona_nodate" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Barcelona <span>Declaration</span> on <span>Open</span> <span>Research</span> <span>Information</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>Barcelona Declaration on Open Research Information</em>. Accessed October 17, 2024. <a href="https://barcelona-declaration.org/">https://barcelona-declaration.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-kindling_21_2024" class="csl-entry">
Kindling, Maxi, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“21. <span>Oktober</span> 2024: <span>Open</span> <span>Access</span> <span>Monitoring</span> – <span>Chancen</span> Und <span>Herausforderungen</span> Für Die Offene <span>Wissenschaft</span> (<span>Auftaktveranstaltung</span> in Der <span>Reihe</span> „<span>Quo</span> Vadis Offene <span>Wissenschaft</span> in <span>Berlin</span> Und <span>Brandenburg</span>“) – <span>Open</span> <span>Access</span> <span>Blog</span> <span>Berlin</span>.”</span> <a href="https://blogs.fu-berlin.de/open-access-berlin/2024/08/02/quo-vadis-4-auftaktveranstaltung/">https://blogs.fu-berlin.de/open-access-berlin/2024/08/02/quo-vadis-4-auftaktveranstaltung/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-noauthor_open_2024" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Open <span>Access</span> <span>Week</span>.”</span> 2024. <em>Wikipedia</em>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Open_Access_Week&amp;oldid=1251639261">https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Open_Access_Week&amp;oldid=1251639261</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-priem_openalex_2022" class="csl-entry">
Priem, Jason, Heather Piwowar, and Richard Orr. 2022. <span>“<span>OpenAlex</span>: <span>A</span> Fully-Open Index of Scholarly Works, Authors, Venues, Institutions, and Concepts.”</span> arXiv. <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2205.01833">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2205.01833</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-open_access_week_theme_nodate" class="csl-entry">
Week, Open Access. n.d. <span>“Theme for <span>Open</span> <span>Access</span> <span>Week</span> 2024 <span>Continues</span> <span>Call</span> to <span>Put</span> <span>‘<span>Community</span> over <span>Commercialization</span>’</span>.”</span> Accessed October 17, 2024. <a href="https://www.openaccessweek.org/theme/en">https://www.openaccessweek.org/theme/en</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Our {Contribution} to {Open} {Access} {Week} 2024},
  date = {2024-10-21},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/9n4et-tkf55},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2024. <span>“Our Contribution to Open Access Week
2024.”</span> October 21, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/9n4et-tkf55">https://doi.org/10.59350/9n4et-tkf55</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-21-Our-Contribution-to-Open-Acces-Week-2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-21-Our-Contribution-to-Open-Acces-Week-2024/oaweek2024.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Blogs as a blueprint for community-led Open Access publishing</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Evin Dalkilic</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martin Fenner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mareike König</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ulrike Stockhausen</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-16-blogs-as-blueprint-for-community-led-OA-publishing/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Scholarly blogs can disseminate current research content quickly and beyond their own specialist community and put it up for discussion. Open communication without paywalls increases the visibility of scholarly research. Researchers as well as information infrastructure and cultural institutions therefore have an interest in supporting scholarly blogs as an Open Access publication format. But what can the individual actors do to strengthen and further develop scholarly blogs and how do scholarly blogs fit into current discussions about the science-led development of the Open Access transformation <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_thesen_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span>?</p>
<p>During the workshop ‘Blogs as a blueprint for community-led Open Access publishing’ which took place as a part of the Open-Access-Tage 2024, the role of blogs within science communication was discussed using three statements <span class="citation" data-cites="noauthor_open-access-tage_nodate">(<span>“Open-<span>Access</span>-<span>Tage</span>: <span>Mittwoch</span>, 11.09.2024”</span> n.d.)</span>.</p>
<p>The workshop was organized and moderated by Evin Dalkilic from <a href="https://verfassungsblog.de/">Verfassungsblog</a>, Martin Fenner from <a href="https://front-matter.io/">Front Matter</a>, Mareike König from the <a href="https://www.dhi-paris.fr/home.html">German historical Institute Paris</a>, Catharina Ochsner from the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de">Berlin School of Library and Information Science</a> at the <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/de">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a> , Heinz Pampel, also from Berlin School of Library and Information Science as well as the <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> and Ulrike Stockhausen from the <a href="https://www.maxweberstiftung.de/startseite.html">Max Weber Foundation</a> / <a href="https://de.hypotheses.org/">de.hypotheses</a>. The workshop was aimed at scientists, as well as information and publication professionals. The aims of the workshop were: to create a deeper understanding of the importance of scholarly blogs as an instrument of scholarly and science communication, to strengthen the recognition of their contribution to an open and sustainable research culture, and to identify needs for the further development of community-led open access publication infrastructures, based on the experiences of the participants <span class="citation" data-cites="noauthor_open-access-tage_nodate">(<span>“Open-<span>Access</span>-<span>Tage</span>: <span>Mittwoch</span>, 11.09.2024”</span> n.d.)</span>.</p>
<p>Together with the participants, statements on the following three topics were discussed: (1) workflow-related basic services, (2) networking services and (3) reputation management of scholarly blogs.</p>
<section id="discussion-1-workflow-related-basic-services-statement" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion-1-workflow-related-basic-services-statement">Discussion 1: Workflow-related basic services Statement:</h3>
<p>“Scholarly blogs must provide the same basic services as other forms of scientific publication: including PID assignment with relevant metadata, indexing in relevant catalogs, provision of full texts in various formats and long-term archiving.”</p>
<p>A central topic in the discussion on thesis 1 was the question of the definition of scholarly blogs: What formats and content characterize ‘scholarly blogs’? Which components should be archived in the long term? This also raises the question of whether authors are interested in permanent availability. Since the role of blogs varies greatly depending on discipline, bloggers also have different requirements for their archiving. The format also raises the question of whether discussions and comments, which are important additions to the blog posts, should and can be archived. The participants emphasized that the responsibility for making blogs and their content findable, visible and accessible in the long term lies not only with the bloggers, but also with information infrastructure institutions.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussion-2-networking-services" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion-2-networking-services">Discussion 2: Networking services</h3>
<p>Statement: “Scholarly blogs are living networks and show research at its best: open, transparent, serious.”</p>
<p>Once again, the participants discussed issues relating to the definition and function of scholarly blogs and the quality assurance of content, as scholarly blogs are used for very different purposes and with different requirements - while some have their own editorial boards, others focus more on popular science communication. In the discussion, it became clear that quality assurance on scholarly blogs can be made possible primarily through openness and transparency (e.g.&nbsp;through versioning and comments). The connection of many blogs to research institutes or third-party funded projects also creates transparency and quality assurance. The possibility of low-threshold commenting and discussing content also contributes significantly to quality assurance (keyword: open peer review).</p>
<p>With regard to the quality assurance of scholarly blogs in comparison to the traditional scholarly publication landscape, the concern was also expressed that traditional publishing structures - such as gatekeeping by editorial offices and publishers- could be adopted in the blog landscape, although blogs should offer a more open format for scientific communication.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussion-3-reputation-management" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion-3-reputation-management">Discussion 3: Reputation management</h3>
<p>Statement: “Science blogs as a low-threshold, genuinely freely accessible and digital publication format are particularly suitable for reputation building.”</p>
<p>Questions of quality assurance, trustworthiness and scientific rigor were also discussed as part of the third statement. However, the answers to these questions also depend on the blog’s target audience. Should the interested public or the scientific community be addressed? The primary target audience has a decisive influence on how research is communicated and from whom recognition and reputation are expected. It was also observed that the reputation of blog posts depends on the respective blog and their discipline. Open peer reviews, e.g.&nbsp;through comment columns, were mentioned as a means of quality assurance, but consideration was also given to orienting oneself on existing quality assurance procedures for journals or other journalistic outlets. At the same time, blogs also offer the opportunity to break away from traditional publishers and establish themselves as an independent, academic publication format. In particular, blogs make it possible to develop and test new ideas. They often serve as a starting point for more extensive publications such as journal articles - which then also incorporate the discussions on the blog.</p>
<p>Conclusion Scholarly blogs offer a diverse format for presenting and discussing scientific ideas and research results at an early stage, flexibly and with a low threshold. They can serve as an independent publication platform for scholarly and science communication. Although quality and reputation can vary depending on the discipline and blog, scholarly blogs have the potential to establish themselves as a serious, open and transparent publication medium. Quality assurance, archiving and recognition represent a challenge that differs from traditional publications. In addition, very fundamental questions arise, such as the definition of scholarly blogs, i.e.&nbsp;their formal, technical and content requirements, or their function as a medium of science communication.</p>
<p>Updates and further information on the Infra Wiss Blog can be found on the Project Website On December 06, 2024, the project team at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science will organize a networking workshop in Berlin at the Einstein Center Digital Future (ECDF) in Berlin. The event will be held in German. Registration is possible here. We look forward to further discussions on the topic.</p>
<p>Further information about the research and teaching group, Information Management, at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science can be found on the official group <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-noauthor_open-access-tage_nodate" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Open-<span>Access</span>-<span>Tage</span>: <span>Mittwoch</span>, 11.09.2024.”</span> n.d. Accessed September 23, 2024. <a href="https://open-access-tage.de/open-access-tage-2024-koeln/koeln/programm/mittwoch-11092024">https://open-access-tage.de/open-access-tage-2024-koeln/koeln/programm/mittwoch-11092024</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel_thesen_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Margo Bargheer, Roland Bertelmann, Ben Kaden, Maxi Kindling, Dagmar Schobert, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2024. <span>“Thesen Zur <span>Zukunft</span> Des Wissenschaftsgeleiteten <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Publizierens</span> – <span>Entwicklung</span> Und <span>Diskussion</span> in Einem Partizipativen <span>Prozess</span>.”</span> <em>Bibliothek Forschung Und Praxis</em> 48 (2): 322–33. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/bfp-2024-0027">https://doi.org/10.1515/bfp-2024-0027</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2024,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Pampel, Heinz and Dalkilic, Evin and
    Fenner, Martin and König, Mareike and Stockhausen, Ulrike},
  title = {Blogs as a Blueprint for Community-Led {Open} {Access}
    Publishing},
  date = {2024-10-17},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/b971b-ek551},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, Heinz Pampel, Evin Dalkilic, Martin Fenner, Mareike
König, and Ulrike Stockhausen. 2024. <span>“Blogs as a Blueprint for
Community-Led Open Access Publishing.”</span> October 17, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/b971b-ek551">https://doi.org/10.59350/b971b-ek551</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-16-blogs-as-blueprint-for-community-led-OA-publishing/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-16-blogs-as-blueprint-for-community-led-OA-publishing/OAT.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="80" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Interview on Shadow Libraries on Deutschlandfunk</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-17-Interview-on-Shadow-Libraries-on-Deutschlandfunk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the latest episode of <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/breitband-100.html">“Breitband”</a> on Deutschlandfunk Kultur, there is an interview with <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/institut/personen/strecker">Dorothea Strecker</a> from our research group at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science on shadow libraries <span class="citation" data-cites="belanger_pirate_2024">(Belanger 2024)</span>. The occasion for the interview was the lawsuit for damages against LibGen in the United States.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-17-Interview-on-Shadow-Libraries-on-Deutschlandfunk/schattenbibliotheken.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Here’s the linkt to the Interview: <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/libgen-schattenbibliothek-ebook-piraterie-100.html">“LibGen: Shadow Libraries and eBook Piracy”</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="deutschlandfunkkulturde_libgen-urteil_2024">(deutschlandfunkkultur.de 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>Further information about our research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-belanger_pirate_2024" class="csl-entry">
Belanger, Ashley. 2024. <span>“Pirate Library Must Pay Publishers $<span>30M</span>, but No One Knows Who Runs It.”</span> <em>Ars Technica</em>. <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/09/pirate-library-must-pay-publishers-30m-but-no-one-knows-who-runs-it/">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/09/pirate-library-must-pay-publishers-30m-but-no-one-knows-who-runs-it/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-deutschlandfunkkulturde_libgen-urteil_2024" class="csl-entry">
deutschlandfunkkultur.de. 2024. <span>“<span>LibGen</span>-<span>Urteil</span>: <span>E</span>-<span>Book</span>-<span>Piraterie</span> Am <span>Ende</span>?”</span> <em>Deutschlandfunk Kultur</em>. <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/libgen-schattenbibliothek-ebook-piraterie-100.html">https://www.deutschlandfunkkultur.de/libgen-schattenbibliothek-ebook-piraterie-100.html</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Interview on {Shadow} {Libraries} on {Deutschlandfunk}},
  date = {2024-10-17},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/66e4r-zd174},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2024. <span>“Interview on Shadow Libraries on
Deutschlandfunk.”</span> October 17, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/66e4r-zd174">https://doi.org/10.59350/66e4r-zd174</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-17-Interview-on-Shadow-Libraries-on-Deutschlandfunk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-17-Interview-on-Shadow-Libraries-on-Deutschlandfunk/schattenbibliotheken.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Recommendations on Regulations for Artificial Intelligence in License Agreements Published</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-17-Recommendations-on-Regulations-for-Artifical-Intelligence-in-License-Agreements-Published/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Together with Christian Agi, Michael Beurskens, Marion von Francken, Judith Ludwig, and Bernhard Mittermaier, I have been working on recommendations for the inclusion of artificial intelligence in license agreements with publishers over the past few months. As part of the Task Force “<a href="https://www.allianzschwerpunkt-digitalitaet.de/2024/10/02/ubersetzung-arrangements-on-artificial-intelligence-in-licence-agreements-recommendations-for-action-of-september-2024-veroffentlicht/">Regulations on Artificial Intelligence in License Agreements</a>,” within the focus area “<a href="https://www.allianzschwerpunkt-digitalitaet.de">Digitalization in Science”</a> of the Alliance of German Science Organizations <span class="citation" data-cites="bertelmann_schwerpunkt_2023">(Bertelmann et al. 2023)</span>, we addressed legal frameworks concerning permissions and prohibitions related to Text and Data Mining (TDM) and Artificial Intelligence (AI) under German law. Our work has led to recommendations for contract design. The recommendations are primarily intended for those negotiating license agreements with publishing service providers and those working with these contracts in libraries. It also indirectly benefits researchers who wish to use licensed content for TDM and AI applications. The recommendations are now available in both German <span class="citation" data-cites="agi_regelungen_2024">(Agi et al. 2024b)</span> and English <span class="citation" data-cites="agi_arrangements_2024">(Agi et al. 2024a)</span>. The goal of the focus area”Digitalization in Science” is to identify the needs of scientists concerning digital infrastructures and services, engage in dialogue with relevant communities, develop practical expertise to support the scholarly work of Alliance organizations, and help shape the framework for digital research. The initiative is guided by principles that prioritize Open Access, while also ensuring sovereignty over data, tools, and infrastructures. <span class="citation" data-cites="allianz_der_wissenschaftsorganisationen_initiatives_nodate">(Wissenschaftsorganisationen n.d.)</span>.</p>
<p>Further information about the work of our research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-agi_arrangements_2024" class="csl-entry">
Agi, Christian, Michael Beurskens, Marion von Francken-Welz, Judith Ludwig, Bernhard Mittermaier, and Heinz Pampel. 2024a. <span>“Arrangements on Artificial Intelligence in Licence Agreements.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13837688">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13837688</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-agi_regelungen_2024" class="csl-entry">
———. 2024b. <span>“Regelungen Zu <span>Künstlicher</span> <span>Intelligenz</span> in <span>Lizenzverträgen</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13837664">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13837664</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-bertelmann_schwerpunkt_2023" class="csl-entry">
Bertelmann, Roland, Angela Cornelia Holzer, Wolfram Horstmann, Lisa Kressin, and Rainer Lange. 2023. <span>“Schwerpunkt "<span>Digitalität</span> in Der <span>Wissenschaft</span>" Der <span>Allianz</span> Der Deutschen <span>Wissenschaftsorganisationen</span>. <span>Digitalität</span> Gestalten – <span>Offenheit</span> Und <span>Souveränität</span> Vorantreiben. 2023-2028.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11189484">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11189484</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-allianz_der_wissenschaftsorganisationen_initiatives_nodate" class="csl-entry">
Wissenschaftsorganisationen, Allianz der. n.d. <span>“Initiatives.”</span> Accessed October 9, 2024. <a href="https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/en/initiatives/">https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/en/initiatives/</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Recommendations on {Regulations} for {Artificial}
    {Intelligence} in {License} {Agreements} {Published}},
  date = {2024-10-17},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/qje5d-11g43},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2024. <span>“Recommendations on Regulations for
Artificial Intelligence in License Agreements Published.”</span> October
17, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/qje5d-11g43">https://doi.org/10.59350/qje5d-11g43</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-17-Recommendations-on-Regulations-for-Artifical-Intelligence-in-License-Agreements-Published/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-17-Recommendations-on-Regulations-for-Artifical-Intelligence-in-License-Agreements-Published/Arrangements on artificial intelligence in licence agreements.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Invitation to the networking workshop of the Infra Wiss Blogs project</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-09-Invitation-to-the-networking-workshop-infrawissblogs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-09-Invitation-to-the-networking-workshop-infrawissblogs/vernetzungsworkshop.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As part of the Infra Wiss Blogs <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_kooperative_2024">(Pampel and Rothfritz 2024)</span> project, we are organizing a first networking workshop for blogging researchers and employees from infrastructure facilities on 06.12.2024.</p>
<p>The aim is to share initial experiences of the various stakeholders and promote their exchange. We will also present the initial results of our survey of German science blogs.</p>
<p>When? Wednesday, 06.12.2024, 10:30-15:00</p>
<p>Where? Robert-Koch-Forum of the Einstein Center Digital Future (ECDF), Wilhelmstraße 67, 10117 Berlin</p>
<p>We are currently planning with the following program:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 76%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Time</strong></td>
<td><strong>Topic</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>10:30</td>
<td>Welcome</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>11:00</td>
<td>Presentation of the results of the mapping of the German science blog landscape.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>11:30</td>
<td>Coffee Break</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>12:00</td>
<td>Presentation by Henning Krause (Helmholtz Blogs) (angefragt)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>12:30</td>
<td>Presentation by Martin Fenner (Front Matter)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>13:00</td>
<td>Food break</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>13:30</td>
<td>Impulses from practice</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>14:00</td>
<td>Discussion round 1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>14:30</td>
<td>Discussion round 2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>15:00</td>
<td>Summary of the results</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>15:15</td>
<td>End of the Workshop</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The workshop will be organized in German. <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/vernetzungsworkshop-infra-wiss-blogs/anmeldung-vernetzungsworkshop-infra-wiss-blogs">Registration</a> is possible through the website of our research group.</p>
<p>If you have any questions, feel free to contact Catharina Ochsner directly, who is managing the project for us. Her email address is: <a href="mailto:catharina.ochsner@hu-berlin.de">catharina.ochsner@hu-berlin.de</a></p>
<p>Further information about the project can be found on the new website of the Infra Wiss Blogs site at: <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/" class="uri">https://infrawissblogs.org/</a>. In the future, we will also report on the project’s progress in German on this website, where we will organize a project blog.</p>
<p>Additional workshops are planned for the coming year.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The “First come, first served” motto applies. We have space for about 20 people. We look forward to your participation. Registrations are possible until the 20th of October 2024.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_kooperative_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, and Laura Rothfritz. 2024. <span>“Kooperative <span>Informationsinfrastruktur</span> Für Wissenschaftliche <span>Blogs</span> (<span>Infra</span> <span>Wiss</span> <span>Blogs</span>).”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2024,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Invitation to the Networking Workshop of the {Infra} {Wiss}
    {Blogs} Project},
  date = {2024-10-09},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/7sbqk-ppj44},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“Invitation to the
Networking Workshop of the Infra Wiss Blogs Project.”</span> October 9,
2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/7sbqk-ppj44">https://doi.org/10.59350/7sbqk-ppj44</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-09-Invitation-to-the-networking-workshop-infrawissblogs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-10-09-Invitation-to-the-networking-workshop-infrawissblogs/vernetzungsworkshop.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Survey announcement: Recording publication costs at research performing institutions in Germany</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-30-survey-announcement-publication-costs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The Research and Teaching Group Information Management is conducting a survey on the topic of recording publication costs at research performing institutions in Germany. The survey is part of the project <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a>, which is funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG).</p>
<p>With this survey, we are investigating how research institutions record data on costs that may arise from the publication of research outputs by members of the institution.</p>
<p>Invitations are sent out to a total of 583 representatives of publicly funded Universities and Universities of Applied Sciences, institutes of the Fraunhofer Society, Helmholtz Association, Leibniz Association, Max Planck Society and federal departmental research institutes (see Figure 1).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-30-survey-announcement-publication-costs/map.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 1: Location of the research institutions that will be invited to the survey by type</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The survey takes about 15 to 20 minutes to complete and can be filled out in German and English. Participating in the survey will help to promote transparency in the area of publication costs and is also useful for institutions that are not yet particularly active in this area. Results of the survey will be made available anonymously under an open license, and will be used to develop supporting materials.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2024,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Survey Announcement: {Recording} Publication Costs at
    Research Performing Institutions in {Germany}},
  date = {2024-10-01},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/9z58m-vwv42},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“Survey Announcement:
Recording Publication Costs at Research Performing Institutions in
Germany.”</span> October 1, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/9z58m-vwv42">https://doi.org/10.59350/9z58m-vwv42</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-30-survey-announcement-publication-costs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-30-survey-announcement-publication-costs/map.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="36" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
