<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</title>
<link>https://infomgnt.org/</link>
<atom:link href="https://infomgnt.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.42</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Guide Published: Interplay of Institutional Repositories and CRIS</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Matthias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>To support repository managers and institutional decision-makers, we are pleased to present our second guide from the BMFTR-funded (Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space) project “Professionalisierung der Open-Access-Repositorien-Infrastruktur in Deutschland (Pro OAR DE)”: “Forschungsinformationssysteme (CRIS): Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien” (German only.)</p>
<p>Matthias, L., Pampel, H., Khamis, C. O., Rothfritz, L., &amp; Wrzesinski, M. (2025). <em>Forschungsinformationssysteme (CRIS): Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien. Pro OAR DE Handreichung.</em> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15800262" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15800262</a></p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/FIS_Handreichung_Blogpost.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This publication documents the outcomes of our December 11, 2024 <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-cris">networking forum</a> on Current Research Information Systems (CRIS) and institutional repositories that brought together 67 Open Access professionals from across Germany. The resulting guide synthesizes the collective expertise and insights generated during this collaborative event, offering practical recommendations to enhance collaboration between institutional repositories and current research information systems.</p>
<p>Following expert presentations by <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4905-1936">Daniel Beucke</a> (Göttingen State and University Library) and <a href="https://orcid.org/0009-0004-2098-8076">Malte Kramer</a> (CRIS.NRW), participants engaged in open discussions through a world café format, where they shared institutional experiences and developed practical approaches to common obstacles. The presentation slides from the expert talks are available <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14440151">online</a>.</p>
<p>The guide distills these rich discussions into actionable recommendations across six critical areas for repository managers:</p>
<section id="interoperability-for-automated-data-flows" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interoperability-for-automated-data-flows">1. Interoperability for Automated Data Flows</h3>
<p>The participants identified essential prerequisites for successful interoperability. They emphasized that interoperability can only be guaranteed when the precise purposes of each actor and system are clearly defined as these purposes determine the required quality level, actual workload, and access authorizations for different data views (for researchers versus administrators) with appropriate granularity. This specificity is particularly important because interoperability exists in varying degrees, and the mapping of relationships must function bidirectionally between systems. Core challenges emerged around the standardization of metadata schemas, international connectivity through multilingual labels, and the consistent use of PIDs, particularly in the versioning of preprints. Attendees proposed several possible solutions. These included stakeholder involvement in determining responsibilities, clear guidance systems for data types, Linked Open Data, and regular quality management. Active participation in relevant networks and collaborative projects can further support these efforts.</p>
</section>
<section id="repository-and-cris---complementary-systems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="repository-and-cris---complementary-systems">2. Repository and CRIS - Complementary Systems</h3>
<p>Critical organizational factors include the need for clear system definitions, the determination of a lead system, and the explicit institutional anchoring of responsibilities. Technical hurdles stem from diverse resource types and varying levels of metadata detail. The proposed solution begins with a comprehensive inventory analysis, followed by transparent assignment of responsibilities across departmental boundaries. The graphical representation of workflows was emphasized as a particularly valuable tool for communication among involved actors.</p>
</section>
<section id="standards-for-research-information" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="standards-for-research-information">3. Standards for Research Information</h3>
<p>Insufficient harmonization between the <a href="https://www.kerndatensatz-forschung.de/">KDSF – Standard für Forschungsinformationen in Deutschland</a> and library standards presents a significant obstacle, alongside further development of research evaluation criteria in the context of the <a href="https://coara.eu/">Coalition for Advancing Research Assessment (CoARA)</a> agreement. Participants identified consistent use of PIDs as a crucial technical prerequisite. CRIS systems show particular promise in adding value to the information budget through the systematic capture of publication costs.</p>
</section>
<section id="system-diversity-and-isolated-solutions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="system-diversity-and-isolated-solutions">4. System Diversity and Isolated Solutions</h3>
<p>Participants identified several barriers, such as insufficient user-friendliness, imprecise requirement profiles, inadequate data management, and limited system upgradeability. To address these challenges, they proposed establishing institutional networking and cooperation strategies guided by a dedicated steering group. In addition, they highlighted the precise definition of responsibilities and the strategic involvement of the institutional leadership. Resources emerged as a crucial factor, with particular emphasis on securing adequate IT competencies. This should be complemented by professional project management. The group proposed that user requirements should be systematically documented through user stories and discussed in an interdisciplinary manner.</p>
</section>
<section id="diversity-of-data---publication-data-and-other-research-information" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diversity-of-data---publication-data-and-other-research-information">5. Diversity of Data - Publication Data and Other Research Information</h3>
<p>At the organizational level, participants pointed to insufficient coordination as a central problem. This manifests in poor interdepartmental coordination, unclear responsibilities, and difficulties in collaboration. The situation is further complicated by the diversity of interest groups, different disciplinary cultures, and a lack of technical standards. To address these issues, participants recommended implementing a clear leadership strategy that meaningfully involves all stakeholders while precisely defining responsibilities. They placed particular emphasis on establishing ongoing dialogue with researchers, whose relief and support should be a central priority. The CoARA recommendations provide a valuable guiding framework for these efforts. From a technical perspective, participants advocated leveraging existing data sources like <a href="https://openalex.org/">OpenAlex</a> and adopting uniform data standards to enhance system interoperability.</p>
</section>
<section id="further-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-challenges">6. Further Challenges</h3>
<p>Organizationally, complexities arise in coordinating repositories and CRIS systems, requiring close collaboration among different organizational units. Technical considerations demand preserving the autonomy of individual systems while simultaneously developing uniform standards for various entry types. The disciplinary dimension adds another layer of complexity, requiring careful consideration of different institutional workflows. Attendees recommended an approach combining several key elements, such as a thoroughly documented, professionally moderated development process, sustainable financing models that ensure long-term viability, and targeted training initiatives at the intersection of administrative and technical requirements.</p>
<p>This guide provides a foundation for continued professional exchange. Repository operators, libraries, and institutional decision-makers will find valuable insights for dataflows between institutional Open Access repositories and CRIS systems.</p>
<p>We extend our sincere thanks to all forum participants who contributed their expertise and experience to this collaborative effort. We welcome your feedback and look forward to continuing this important dialogue as we collectively strengthen the Open Access repository landscape.</p>
<p>For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-matthias_forschungsinformationssysteme_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, Christopher Onzie Khamis, Laura Rothfritz, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2025. <span>“Forschungsinformationssysteme (<span>CRIS</span>): <span>Handlungsfeld</span> Für Institutionelle <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Repositorien</span>. <span>Pro</span> <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Handreichung</span>.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.15800262">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.15800262</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Daniel Beucke, and Malte Kramer. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>FIS</span>/<span>CRIS</span>,”</span> December. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14440151">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14440151</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{matthias2025,
  author = {Matthias, Lisa and Pampel, Heinz and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {Guide {Published:} {Interplay} of {Institutional}
    {Repositories} and {CRIS}},
  date = {2025-07-24},
  url = {https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-matthias2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“Guide Published: Interplay of Institutional Repositories and
CRIS.”</span> July 24, 2025. <a href="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/">https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-24-Guide-Published-Interplay-of-Institutional-Repositories-and-CRIS/FIS_Handreichung_Blogpost.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Libraries as operating and preserving institutions for scholarly blogs: Report on a Hands-on Lab at the 113th Bibliocon</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Till Stadtbäumer</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martin Fenner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sven Ködel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Charmaine Voigt</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Britta Woldering</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/IMG_3511.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Scholarly blogs have established themselves as important platforms for making research findings and discourse accessible both within scientific communities and to the general public. Considering the changing social media landscape, the role of non-commercial infrastructures such as blogs or the Fediverse is becoming increasingly important. Blogs can also be seen as part of scholarly-led open access publishing <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">(Ochsner et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>The long-term accessibility of blogs, especially outside of infrastructures such as <a href="https://de.hypotheses.org/">de.hypotheses.org</a>, is a challenge that has not yet been solved. Archiving dynamic content and comments is a technical and organisational challenge, especially when such content is cited in scientific articles or even court rulings (such as in the <a href="https://verfassungsblog.de">Verfassungsblog</a>). The hacker attacks on the <a href="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</a> in the fall of 2024 furthermore underline the general fragility of digital sources <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">(Ochsner et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>As part of the <a href="https://bid-kongress2025.de/">BID Congress 2025</a>, the Hands-on Lab ‘Libraries as Operating and Preserving Institutions for Scholarly Blogs’ took place on 26 June in Bremen. The lab was initiated by the project ’Infra Wiss Blogs – Kooperative Informationsinfrastruktur für wissenschaftliche Blogs‘ funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG) <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">Pampel and Rothfritz (2024)</span>.</p>
<p>The aim of the Hands-on Lab was to bring together experts from the scholarly blogosphere and libraries to discuss the challenges and potential of scholarly blogs with regard to visibility, indexing and long-term accessibility. Using the World Café method, the participants discussed aspects such as technology, organisation and framework conditions for the sustainable safeguarding and visibility of scholarly blogs in moderated discussion rounds, with a particular focus on the role of libraries as potential supporting institutions <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner2025">(Ochsner et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<section id="these-1-metadaten-und-licenses" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="these-1-metadaten-und-licenses">These 1: Metadaten und Licenses</h3>
<p>The first thesis was: ‘For the long-term archiving of their publications, scholarly blogs must carry out the necessary preparatory work, such as maintaining metadata and issuing (open) licences.’</p>
<p>The discussion showed that there is often a lack of awareness of these requirements in the blog community. Although blogs are valued as a low-threshold form of communication, it is precisely this low-threshold nature that is in tension with requirements such as metadata maintenance, licensing and technical standardisation.</p>
<p>According to the discussion, the responsibility lies with the blogs or authors - for example with regard to clear licence declarations, clarification of copyright issues (e.g.&nbsp;for embedded images) or the uniform use of CSS classes to support automated import processes. In this context, infrastructure providers, such as libraries, are responsible for providing technical solutions such as plugins to import blog posts into their information systems, as well as providing low-threshold information services.</p>
<p>The extent to which nudging strategies could help to establish more sustainable practices was also discussed. The promotion of open licences was highlighted as a particularly relevant field of action in order to overcome legal challenges in subsequent use, for example in the context of archiving.</p>
</section>
<section id="these-2-cataloguing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="these-2-cataloguing">These 2: Cataloguing</h3>
<p>The second thesis focused on the cataloguing of scholarly blogs: ‘The cataloguing of scholarly blogs presents libraries with new challenges, as they can only be catalogued to a limited extent using traditional cataloguing criteria.’</p>
<p>The discussion focused on how deeply blogs should be catalogued. The variety of formats - from individual posts and comments to multimedia content - as well as the often multiple authorship lead to uncertainties in library practice.</p>
<p>Technical aspects such as different platforms, software architectures or feed maintenance also make standardisation difficult. The possible use of web scraping or aggregators such as <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org">Rogue Scholar</a> was discussed. The debate was supplemented by considerations on the sustainability of file formats (e.g.&nbsp;PDF-A, HTML), legal categorisation and liability for international content. One thing became clear: A more systematic approach to librarian fields of action in dealing with blogs is needed.</p>
</section>
<section id="these-3-responsibility-and-infrastructure-institutions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="these-3-responsibility-and-infrastructure-institutions">These 3: Responsibility and Infrastructure Institutions</h3>
<p>The third thesis to be discussed was: “The long-term archiving of scholarly blogs must no longer be treated as a secondary task of public institutions. If necessary, this task must be secured by community-supported platforms.”</p>
<p>This statement was met with broad approval. The focus was on the question of which community can take on this role. Examples from practice showed the commitment of regional depository libraries or specialised information services (FIDs). Several participants reported on ongoing initiatives in their institutions.</p>
<p>Web archiving services and federated models such as <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub</a> were discussed as technical solutions. There was consensus that there is a need for better mapping of existing actors, activities and data flows at the infrastructure level.</p>
</section>
<section id="concluding-discussion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concluding-discussion">Concluding discussion</h3>
<p>In the final discussion, the question of how a sustainable, community-supported archiving of scholarly blogs could be designed was discussed: centralised through a new software solution or decentralised through stronger integration of existing institutions?</p>
<p>There was a consensus that cooperative models are needed in which different actors take on different roles, for example in metadata management, storage or visibility. A systematic approach was proposed: who is already active, what infrastructures exist and how can a cooperative system be formed from them?</p>
<p>The potential of web archiving was emphasised, especially in combination with targeted metadata extraction. The idea of parallel archiving, by the DNB, discipline-specific FIDs or institutional repositories, met with broad approval.</p>
<p><a href="https://rogue-scholar.org">Rogue Scholar</a> was highlighted as an example of good practice. However, it also became clear that there is still considerable room for improvement in ensuring data flows, e.g.&nbsp;for linking archiving, cataloguing and referencing.</p>
<p>Another topic was the role of scholarly blogs in the reputation system. Some called for blogs to be made more visible and integrated into recognition mechanisms for research evaluation. Others emphasised the independence of blogs, analogous to preprints, but without identical rules.</p>
<p>This led to the central question of definition: When is a blog considered scientific enough? The Infra Wiss Blogs project applies a broad definition: Scholarly blogs can be understood as those blogs that are written by scholars or are concerned with scholarly topics. The participants also favoured an orientation towards relevance rather than formal scientificity.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>In the Hands-on Lab, there was overwhelming support for a distributed system with various technical and organisational solutions, supported by a committed, interdisciplinary community that takes responsibility for the maintenance and visibility of scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official Website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina, Elena Di Rosa, Martin Fenner, Sven Ködel, Heinz Pampel, Britta Woldering, Till Stadtbäumer, Charmaine Voigt, and Jonas Höfting. 2025. <span>“Bibliotheken Als Betreibende Und Bewahrende Institutionen Für Wissenschaftliche Blogs.”</span> In. <a href="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-194690">https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-194690</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, and Laura Rothfritz. 2024. <span>“Kooperative Informationsinfrastruktur Für Wissenschaftliche Blogs (Infra Wiss Blogs).”</span> <em>Zenodo</em>, August. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13234482</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Stadtbäumer, Till and Fenner, Martin and
    Ködel, Sven and Voigt, Charmaine and Woldering, Britta and Ochsner,
    Catharina and Höfting, Jonas and Onzie Khamis, Christopher},
  title = {Libraries as Operating and Preserving Institutions for
    Scholarly Blogs: {Report} on a {Hands-on} {Lab} at the 113th
    {Bibliocon}},
  date = {2025-07-23},
  url = {https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-hands-on-lab-wissenschaftsblogs/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Till Stadtbäumer, Martin Fenner, Sven Ködel, Charmaine
Voigt, Britta Woldering, Catharina Ochsner, Jonas Höfting, and
Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025. <span>“Libraries as Operating and
Preserving Institutions for Scholarly Blogs: Report on a Hands-on Lab at
the 113th Bibliocon.”</span> July 23, 2025. <a href="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-hands-on-lab-wissenschaftsblogs/">https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-hands-on-lab-wissenschaftsblogs/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-23-Libraries-as-operating-and-preserving-institutions-for-scholarly-blogs/IMG_3511.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>BUA fellowship: Metadata flows in the context of research data</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/fellowship_program.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>In my PhD research, I investigate how metadata for research data are generated and maintained. I have started by analyzing how metadata records of the DOI registration agency DataCite change over time <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_changes_2024 strecker_how_2024">(Strecker 2024a, 2024b)</span>. Recently, I was awarded a grant by the Berlin University Alliance (BUA) - through the <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/en/commitments/research-quality/forschung/fellowship/index.html">BUA Fellowship Program of the Objective 3 - Advancing Research Quality and Value</a>. This grant will allow me to visit Stefanie Haustein, associate professor at the School of Information Studies at the University of Ottawa and co-director of the <a href="https://www.scholcommlab.ca">ScholCommLab</a>. During my stay, I will investigate metadata flows in the context of research data. In particular, I will examine the transfer of metadata from local to global contexts.</p>
<section id="metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data">Metadata flows in the context of research data</h3>
<p>Research data are typically deposited in research data repositories - infrastructures that specialize in handling this resource type. Metadata describing the datasets are also generated and maintained at these infrastructures. Numerous standards - metadata schemas - are used to describe research data <span class="citation" data-cites="asok_common_2024 koshoffer_giving_2018">(Asok et al. 2024; Koshoffer et al. 2018)</span>. Even within a discipline, the use of metadata schemas is not uniform <span class="citation" data-cites="mayernik_role_2022">(Mayernik and Liapich 2022)</span>. This variance arises because research data repositories create metadata for different use cases. On the one hand, metadata are needed to describe research data in a general and homogeneous way - for example, to enable data discovery in large search services. On the other hand, researchers need subject-specific metadata in order to be able to make an informed decision about whether they want to reuse a dataset <span class="citation" data-cites="de_vries_flexible_2022 doran_reconciling_2021 sostek_discovering_2024">(De Vries et al. 2022; Doran, Edmond, and Nugent-Folan 2021; Sostek et al. 2024)</span>. In order to cover this range of requirements, many research data repositories use several metadata schemas in parallel, e.g.&nbsp;the general DataCite metadata schema for DOI registration and a specialized schema adressing the needs of local users <span class="citation" data-cites="habermann_connecting_2023 lee_landscape_2019 wu_analysis_2023">(Habermann 2023; Lee and Jeng 2019; Wu et al. 2023)</span>. In research data repositories, metadata are often initially generated based on a locally implemented, specific metadata schema. Metadata are then mapped to a general schema to meet global requirements such as DOI registration or harvesting <span class="citation" data-cites="habermann_connecting_2023">(Habermann 2023)</span>. During these mapping processes, however, information from the original comprehensive description can be lost <span class="citation" data-cites="radio_manifestations_2017 taylor_think_2022">(Radio et al. 2017; Taylor et al. 2022)</span>. As a result, metadata lose completeness when they are transferred from local to global contexts <span class="citation" data-cites="mayernik_role_2022">(Mayernik and Liapich 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>During the fellowship, I will investigate metadata flows from research data repositories to DataCite. The aim is to determine whether information that is missing in DataCite metadata are also missing in local contexts or would be available but are not transmitted.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-this-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-this-matters">Why this matters</h3>
<p>Complete metadata are necessary to convey the context of research data. This is relevant for many interactions with research data, including discovery, reuse and citation. Bibliometric research in particular is hindered by incomplete metadata, as is the development of metrics that are intended to reflect the impact of research data <span class="citation" data-cites="ninkov_datasets_2021">(Ninkov et al. 2021)</span>. This research will assess the potential of an approach to improve metadata quality - the optimization of mappings to the DataCite metadata schema.</p>
<p>Further information about our research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-asok_common_2024" class="csl-entry">
Asok, Kavya, Sushree Snigdha Dandpat, Dinesh K. Gupta, and Prashant Shrivastava. 2024. <span>“Common <span>Metadata</span> <span>Framework</span> for <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Repository</span>: <span>Necessity</span> to <span>Support</span> <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of Library Metadata</em> 24: 1–13. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2024.2329370">https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2024.2329370</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-de_vries_flexible_2022" class="csl-entry">
De Vries, Jerry, Vyacheslav Tykhonov, Andrea Scharnhorst, Eko Indarto, Femmy Admiraal, and Mike Priddy. 2022. <span>“Flexible <span>Metadata</span> <span>Schemes</span> for <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Repositories</span>.<span>The</span> <span>Common</span> <span>Framework</span> in <span>Dataverse</span> and the <span>CMDI</span> <span>Use</span> <span>Case</span>.”</span> In, 168–80. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3384/ecp18915">https://doi.org/10.3384/ecp18915</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-doran_reconciling_2021" class="csl-entry">
Doran, Michelle, Jennifer Edmond, and Georgina Nugent-Folan. 2021. <span>“Reconciling the <span>Cultural</span> <span>Complexity</span> of <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span>: <span>Can</span> We <span>Make</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Interdisciplinary</span> Without <span>Hiding</span> <span>Disciplinary</span> <span>Knowledge</span>.”</span> <a href="http://www.tara.tcd.ie/handle/2262/83156">http://www.tara.tcd.ie/handle/2262/83156</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-habermann_connecting_2023" class="csl-entry">
Habermann, Ted. 2023. <span>“Connecting <span>Repositories</span> to the <span>Global</span> <span>Research</span> <span>Community</span>: <span>A</span> <span>Re</span>-<span>Curation</span> <span>Process</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of eScience Librarianship</em> 12 (3): e739. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.739">https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.739</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-koshoffer_giving_2018" class="csl-entry">
Koshoffer, Amy, Amy E. Neeser, Linda Newman, and Lisa R. Johnston. 2018. <span>“Giving <span>Datasets</span> <span>Context</span>: A <span>Comparison</span> <span>Study</span> of <span>Institutional</span> <span>Repositories</span> That <span>Apply</span> <span>Varying</span> <span>Degrees</span> of <span>Curation</span>.”</span> <em>International Journal of Digital Curation</em> 13 (1): 15–34. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2218/ijdc.v13i1.632">https://doi.org/10.2218/ijdc.v13i1.632</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-lee_landscape_2019" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Jian‐Sin, and Wei Jeng. 2019. <span>“The Landscape of Archived Studies in a Social Science Data Infrastructure: <span>Investigating</span> the <span>ICPSR</span> Metadata Records.”</span> <em>Proceedings of the Association for Information Science and Technology</em> 56 (1): 147–56. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/pra2.62">https://doi.org/10.1002/pra2.62</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-mayernik_role_2022" class="csl-entry">
Mayernik, Matthew S., and Yauheniya Liapich. 2022. <span>“The <span>Role</span> of <span>Metadata</span> and <span>Vocabulary</span> <span>Standards</span> in <span>Enabling</span> <span>Scientific</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Interoperability</span>: <span>A</span> <span>Study</span> of <span>Earth</span> <span>System</span> <span>Science</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Facilities</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of eScience Librarianship</em> 11 (2). <a href="https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.619">https://doi.org/10.7191/jeslib.619</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ninkov_datasets_2021" class="csl-entry">
Ninkov, Anton Boudreau, Kathleen Gregory, Isabella Peters, and Stefanie Haustein. 2021. <span>“Datasets on <span>DataCite</span> - an <span>Initial</span> <span>Bibliometric</span> <span>Investigation</span>.”</span> In. Leuven, Belgium (Virtual). <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4730857">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4730857</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-radio_manifestations_2017" class="csl-entry">
Radio, Erik, Fernando Rios, Jeffrey C. Oliver, Benjamin Hickson, and Niamh Wallace. 2017. <span>“Manifestations of <span>Metadata</span> <span>Structures</span> in <span>Research</span> <span>Datasets</span> and <span>Their</span> <span>Ontic</span> <span>Implications</span>.”</span> <em>Journal of Library Metadata</em> 17 (3-4): 161–82. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2018.1439278">https://doi.org/10.1080/19386389.2018.1439278</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-sostek_discovering_2024" class="csl-entry">
Sostek, Katrina, Daniel Russell, Nitesh Goyal, Tarfah Alrashed, Stella Dugall, and Natasha Noy. 2024. <span>“Discovering <span>Datasets</span> on the <span>Web</span> <span>Scale</span>: <span>Challenges</span> and <span>Recommendations</span> for <span>Google</span> <span>Dataset</span> <span>Search</span>.”</span> <em>Harvard Data Science Review</em> Special Issue 4. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/99608f92.4c3e11ca">https://doi.org/10.1162/99608f92.4c3e11ca</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_changes_2024" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea. 2024a. <span>“Changes in <span>DataCite</span> <span>DOI</span> Metadata for Research Data.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14274240">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14274240</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_how_2024" class="csl-entry">
———. 2024b. <span>“How Permanent Are Metadata for Research Data? <span>Understanding</span> Changes in <span>DataCite</span> <span>DOI</span> Metadata.”</span> arXiv. <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arxiv.2412.05128">https://doi.org/10.48550/arxiv.2412.05128</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-taylor_think_2022" class="csl-entry">
Taylor, Shawna, Sarah Wright, Mikala R. Narlock, and Ted Habermann. 2022. <span>“Think <span>Globally</span>, <span>Act</span> <span>Locally</span>: <span>The</span> <span>Importance</span> of <span>Elevating</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Repository</span> <span>Metadata</span> to the <span>Global</span> <span>Infrastructure</span>.”</span> In. <a href="https://hdl.handle.net/11299/228001">https://hdl.handle.net/11299/228001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wu_analysis_2023" class="csl-entry">
Wu, Mingfang, Stephen M. Richard, Chantelle Verhey, Leyla Jael Castro, Baptiste Cecconi, and Nick Juty. 2023. <span>“An <span>Analysis</span> of <span>Crosswalks</span> from <span>Research</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Schemas</span> to <span>Schema</span>.org.”</span> <em>Data Intelligence</em> 5 (1): 100–121. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/dint_a_00186">https://doi.org/10.1162/dint_a_00186</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea},
  title = {BUA Fellowship: {Metadata} Flows in the Context of Research
    Data},
  date = {2025-07-18},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea. 2025. <span>“BUA Fellowship: Metadata Flows in the
Context of Research Data .”</span> July 18, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07">https://doi.org/10.59350/wwwj7-4cm07</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-18-BUA-Fellowship-Metadata-flows-in-the-context-of-research-data/fellowship_program.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Connecting Knowledge with Wikidata: A Practical Project with the Museum für Naturkunde Berlin</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Stefanie Paß</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sabine von Mering</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Clara Schindler</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>How can scholarly publications be made more visible, discoverable, and interconnected? This question is the focus of a student practical project conducted as part of the seminar within the module Information Production and Management (BP3) in the summer semester 2025.</p>
<p>In close collaboration with colleagues from the <a href="https://www.museumfuernaturkunde.berlin/de/forschung/bibliothek">Coordination Office for Scholarly Publishing at the Library</a> as well as a research associate from the “Future of Collections” research area at the Museum für Naturkunde Berlin (MfN), the students are working on an exciting task: documenting scholarly journals in Wikidata from the fields of zoology, biodiversity research, and paleontology, including taxonomy and systematics of fossil organisms, enriching them with information, and linking them to each other.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/mfn_visit.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As part of this semester’s “Übung”, students received an introduction to Linked Open Data, with a particular focus on Wikidata. Especially for library applications, Wikidata is an exciting project because authorities, publications, and collections can be linked together, creating new opportunities for discovery, contextualization, and visibility.</p>
<p>The students worked with real datasets on the Museum für Naturkunde’s in-house journals <a href="https://zse.pensoft.net/">Zoosystematics and Evolution (ZSE)</a>, <a href="https://fr.pensoft.net/">Fossil Record (FR)</a> and <a href="https://dez.pensoft.net/">Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift (DEZ)</a>. Among other tasks, their work involved reviewing existing Wikidata entries, adding missing information, and linking relevant metadata (for example ISSNs, publishers, publication periods) with authority records such as the <a href="https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/">Biodiversity Heritage Library (BHL)</a>, the <a href="https://gnd.network/Webs/gnd/DE/Entdecken/entdecken_node.html">Gemeinsame Normdatei (GND)</a>, or the <a href="https://viaf.org/de">Virtual International Authority File (VIAF)</a>.</p>
<p>The module at the Institute for Library and Information Science also included a visit to the Museum für Naturkunde, where students received a tour of the collections. This provided a hands-on introduction to working with real museum objects as part of their data-related assignments.</p>
<p>The edit-a-thon, embedded in a university seminar, demonstrated impressively the potential of structured, machine-readable data for digital science communication. Through the targeted recording and interlinking of publication data in Wikidata, new possibilities emerge for analysis and visualization. Tools like <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/">Scholia</a> already offer fascinating insights into topics such as “Top Topics through Time,” author networks, or gender ratios in science.</p>
<p>Examples from Scholia for individual publication periods of the three journals:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>ZSE (2008–present): <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q15755646" class="uri">https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q15755646</a></p></li>
<li><p>FR (2008–present): <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q2455930" class="uri">https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q2455930</a></p></li>
<li><p>DEZ (1954–present): <a href="https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q403726">https://scholia.toolforge.org/venue/Q4037265</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>By systematically capturing article data from more than 160 years of publishing activity, a valuable resource is created for future research questions. Scholarly publications serve here as references and as data sources, but also as links to other entities such as groups of organisms, people, places, research expeditions, and collections (von Mering, 2024). The overarching goal is an open knowledge infrastructure for everyone, both researchers and the broader public. The Museum für Naturkunde Berlin will continue along this path with its own digitization initiatives and in collaboration with external partner projects.</p>
<p>Further information: Post about Open Cultural Data in Wikimedia Germany’s blog: <a href="https://blog.wikimedia.de/2024/04/22/wie-das-naturkundemuseum-mit-linked-open-data-unbekannte-forschende-sichtbar-macht/">Wie das Naturkundemuseum mit Linked Open Data unbekannte Forschende sichtbar macht</a></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-10.3897/rio.10.e118851" class="csl-entry">
von Mering, Sabine, Erik Stolze, Katja Kaiser, and Mareike Petersen. 2024. <span>“Sharing Data, Caring for Collections. <span>Open</span> Data on Collection Agents Affiliated with the <span>Museum</span> f<span>ü</span>r <span>Naturkunde Berlin</span>.”</span> <em>Research Ideas and Outcomes</em> 10: e118851. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.10.e118851">https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.10.e118851</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2025,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura and Paß, Stefanie and von Mering, Sabine
    and Schindler, Clara and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Connecting {Knowledge} with {Wikidata:} {A} {Practical}
    {Project} with the {Museum} Für {Naturkunde} {Berlin}},
  date = {2025-07-16},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/hzjde-ss694},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura, Stefanie Paß, Sabine von Mering, Clara Schindler, and
Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Connecting Knowledge with Wikidata: A
Practical Project with the Museum Für Naturkunde Berlin.”</span> July
16, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/hzjde-ss694">https://doi.org/10.59350/hzjde-ss694</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Teaching</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-07-16-Connecting-Knowledge-with-Wikidata-a-practical-Project-with-the-Museum-fuer-Naturkunde-Berlin/mfn_visit.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access Repositories in Germany</title>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Matthias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are excited to share our first guide from the BMFTR-funded (Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space) project “Professionalisierung der Open-Access-Repositorien-Infrastruktur in Deutschland (Pro OAR DE)”: “Preprints: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien” (German only.)</p>
<p>Matthias, L., Pampel, H., Khamis, C. O., Rothfritz, L., &amp; Wrzesinski, M. (2025). <em>Preprints: Handlungsfeld für institutionelle Open-Access-Repositorien. Pro OAR DE Handreichung.</em> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096</a></p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/Blogpost_Preprint_Handreichung.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This publication stems from our November 13, 2024 <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-preprints">networking forum</a> on preprints and institutional repositories, which brought together 59 Open Access professionals from across Germany. The guide captures the collective expertise and insights generated during this collaborative event, offering practical recommendations to enhance how institutional repositories handle preprints.</p>
<p>Following expert presentations by <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7060-3670">Lea-Maria Ferguson</a> (Helmholtz Open Science Office) and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9846-5516">Alexander Wagner</a> (DESY), participants engaged in dynamic discussions in a “world café” format where they shared experiences and developed solutions to common obstacles. The presentation slides are available <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14185122">online</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>The guide distills these rich discussions into actionable recommendations across five critical areas for repository managers:</p>
<section id="policy-for-preprints" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="policy-for-preprints">1. Policy for Preprints</h3>
<p>Without overarching standards, institutions struggle with unclear definitions distinguishing publication types. Proposed solutions include establishing clear typological classifications at submission, setting explicit criteria for different preprint versions, implementing automated notification systems for updates, and creating robust links between preprints and their final published versions.</p>
</section>
<section id="accessibility-workflows" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accessibility-workflows">2. Accessibility Workflows</h3>
<p>Repository managers face a complex web of challenges: the relationship between institutional and subject-specific repositories, technical representation issues, and limited researcher awareness about the strategic implications of preprints. Solutions include fostering cross-institutional dialogue, setting focused goals to reduce maintenance overhead, and providing comprehensive consultation services that empower researchers to make informed publication decisions.</p>
</section>
<section id="versioning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="versioning">3. Versioning</h3>
<p>Three major barriers complicate version management: First, many repository systems simply lack versioning functionalities. Second, those with versioning capabilities must navigate the trade-off between merge approaches and split approaches. Third, authors have no obligation to report when their preprints are subsequently published, making it difficult to track version evolution. The community strongly advocated for early publication counseling and proactive author engagement to map out publication trajectories and develop appropriate pathways collaboratively.</p>
</section>
<section id="disciplinary-diversity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="disciplinary-diversity">4. Disciplinary Diversity</h3>
<p>Preprint definitions and practices vary across disciplines, creating workflow complexities that require tailored solutions and generating reporting issues when publications appear across multiple platforms and stages. This diversity demands flexible approaches: facilitating faculty-level decision-making, establishing discipline-specific editorial networks for quality assurance, and emphasizing the critical role of high-quality metadata.</p>
</section>
<section id="further-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-challenges">5. Further Challenges</h3>
<p>Communication barriers with publishers (particularly in the humanities), absent technical standards for metadata transfer and linking, and limited training opportunities for repository managers continue to hinder progress. Highlighted solutions include targeted outreach to academic communities, developing robust technical interfaces for better interoperability, establishing preprint policies with clear Persistent identifier (PID) recommendations, and expanding professional development programs both nationally and internationally.</p>
<hr>
<p>This guide provides a foundation for continued professional exchange. Repository operators, libraries, and institutional decision-makers will find valuable insights for strategically embedding preprints within their institutions.</p>
<p>We extend our sincere thanks to all forum participants who contributed their expertise and experience to this collaborative effort. We welcome your feedback and look forward to continuing this important dialogue as we collectively strengthen the Open Access repository landscape.</p>
<p>The Pro OAR DE project continues with its sixth Networking Forum on July 7, 2025, focusing on “Compliance with Funding Requirements for Open Access.” We are delighted to welcome representatives from the European Research Council (ERC) and the German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG), who will provide insights into their repository strategies and Open Access policies. <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-compliance">Registration</a> is now open for this virtual event.</p>
<p>For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our official <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>. This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-matthias_preprints_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, Christopher Onzie Khamis, Laura Rothfritz, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2025. <span>“Preprints: <span>Handlungsfeld</span> Für Institutionelle <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Repositorien</span>. <span>Pro</span> <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Handreichung</span>.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15603096</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Alexander Wagner, Lea-Maria Ferguson, and Marcel Meistring. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>Preprints</span>,”</span> November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14185122">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14185122</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{matthias2025,
  author = {Matthias, Lisa and Pampel, Heinz and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {Networking for the {Advancement} of {Institutional} {Open}
    {Access} {Repositories} in {Germany}},
  date = {2025-06-23},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/kb3zc-v2x38},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-matthias2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthias, Lisa, Heinz Pampel, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access
Repositories in Germany.”</span> June 23, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/kb3zc-v2x38">https://doi.org/10.59350/kb3zc-v2x38</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-23-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-OA-Repositories/Blogpost_Preprint_Handreichung.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Recap: Infra Wiss Blogs Webinar on Rogue Scholar</title>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="presentations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presentations">Presentations</h2>
<p>On June 11, 2025, the webinar of the project <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG) took place on the topic of “Blog archiving with Rogue Scholar using the example of WordPress hosted blogs”. The webinar highlighted the possibilities and challenges of archiving scholarly blogs. At its core was the presentation of <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org/">Rogue Scholar</a>, a platform for archiving scholarly blogs. Around 50 people took part. This blog post summarizes the key discussion points and findings from the webinar.</p>
<p>After a welcome by <a href="https://heinzpampel.de/">Heinz Pampel</a>, <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/teaminfomanagement">Catharina Ochsner</a> first introduced the topic of scholarly blogs. She introduced the basic concept of scholarly blogging, presented challenges of archiving blogs, and emphasized the importance of the long-term accessibility of scholarly blogs. <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner_blogarchivierung_2025">(Ochsner and Pampel 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>Martin Fenner (<a href="https://front-matter.io/team">Front Matter</a> then presented the functionality and possibilities of <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org/">Rogue Scholar</a>, a platform based on <a href="https://inveniosoftware.org/products/rdm/">Invenio RDM</a>, which is dedicated to archiving scholarly blogs. Rogue Scholar not only archives the content of the blogs, but also assigns Digital Object Identifiers (DOIs) for blog posts and ensures web archiving via the <a href="https://archive.org/about/">Internet Archive</a>. Currently, around 150 blogs and more than 40,000 posts are archived at Rogue Scholar. All blogs archived by Rogue Scholar are licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/">Creative Commons</a> Attribution (CC-BY). To facilitate the archiving of blogs at Rogue Scholar, Martin Fenner made a number of recommendations, such as the use of a CC-BY license or the use of references in the blog posts <span class="citation" data-cites="fenner_blogarchivierung_2025">(Fenner 2025)</span>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/webinar_infrawissblogs.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Afterwards, <a href="https://blog.dini.de/EPub_FIS/author/beucked/">Daniel Beucke</a> from the <a href="https://www02.sub.uni-goettingen.de/en/news/">Göttingen State and University Library (SUB)</a> and <a href="https://zfmedienwissenschaft.de/archiv/autorin/steiner-tobias">Tobias Steiner</a> shared their experiences with Rogue Scholar and the associated archiving of their scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>Daniel Beucke contributed the perspective of the <a href="https://blog.dini.de/EPub_FIS/">DINI blog</a>, which has been reporting from the working groups of the <a href="https://dini.de/">German Initiative for Network Information (DINI)</a> since 2016. He emphasized the relevance of long-term availability and described the simple integration into Rogue Scholar. According to Beucke, a central challenge for the DINI blog is the high number of guest authors and their representation in the metadata <span class="citation" data-cites="beucke_anwenderperspektive_2025">(Beucke 2025)</span>. Tobias Steiner contributed his experience from two perspectives: He not only blogs privately on <a href="https://flavoursofopen.science/">Flavours of Open</a>, but is also an editor for the blog of the open access journal <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/home/CST">Critical Studies in Television</a>, <a href="https://cstonline.net/">CSTonline</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="steiner_archivierung_2025">(Steiner 2025)</span>. Both blogs are archived on Rogue Scholar.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>In the final discussion, a number of themes and questions emerged, which are summarized here.</p>
<p>A first central point of discussion was the use of CC licenses for scholarly blogs. As mentioned above, Rogue Scholar only archives blogs whose posts are published under a CC-BY license. CC-BY can be seen as the standard for open access publications, as this license entails few restrictions and also corresponds most closely to the scholarly citation practice. However, subsequent archiving can lead to complex situations if blog posts in community blogs have not yet been published under an open license. In such cases, all previous authors must be contacted in order to enable subsequent licensing. It is therefore recommended that both the blog and each individual post be clearly licensed in advance.</p>
<p>Technical challenges were also discussed, such as dealing with multimedia content or comments in blogs. Unresolved issues became clear here. The role of scholarly blogs in the publication landscape was considered from several perspectives. Similarities between blog posts and pre-prints were highlighted. Martin Fenner reported on the first successful tests with peer review procedures for blog posts via the platform <a href="https://cms.metaror.org/">MetaROR</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="marcum_peer-review_2025">(Marcum 2025)</span>. The possibility of mapping corrections and retractions of blog posts was also discussed.</p>
<p>In the context of archiving scholarlyblogs, the structural dependence on individual actors was identified as a problem. Two strategies for enabling long-term accessibility emerged from the discussion: firstly, the collective assumption of responsibility through community-supported infrastructures, and secondly, the institutional anchoring of blog offerings within established organizations.</p>
</section>
<section id="summary-and-outlook" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary-and-outlook">Summary and outlook</h2>
<p>The webinar provided insights into both the functioning of Rogue Scholar and the perspectives of its users. The positive response as well as the large number of questions and discussions illustrate the existing need within the scholarly community. At the same time, it became clear that projects such as Infra Wiss Blogs can make an important contribution to structuring discourse on cooperative solutions for digital preservation.</p>
<p>We would like to thank all speakers and participants for their contributions and the insightful discussions. The slide sets of the speakers are available in the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement">Community of the Chair of Information Management on Zenodo</a>. We communicate updates on the project and other events via this blog, the <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">project blog</a> and the project’s <a href="https://www.listserv.dfn.de/sympa/info/infra-wiss-blogs">mailing list</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about our group can be found on the <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-beucke_anwenderperspektive_2025" class="csl-entry">
Beucke, Daniel. 2025. <span>“Anwenderperspektive: <span>DINI</span>-Blog.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640226">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640226</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-fenner_blogarchivierung_2025" class="csl-entry">
Fenner, Martin. 2025. <span>“Blogarchivierung von <span>WordPress</span> Mit Rogue Scholar.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640360">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640360</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-marcum_peer-review_2025" class="csl-entry">
Marcum, Christopher Steven. 2025. <span>“Peer-Review for a Blog Post? My Experience with <span>MetaROR</span>.”</span> <em>Upstream</em>, April. <a href="https://doi.org/10.54900/bymaz-4fw37">https://doi.org/10.54900/bymaz-4fw37</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ochsner_blogarchivierung_2025" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Blogarchivierung Mit Rogue Scholar Am Beispiel von <span>WordPress</span> Gehosteten Blogs.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640371">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640371</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-steiner_archivierung_2025" class="csl-entry">
Steiner, Tobias. 2025. <span>“Archivierug von Blogs in Rogue Scholar – Zwei Beispiele Aus Der Community.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640396">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15640396</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{höfting2025,
  author = {Höfting, Jonas and Ochsner, Catharina and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Recap: {Infra} {Wiss} {Blogs} {Webinar} on {Rogue} {Scholar}},
  date = {2025-06-19},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/5azm1-a0n89},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-höfting2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Höfting, Jonas, Catharina Ochsner, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Recap:
Infra Wiss Blogs Webinar on Rogue Scholar.”</span> June 19, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/5azm1-a0n89">https://doi.org/10.59350/5azm1-a0n89</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-19-Recap-Infra-Wiss-Blogs-Webinar-on-Rogue-Scholar/webinar_infrawissblogs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="94" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Open Access Dashboard Collection Launched</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Johannes Schneider</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="open-access-dashboard-collection-launched" class="level1">
<h1>Open Access Dashboard Collection Launched</h1>
<p>As Open Access becomes increasingly central to scholarship and science policy, understanding the proportion of open publications within the overall publication output, whether at the level of research-performing organizations, individual countries, or globally, is gaining importance.</p>
<p>In recent years, an increasing number of dashboards have been created to track different facets of Open Access. Yet, a comprehensive overview of these tools has been missing. In our project <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en/">OA Datenpraxis</a> (Data Practice for Shaping the Open Access Transformation – Analysis, Recommendation, Training &amp; Networking), funded by the <a href="https://www.dfg.de/">German Research Foundation (DFG)</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_datenpraxis_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span>, we have spent the past several months engaging with this topic by systematically mapping and analyzing the current landscape of Open Access dashboards.</p>
<p>We conducted a survey in which we identified nearly 60 dashboards. To enable a structured description of these dashboards, we developed a dedicated <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/dashboards_schema.html">metadata schema</a>. This schema captures key characteristics such as data sources, their license, responsible organizations, the type of output they monitor and more.</p>
<p>The resulting <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en/dashboard_uebersicht.html">Open Access Dashboard Collection</a> is now available on the project website. The underlying <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/dashboards_schema.html">metadata schema</a> is also accessible there and open for reuse.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/oa-dashboard-collection.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We aim to continue developing this dataset through an open and participatory process. We welcome suggestions for additional dashboards as well as ideas for further refining the dataset and its structure.</p>
<p>An editable version of the collection is available in a <a href="https://nextcloud.gfz.de/s/QG38J6kEDbJ8DXz">shared Nextcloud folder</a>, where you can directly add your suggestions. For questions, feedback, or submissions, please contact us at: <a href="mailto:oa-datenpraxis-dashboards@listserv.dfn.de">oa-datenpraxis-dashboards@listserv.dfn.de</a>. We look forward to hearing from you!</p>
<p>The project OA Datenpraxis supports the development of infrastructures for the open access transformation at research institutions in Germany. It focuses on promoting and establishing sovereign data practices to shape and manage this transformation effectively.</p>
<p>Further information about the project can be found on the <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en">project website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_datenpraxis_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Najko Jahn, Roland Bertelmann, Wolfram Horstmann, Laura Rothfritz, Lea Maria Ferguson, Birgit Schmidt, and Anna Stisser. 2024. <span>“Datenpraxis Zur <span>Gestaltung</span> Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Transformation</span> - <span>Analyse</span>, <span>Empfehlung</span>, <span>Training</span> &amp; <span>Vernetzung</span> (<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span>).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Schneider, Johannes},
  title = {Open {Access} {Dashboard} {Collection} {Launched}},
  date = {2025-06-12},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/gj3rx-m5059},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, and Johannes Schneider. 2025. <span>“Open Access
Dashboard Collection Launched.”</span> June 12, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/gj3rx-m5059">https://doi.org/10.59350/gj3rx-m5059</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-12-Open-Access-Dashboard-Collection-Launched/oa-dashboard-collection.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar zu offenen Metadaten für Hochschulrankings am Beispiel des Leiden Ranking</title>
  <dc:creator>Sophia Dörner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Am 04.04.2025 veranstaltete das von der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) geförderte Projekt <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/">OA Datenpraxis</a> ein Webinar zum Thema “Offene Metadaten für Hochschulrankings am Beispiel des Leiden Ranking”. Für das Webinar konnten Nees Jan von Eck (CWTS Leiden) und Anja Oberländer (Universität Konstanz) als Vortragende gewonnen werden. Der Vortrag von Nees Jan van Eck bot Einblicke in die Hintergründe und Entwicklung des CWTS Leiden Ranking vom traditionellen Ranking hin zur Open Edition. Der Vortrag von Anja Oberländer komplettierte dies durch Schilderungen zur Anwenderperspektive des Leiden Ranking Open Edition am Beispiel der Universität Konstanz, insbesondere in Bezug auf die datengestützte Kommunikation der institutionellen Forschungs- und Open-Access-Erfolge nach innen und außen.</p>
<p>Dieser Beitrag fasst zentrale Punkte der beiden Vorträge sowie der anschließenden Frage-und-Antwort-Runde zusammen.</p>
<section id="leiden-ranking-open-edition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leiden-ranking-open-edition">Leiden Ranking (Open Edition)</h2>
<p>Nees Jan van Eck eröffnete das Webinar mit einer detaillierten Präsentation über die Entwicklung des Leiden Ranking Open Edition. Diese Initiative wurde von der strategischen Ausrichtung des CWTS zu <a href="https://www.cwts.nl/blog?article=n-r2q274">verantwortungsvollem Hochschulranking-Design</a> getragen. Im Gegensatz zum traditionellen Leiden Ranking, das auf proprietären Daten aus dem Web of Science von Clarivate basiert, erreicht die Open Edition vollständige Transparenz, indem sie auf OpenAlex setzt, einer vollständig offenen Datenquelle von <a href="https://ourresearch.org/">OurResearch</a>. Sowohl die zugrundeliegenden Daten als auch der Quellcode sind offen zugänglich, was es ermöglicht, die Publikationen zu identifizieren, die verschiedene Indikatorenwerte maßgeblich beeinflussen. Die bibliometrische Methodik ist größtenteils unverändert, um Vergleiche zwischen den beiden Ranking-Versionen zu ermöglichen. Der Vortrag addressierte auch Herausforderungen, wie z. B. eine unzureichende Datenabdeckung und -qualität, die bei der Verwendung offener Datenquellen auftreten können. Nees Jan van Eck betonte, dass die aktive Nutzung offener Daten nicht nur Probleme transparent macht, sondern auch rasche Verbesserungen durch einen community-basierten Ansatz ermöglicht.</p>
</section>
<section id="anwendung-des-leiden-rankings-an-der-universität-konstanz" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="anwendung-des-leiden-rankings-an-der-universität-konstanz">Anwendung des Leiden Rankings an der Universität Konstanz</h2>
<p>Anja Oberländer stellte die praktische Anwendung des Leiden Ranking Open Edition an der Universität Konstanz vor. Sie hob die bundesweit führende Position der Universität in der Open Access Dimension hervor und führte diesen Erfolg auf strategische Initiativen wie die zentrale Nutzung des institutionellen Repositoriums für Open-Access-Publikationen, die Pflege der Hochschulbibliographie und die Nutzung als Datenquelle für die Berichterstattung zurück. Darüber hinaus hat eine proaktive institutionelle Open-Access-Politik eine entscheidende Rolle gespielt. Die herausragende Platzierung der Universität in der Open Access Dimension ist daneben vor allem auf den hohen Anteil an Publikationen zurückzuführen, die über den grünen Weg des Open Access zugänglich sind. Der Vortrag addressierte auch die Herausforderungen der Universität Konstanz, diese Spitzenposition zu halten, da andere Einrichtungen zunehmend ähnliche Strategien verfolgen und verlagsseitige Open-Access-Veröffentlichungen verstärkt über Transformationsverträge ausgehandelt werden.</p>
</section>
<section id="diskussionspunkte" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diskussionspunkte">Diskussionspunkte</h2>
<p>Im Anschluss an die Vorträge hatten die Teilnehmer:innen des Webinars die Gelegenheit, Nachfragen zu stellen. Interesse weckten beispielsweise folgende zentrale Punkte:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Datenquellen und Vergleichbarkeit: In der Diskussion wurde auf die Unterschiede zwischen OpenAlex, Scopus und Web of Science eingegangen. Es wurde hervorgehoben, dass OpenAlex eine breitere Abdeckung bietet. Trotz Unterschieden zwischen den Datenquellen ermöglicht die Verwendung der gleichen Methodik für die traditionelle und die Open Edition des Leiden Ranking einen Vergleich beider Versionen. Für die Open Access Dimension stützen sich alle Datenquellen auf Unpaywall, durch diesen gemeinsamen Referenzpunkt ist in diesem Aspekt bereits eine Vergleichbarkeit zwischen den Datenquellen gegeben.</p></li>
<li><p>Datenqualität und Einbindung der Community: Die Diskussion hob die Bedeutung des Feedbacks aus der Community bei der Identifizierung und Korrektur von Datenfehlern in OpenAlex wurde hervor. Probleme wie die falsche Klassifizierung von Publikationstypen und Fehler bei Affiliationsdaten konnten bereits durch entsprechende Rückmeldungen an OpenAlex verbessert werden.</p></li>
<li><p>Institutionelle Strukturen und ROR: Die Komplexität von institutionellen Strukturen und ihre Abbildung im Research Organisation Registry (ROR) wurde diskutiert. CWTS korrigiert Fehler im ROR manuell und fügt zusätzliche Beziehungen für die Nutzung im Leiden Ranking hinzu. Die community-basierte Kuratierung von ROR Daten trägt ebenfalls zur Verbesserung der Genauigkeit bei.</p></li>
<li><p>Verwendung von Ranking-Daten: Es wurde betont, dass die Daten des Leiden Ranking Open Edition zur Nachnutzung offen zugänglich sind. Sie können über eine Google Big Query-Instanz oder ein Webinterface abgerufen werden, wodurch die Nachnutzung für Nutzende mit unterschiedlicher technischer Versiertheit ermöglicht wird. Die Einrichtungen wurden ermutigt, mit den Daten basierend auf ihren spezifischen Interessen zu experimentieren.</p></li>
<li><p>Indikatoren: Es wurde darüber diskutiert, wie man über die traditionellen Metriken hinausgehen kann, die im Zuge von Reformen der Forschungsbewertung kritisiert werden. OpenAlex bietet eine gute Grundlage für die Weiterentwicklung, beispielsweise durch die Berücksichtigung nicht-englischsprachiger Publikationen und anderer Arten von wissenschaftlichem Output.</p></li>
<li><p>Open-Access-Strategien: Die Bedeutung einer umfassenden Unterstützung für Forscher:innen, die Förderung von Diamond Open Access und ein ganzheitlicher Ansatz anstatt einer Fokussierung ausschließlich auf quantitative Maßnahmen wurden als Schlüsselstrategien zur Erreichung von “Exzellenz” im Bereich Open Access hervorgehoben.</p></li>
<li><p>Vollständigkeit der Hochschulbibliographie: Auf die Frage nach der Vollständigkeit der Hochschulbibliographie an der Universität Konstanz und der Möglichkeit, dieses Vorgehen auf größere Universitäten zu übertragen, antwortete Anja Oberländer, dass die Bibliographie in den Naturwissenschaften sehr vollständig ist, während es in den Geisteswissenschaften Lücken gibt. Diese sind oft auf mangelndes Engagement der Forscher:innen zurückzuführen. Größere Universitäten können dieses Vorgehen zwar übernehmen, müssen jedoch mit einem höheren Zeitaufwand und mehr Ressourcen rechnen.</p></li>
<li><p>Kommunikation der Ranking-Ergebnisse an die Hochschulleitung: Auf die Frage, ob die Universität Konstanz das Ranking aktiv in die Hochschulleitung einbringt, um für Open Access zu werben, erläuterte Anja Oberländer, dass dies nicht nötig ist, da die Hochschulleitung den Wert von Open Access bereits anerkennt und die Ergebnisse aktiv nutzt. Die kleine Größe der Universität erleichtert dies.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="materialien-zum-webinar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="materialien-zum-webinar">Materialien zum Webinar</h2>
<p>Die Folien der beiden Vorträge sind unter folgenden Links verfügbar:</p>
<ul>
<li>CWTS Leiden Ranking Open Edition: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838</a></li>
<li>Leiden Ranking at the University of Konstanz: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis">Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.oa-datenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a> ist ein gemeinsames DFG-Projekt des <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de">Instituts für Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a>, des <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> und der <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de">Niedersächsischen Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen</a>.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis finden Sie auf der <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/events.html">Webseite</a> des Projektes.</p>
<p>Dieser Text - mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Teilen - ist lizenziert unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-oberlander_leiden_2025" class="csl-entry">
Oberländer, Anja. 2025. <span>“Leiden Ranking at the University of Konstanz.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15593872</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-van_eck_cwts_2025" class="csl-entry">
Van Eck, Nees Jan. 2025. <span>“<span>CWTS</span> Leiden Ranking Open Edition.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15147838</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{dörner2025,
  author = {Dörner, Sophia},
  title = {Rückblick: {OA} {Datenpraxis} {Webinar} Zu Offenen
    {Metadaten} Für {Hochschulrankings} Am {Beispiel} Des {Leiden}
    {Ranking}},
  date = {2025-06-11},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/21rye-3j054},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-dörner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Dörner, Sophia. 2025. <span>“Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar Zu
Offenen Metadaten Für Hochschulrankings Am Beispiel Des Leiden
Ranking.”</span> June 11, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/21rye-3j054">https://doi.org/10.59350/21rye-3j054</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-06-11-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zu-offenen-Metadaten-fuer-Hochschulrankings/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Webinar: Blog archiving with Rogue Scholar using the example of WordPress Blogs</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-05-16-Webinar-Blog-archiving-with-Rogue-Scholar-using-the-example-of-WordPress-Blogs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As part of the <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> project funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG), we invite you to a webinar on the topic of archiving scholarly blogs. This webinar will focus on the <a href="https://preview.rogue-scholar.org/de">Rogue Scholar</a> service by <a href="https://front-matter.io/">Front Matter</a>. After an introduction to the Infra Wiss Blogs project, we will present and discuss how WordPress-hosted scholarly blogs can be archived with Rogue Scholar. This will be followed by user reports on their experiences of using Rogue Scholar. The webinar will conclude with an open discussion.</p>
<p>The webinar is aimed at scholars, bloggers, experts from information infrastructures and anyone involved in digital scholarly communication and sustainable archiving. The Webinar will be held in German.</p>
<p><strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday, June 11th 2025</p>
<p><strong>Duration:</strong> 10:00 - 11:30</p>
<p><strong>Please register here:</strong> <a href="https://hu.berlin/infrawissblogs" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/infrawissblogs</a></p>
<p><strong>Contact:</strong> <a href="mailto:catharina.ochsner@hu-berlin.de">catharina.ochsner@hu-berlin.de</a></p>
<p>We are currently planning with the following program:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Uhrzeit</th>
<th>Thema</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>10:00</td>
<td>Welcome and presentation of Infra Wiss Blogs (Heinz Pampel and Catharina Ochsner)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>10:10</td>
<td>Introduction to Rogue Scholar (Martin Fenner, Front Matter)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>10:30</td>
<td>User perspective I: <a href="https://blog.dini.de/EPub_FIS/ueber-uns/">Gemeinsamer Blog der AGs Forschungsinformationen &amp; -systeme, Elektronisches Publizieren und des Kompetenzzentrums Interoperable Metadaten der Deutsche Initiative für Netzwerkinformation e. V.</a> (DINI) (Daniel Beucke, Niedersächsischen Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>10:45</td>
<td>User perspective II: <a href="https://cstonline.net/">CSTonline, community blog of the journal <em>Critical Studies in Television</em></a> (Tobias Steiner, COPIM)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>11:00</td>
<td>Discussion</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>11:30</td>
<td>End of webinar</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Further details and updates on the workshop and the project Infra Wiss Blogs will be communicated via the <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">project blog</a> as well as the project’s <a href="https://www.listserv.dfn.de/sympa/info/infra-wiss-blogs">mailing list</a>. If you have any questions, please contact <a href="mailto:catharina.ochsner@hu-berlin.de">Catharina Ochsner</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Webinar: {Blog} Archiving with {Rogue} {Scholar} Using the
    Example of {WordPress} {Blogs}},
  date = {2025-05-16},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/72ce4-12298},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Webinar: Blog
Archiving with Rogue Scholar Using the Example of WordPress
Blogs.”</span> May 16, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/72ce4-12298">https://doi.org/10.59350/72ce4-12298</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-05-16-Webinar-Blog-archiving-with-Rogue-Scholar-using-the-example-of-WordPress-Blogs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-05-16-Webinar-Blog-archiving-with-Rogue-Scholar-using-the-example-of-WordPress-Blogs/roguescholar.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="124" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Interviews on Shadow Libraries and AI in Publishing</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In April, two members of our research group were featured in interviews:</p>
<p>Dorothea Strecker, who has been studying shadow libraries for many years, was interviewed by the Norwegian newspaper Klassekampen <span class="citation" data-cites="stormyren_larsen_disse_2025">(Stormyren Larsen and Ugelstad Aas 2025)</span>. The interview was prompted by the investigation “The Unbelievable Scale of AI’s Pirated-Books Problem” published in The Atlantic <span class="citation" data-cites="reisner_unbelievable_2025">(Reisner 2025)</span>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/infomgnt_interview.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Heinz Pampel was interviewed for the @mediasres program on Deutschlandfunk <span class="citation" data-cites="deutschlandfunkde_eigene_2025">(deutschlandfunk.de 2025)</span>. The topic was the AI strategies of academic publishers. The interview was triggered by Politico’s announcement of a Policy Intelligence Assistant <span class="citation" data-cites="cooke_politico_2025">(Cooke 2025)</span>. We’re pleased about the interest in our research!</p>
<p>Further information about our research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-cooke_politico_2025" class="csl-entry">
Cooke, Melissa. 2025. <span>“<span>POLITICO</span> <span>Unveils</span> <span>Policy</span> <span>Intelligence</span> <span>Assistant</span>: <span>An</span> <span>AI</span> <span>Powered</span> <span>Suite</span> for <span>Policy</span> <span>Professionals</span>.”</span> <em>POLITICO</em>. <a href="https://politi.co/4is1z5g">https://politi.co/4is1z5g</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-deutschlandfunkde_eigene_2025" class="csl-entry">
deutschlandfunk.de. 2025. <span>“Eigene <span>KI</span>-<span>Assistenten</span> Und <span>Chatbots</span>: <span>Medienhäuser</span> Starten Neue <span>Anwendungen</span>.”</span> <em>Deutschlandfunk</em>. <a href="https://www.deutschlandfunk.de/eigene-ki-assistenten-und-chatbots-medienhaeuser-starten-neue-anwendungen-100.html">https://www.deutschlandfunk.de/eigene-ki-assistenten-und-chatbots-medienhaeuser-starten-neue-anwendungen-100.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-reisner_unbelievable_2025" class="csl-entry">
Reisner, Alex. 2025. <span>“The <span>Unbelievable</span> <span>Scale</span> of <span>AI</span>’s <span>Pirated</span>-<span>Books</span> <span>Problem</span>.”</span> <em>The Atlantic</em>. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2025/03/libgen-meta-openai/682093/">https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2025/03/libgen-meta-openai/682093/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-stormyren_larsen_disse_2025" class="csl-entry">
Stormyren Larsen, Selma, and Endre Ugelstad Ugelstad Aas. 2025. <span>“Disse Kan Leses Gratis.”</span> <em>Klassekampen.no</em>. <a href="https://klassekampen.no/artikkel/2025-03-27/disse-kan-leses-gratis">https://klassekampen.no/artikkel/2025-03-27/disse-kan-leses-gratis</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Interviews on {Shadow} {Libraries} and {AI} in {Publishing}},
  date = {2025-04-22},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/dp96r-bxb36},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Interviews on Shadow
Libraries and AI in Publishing.”</span> April 22, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/dp96r-bxb36">https://doi.org/10.59350/dp96r-bxb36</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Interviews-on-Shado-Libraries-and-AI-in-Publishing/infomgnt_interview.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access Repositories in Germany</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lisa Mattihas</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Funded by the Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF), our research project Pro OAR DE investigates current challenges in operating institutional repositories (IR) in Germany. Since completing our initial research phase—which included a systematic review and an interview study with IR managers at academic institutions—we have organized four networking forums since November 2024. In this blog post, we provide an overview of these four events.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/Blogpost_image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our inaugural networking forum on <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-preprints">“Institutional Repositories and Preprints”</a>, held on November 19, 2024, attracted 64 participants across Germany. Following an introductory presentation by the project team, <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7060-3670">Lea-Maria Ferguson</a> (Helmholtz Open Science Office) highlighted challenges in quality assurance, standardization, and workflows from submission to maintenance and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9846-5516">Alexander Wagner</a> (Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron DESY) then focused on technical and practical aspects of integrating preprints into institutional repositories and illustrated how preprints are handled at DESY, a Helmholtz Center. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14185122">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>Our second networking forum,“Institutional Repositories and FIS/CRIS”, took place on December 11, 2024, and drew 103 participants. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9846-5516">Daniel Beucke</a> (Göttingen State and University Library) shared practical experiences integrating repositories with research information systems, highlighting challenges in interoperability and emphasizing the importance of networking, standards and persistent identifiers. <a href="https://orcid.org/0009-0004-2098-8076">Malte Kramer</a> (CRIS.NRW, University of Münster) introduced the CRIS.NRW initiative from the federal state of North Rhine-Westphalia, highlighting the interaction between institutional repositories and research information systems while stressing the necessity of compatible input workflows and identifier systems for successful integration. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.14440151">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>The third networking forum on <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-zweitveroeffentlichung/prooarde-zweitveroeffentlichung/">“Institutional Repositories and Zweitveröffentlichung (self-archiving)”</a> took place on January 13, 2025, with 125 participants in attendance. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5994-0820">Sonja Härkönen</a> from the University of Augsburg presented her library’s service-oriented approach to self-archiving based on sustainable and user-friendly workflows, addressing communication challenges with researchers and emphasizing the collaborative role of the open-access.network’s Focus Group on Self-Archiving. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7279-2962">Tomasz Stompor</a> (Cooperative Library Network Berlin-Brandenburg) introduced DeepGreen as a central data hub for automated delivery of publications to repositories, outlining its evolution from a DFG project to an established service. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725628">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>On March 10, 2025, the fourth networking forum on <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/prooarde-monitoring">“On monitoring and reporting with institutional repositories”</a> was held with 100 participants. <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6083-9348">Dirk Pieper</a> and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5959-4999">Julia Bartlewski</a> (University of Bielefeld, openCost) introduced the openCost metadata schema as a standardized exchange format for publication costs and demonstrated its integration within their institutional repository as part of implementing an information budget.</p>
<p><a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8503-1740">Colin Sippl</a> and <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7462-3847">Gernot Deinzer</a> (University of Regensburg), who presented their institution’s experience with integrating publication cost management into their repository, were showing the historical development from 2011 to their current system that handles both article-level costs and publishing agreements. Documentation and slide decks from the event are available through <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15056242">Zenodo</a>.</p>
<p>The insights and discussions from these networking forums, combined with the themed breakout groups held during each event, will form the foundation for developing topic-specific guidelines for open access and IR professionals throughout Germany.</p>
<p>Through these collaborative events, we have created opportunities for the open access community to collectively address key challenges in managing and evolving institutional repositories, identify practical solutions, and strengthen professional exchange across Germany’s IR landscape.</p>
<p>For more information about Pro OAR DE and our upcoming activities, please visit our official <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled sections – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-matthias_pro_2025" class="csl-entry">
Matthias, Lisa, Dirk Pieper, Julia Bartlewski, Colin Sippl, and Gernot Deinzer. 2025. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Publikations</span>- Und <span>Kostenmonitoring</span> Mit Institutionellen <span>Repositorien</span>,”</span> March. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.15056242">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.15056242</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024-1" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Daniel Beucke, and Malte Kramer. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>FIS</span>/<span>CRIS</span>,”</span> December. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14440152">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14440152</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_vernetzungsforum_2025" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Sonja Härkönen, and Tomasz Stompor. 2025. <span>“Vernetzungsforum: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>Zweitveröffentlichung</span>,”</span> January. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725629">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14725629</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wrzesinski_pro_2024" class="csl-entry">
Wrzesinski, Marcel, Alexander Wagner, Lea-Maria Ferguson, and Marcel Meistring. 2024. <span>“Pro <span>OAR</span> <span>DE</span> <span>Vernetzungsforum</span>: <span>Institutionelle</span> <span>Repositorien</span> Und <span>Preprints</span>,”</span> November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14185123">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.14185123</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2025,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Mattihas, Lisa and Onzie Khamis,
    Christopher},
  title = {Networking for the {Advancement} of {Institutional} {Open}
    {Access} {Repositories} in {Germany}},
  date = {2025-04-22},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/s3ddy-gdm33},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Lisa Mattihas, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2025.
<span>“Networking for the Advancement of Institutional Open Access
Repositories in Germany.”</span> April 22, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/s3ddy-gdm33">https://doi.org/10.59350/s3ddy-gdm33</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-22-Networking-for-the-Advancement-of-Institutional-Open-Access-Repositories-in-Germany/Blogpost_image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Is the German Scientific Landscape a Strong Driver for Open Science?</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Catalina Bohórquez Díaz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sharleen Frankenstein</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Henriette Humprecht</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zuhal Nur Kocabiyik</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jannik Kuhs-Ohmann</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Max Liebel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sofie-Lilly Prinada</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Patricia Rocha Dias</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Hendrik Zimnol</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background">Background</h2>
<p>As part of the project module <em>Open Science as a Field of Action for Scientific Institutions</em>, students from the Institute for Library and Information Science at Humboldt University zu Berlin (HU), under the supervision of Prof.&nbsp;Dr.&nbsp;Heinz Pampel, organized an event. During the winter semester of 2024/25, the students examined strategies on how scientific institutions shape and promote the topic of Open Science.</p>
<p>To conclude their work, the project course hosted the event <em>“Is the German Scientific Landscape a Strong Driver for Open Science? – Open Science as a Field of Action for Scientific Institutions”</em> on February 4, 2025, at the Einstein Center Digital Future (ECDF) in Berlin.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/PSE_Blogpost_image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="presentations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presentations">Presentations</h2>
<p>Open Science refers to efforts to implement various approaches to an open scientific practice <span class="citation" data-cites="unesco2021">(UNESCO 2021)</span>, aiming to promote transparent and inclusive science.</p>
<p>At the beginning of the event, three invited speakers – Dr.&nbsp;Lisa Kressin from the Leibniz Association, Dr.&nbsp;Stefan Skupien from the Berlin University Alliance (BUA), and Marcel Meistring from the Helmholtz Centre for Geosciences (GFZ) – presented different approaches taken by libraries and research institutions regarding Open Science.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Lisa Kressin (Leibniz Association) began her presentation by discussing the crucial role of infrastructures in promoting Open Science. She also emphasized the significance of self-governance in science for the development of Open Science. According to Kressin, Open Science must be developed in close collaboration with the scientific community rather than being purely politically motivated. However, she acknowledged that political engagement remains essential to advancing Open Science. She highlighted the potential of Open Science in strengthening research quality and reinforcing scientific transparency.</p>
<p>Furthermore, she addressed the challenges of Open Science in practice. Due to varying knowledge cultures, it is impossible to impose uniform expectations on all stakeholders. She advocated for a practical approach to Open Science and stressed that funding remains a pressing issue. Kressin saw great potential in networking among scientific organizations to advance Open Science.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Stefan Skupien (BUA) also highlighted the importance of Open Science networks and collaboration, as many Open Science challenges require cooperative solutions. He underscored the potential of Open Science for research and introduced measures implemented by the BUA to promote it. Besides infrastructure development, Skupien focused on Open Science education and monitoring Open Science practices. These topics are also supported by the BUA through Open Science Fellowships.</p>
<p>Another initiative he mentioned was the establishment of <em>Open Science Ambassadors</em>, who serve as multipliers, spreading Open Science practices within the scientific community. He pointed out that the importance of Open Science varies across faculties within the BUA institutions. Therefore, the BUA aims to establish a reflective and discipline-specific approach to Open Science practices.</p>
<p>In the final presentation, Marcel Meistring from the GFZ Helmholtz Centre for Geosciences emphasized the importance of extensive consulting, research-support services, and support offerings in the field of publishing research results and research data management. He provided insights into the Open Science policy of the Helmholtz Association and the Open Science-related guidelines of the GFZ. He stressed that such policies serve as crucial guidelines in establishing an Open Science culture within scientific institutions.</p>
<p>Additionally, he explained the relevance of adhering to standards and utilizing persistent identifiers (PIDs) for providing, archiving, storing, publishing, and linking texts, research data, and research software. The use of standards and PIDs is crucial for the efficient implementation of Open Science. Meistring also presented current efforts by the Helmholtz Association to develop new quality indicators for research data and software publications. The goal is to adopt a broader perspective on research performance, recognizing published research data and software as valuable research outputs based on specific quality criteria.</p>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>Following the presentations, the speakers engaged in a panel discussion, addressing questions regarding the further development of Open Science and potential fields of action, with additional contributions and questions from the audience. The discussion highlighted the necessity of further advancing Open Science in Germany. The panelists supported additional cross-organizational projects similar to the DEAL initiative.</p>
<p>As repeatedly emphasized in the presentations, intensified collaboration among various Open Science stakeholders is essential to effectively address challenges. However, difficulties arise due to funding constraints and a lack of institutional initiative. The monitoring of Open Science practices was identified as a crucial field of action for advancing Open Science. Additionally, promoting information literacy was deemed essential for the positive development of Open Science.</p>
<p>The discussion also touched upon the integration of Open Science principles into university curricula across all disciplines so that future researchers develop awareness of Open Science’s opportunities and challenges. In this context, the BUA Ambassadors initiative was praised for facilitating communication and exchange across different scientific domains, from which other institutions could also benefit.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In summary, although Open Science has been a relevant topic in Germany for several years, the scientific community still does not allocate it sufficient attention and significance. Enhanced training in the form of workshops and advisory services on Open Science, as well as adequate resources, are crucial for further advancing Open Science in Germany. In this regard, sustainable funding, stronger collaboration among stakeholders, increased resource allocation in infrastructures, and greater public involvement are needed.</p>
<p>Given the budgetary and geopolitical challenges for open and networked science, the speakers expressed some concerns about future developments. Nevertheless, they emphasized the importance of embedding and promoting Open Science in a cooperative and international context to align its progress with UNESCO recommendations.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-deutsche_unesco-kommission_open_2020" class="csl-entry">
Deutsche UNESCO-Kommission, ed. 2020. <em>Open Science: <span>Perspektiven</span> Aus <span>Deutschland</span> Auf Die <span>Erarbeitung</span> Der Geplanten <span>Empfehlung</span> Der <span>UNESCO</span> = <span>UNESCO</span> Recommendation in <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span></em>. Berlin: Deutsche UNESCO-Kommission e.V.
</div>
<div id="ref-unesco2021" class="csl-entry">
UNESCO. 2021. <span>“UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.54677/MNMH8546">https://doi.org/10.54677/MNMH8546</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{catalina_bohórquez_díaz2025,
  author = {Catalina Bohórquez Díaz, Laura and Frankenstein, Sharleen
    and Humprecht, Henriette and Onzie Khamis, Christopher and Nur
    Kocabiyik, Zuhal and Kuhs-Ohmann, Jannik and Liebel, Max and
    Prinada, Sofie-Lilly and Rocha Dias, Patricia and Zimnol, Hendrik},
  title = {Is the {German} {Scientific} {Landscape} a {Strong} {Driver}
    for {Open} {Science?}},
  date = {2025-04-17},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/vc1ht-2mz23},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-catalina_bohórquez_díaz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Catalina Bohórquez Díaz, Laura, Sharleen Frankenstein, Henriette
Humprecht, Christopher Onzie Khamis, Zuhal Nur Kocabiyik, Jannik
Kuhs-Ohmann, Max Liebel, Sofie-Lilly Prinada, Patricia Rocha Dias, and
Hendrik Zimnol. 2025. <span>“Is the German Scientific Landscape a Strong
Driver for Open Science?”</span> April 17, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/vc1ht-2mz23">https://doi.org/10.59350/vc1ht-2mz23</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-17-Is-the-German-Scientific-Landscape-a-Strong-Driver-for-Open-Science/PSE_Blogpost_image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar zur Erfassung von Publikationskosten</title>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Karin Ilg</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Am 28.03.2025 veranstaltete das Projekt OA Datenpraxis <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_datenpraxis_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span> das erste Webinar zum Thema ”Erfassung von Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland”. In dem Webinar wurden Ergebnisse einer Umfrage vorgestellt, die im Jahr 2024 durchgeführt wurde. Die Umfrage, die im Dialog mit Vertreter<em>innen von <a href="https://deal-konsortium.de/">DEAL</a> entwickelt wurde, erhob, wie Daten zu Publikationskosten aktuell an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland erfasst werden. Adressiert wurden Vertreter</em>innen von Universitäten, Fachhochschulen, Instituten außeruniversitärer Forschungseinrichtungen sowie Ressortforschungseinrichtungen des Bundes. Von 583 eingeladenen Personen beteiligten sich 258 (44,3 %) an der Umfrage. Die Umfrage ist die erste umfassende Erhebung zur Erfassung von Publikationskosten in Deutschland. An der Veranstaltung nahmen erfreulicherweise über 200 Personen aus Wissenschaft, Verwaltung, Informationsinfrastruktur und Forschungsförderung teil.</p>
<p>In diesem Beitrag werden kurz einige zentrale Punkte der Veranstaltung zusammengefasst: Ergebnisse der Umfrage, Fragen aus dem Kreis der Teilnehmenden, sowie einige Diskussionspunkte aus der abschließenden Paneldiskussion.</p>
<section id="ergebnisse-der-umfrage" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ergebnisse-der-umfrage">Ergebnisse der Umfrage</h2>
<p>Nach der Begrüßung und Einführung wurden zentrale Ergebnisse der Studie vorgestellt: Während die systematische Erfassung von Publikationen und Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen durchaus verbreitet ist, haben viele Einrichtungen diese noch nicht fest etabliert und nutzen zudem das Potenzial dieser Daten noch nicht voll aus. Für die Finanzierung von Open-Access-Publikationen stellen Publikationsfonds eine tragende Säule dar. Die Etablierung von Informationsbudgets dagegen befindet sich noch in der Aufbauphase. Zur Förderung der Open-Access-Transformation sollte die Finanzierung weiter untersucht werden. Diese und weitere Ergebnisse können den Vortragsfolien <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_oa_2025">(Strecker, Pampel, and Höfting 2025)</span> entnommen werden. Eine Publikation dazu ist in Vorbereitung.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="fragen-der-teilnehmenden" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fragen-der-teilnehmenden">Fragen der Teilnehmenden</h2>
<p>Im Anschluss an die Ergebnispräsentation hatten die Teilnehmer:innen des Webinars die Gelegenheit, Nachfragen zu stellen. Interesse weckten beispielsweise die für das Monitoring in den Einrichtungen genutzten Tools und die Verwendung der Daten für die strategische Planung. Kritisch diskutiert wurde die Belastbarkeit von bestehenden Datensammlungen zu Open Access. Mehrere Fragen adressierten die Notwendigkeit von Standardisierung in diesem Bereich.</p>
</section>
<section id="paneldiskussion-mit-mitgliedern-der-deal-gruppe" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paneldiskussion-mit-mitgliedern-der-deal-gruppe">Paneldiskussion mit Mitgliedern der DEAL-Gruppe</h2>
<p>An der Paneldiskussion nahm seitens der DEAL-Gruppe Karin Ilg (Hochschule Bielefeld) teil (weitere Mitglieder der DEAL-Gruppe mussten ihre Teilnahme kurzfristig absagen) . und teilte ihre Perspektive auf die Ergebnisse. Sie hob positiv hervor, dass einige Einrichtungen trotz schwieriger Rahmenbedingungen – wie der teilweise dezentralen Erfassung durch mehrere Abteilungen in verschiedenen Systemen – bereits einen systematischen Überblick über ihre Publikationskosten erreicht haben. Gleichzeitig betonte sie, dass flächendeckende Monitoringaktivitäten noch fehlten. In dieser Phase der Open-Access-Transformation sei eine aktivere Rolle der Leitungsebenen sowie eine stärkere Vernetzung zwischen Einrichtungen erforderlich. Auf die Herausforderungen bei der Etablierung von Informationsbudgets angesprochen verwies sie auf erhebliche Hürden, stellte aber auch die strukturbildenden Effekte von Programmen wie <a href="https://www.dfg.de/de/foerderung/foerdermoeglichkeiten/programme/infrastruktur/lis/lis-foerderangebote/open-access-publikationskosten">Open-Access-Publikationskosten</a> der DFG und von DEAL heraus. Die communitybasierte Entwicklung einheitlicher Standards der Datenerfassung stelle einen dringenden Handlungsbedarf dar.</p>
</section>
<section id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis">Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.oadatenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a> ist ein gemeinsames DFG-Projekt des <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de">Instituts für Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a>, des <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> und der <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de">Niedersächsischen Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen</a>.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis finden Sie auf der <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/events.html">Webseite</a> des Projektes. Weitere Informationen zu unserer Arbeit am Lehrstuhl Information Management finden Sie auf unserer <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">offiziellen Webseite</a>.</p>
<p>Dieser Text - mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Teilen - ist lizenziert unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_datenpraxis_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Najko Jahn, Roland Bertelmann, Wolfram Horstmann, Laura Rothfritz, Lea Maria Ferguson, Birgit Schmidt, and Anna Stisser. 2024. <span>“Datenpraxis Zur <span>Gestaltung</span> Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Transformation</span> - <span>Analyse</span>, <span>Empfehlung</span>, <span>Training</span> &amp; <span>Vernetzung</span> (<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span>).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10794298">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10794298</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_oa_2025" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea, Heinz Pampel, and Jonas Höfting. 2025. <span>“<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span> <span>Webinar</span>: <span>Erfassung</span> von <span>Publikationskosten</span> an Wissenschaftlichen <span>Einrichtungen</span> in <span>Deutschland</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15076512">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15076512</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{höfting2025,
  author = {Höfting, Jonas and Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz and
    Ilg, Karin},
  title = {Rückblick: {OA} {Datenpraxis} {Webinar} Zur {Erfassung} von
    {Publikationskosten}},
  date = {2025-04-14},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/c7d5j-rw005},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-höfting2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Höfting, Jonas, Dorothea Strecker, Heinz Pampel, and Karin Ilg. 2025.
<span>“Rückblick: OA Datenpraxis Webinar Zur Erfassung von
Publikationskosten.”</span> April 14, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/c7d5j-rw005">https://doi.org/10.59350/c7d5j-rw005</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-04-14-Rueckblick-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-zur-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten/logo_oa_datenpraxis(2).png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Information Management Research Group at the BID Kongress 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-14-the-information-management-research-group-at-the-bid-kongress/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are pleased to announce that the projects <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/index.html">OA Datenpraxis</a> and <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> of the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement">Information Management Research Group</a> from the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de">Berlin School of Library and Information Science</a> at the <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/de">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a> will be represented at this year’s BID Congress. Furthermore, Heinz Pampel will be involved in several other events during the BID Congress.</p>
<section id="oa-datenpraxis" class="level1">
<h1>OA Datenpraxis</h1>
<p>The Hands-on Lab titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/sessions/79">Open-Access-Monitoring-Dashboards mit Quarto</a>’ will take place on June 24th from 16:00–18:00 in Salon London. <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/kontakt/personen-a-z/personendetails/person/sophia-doerner/">Sophia Dörner</a> will give a practical introduction to the development of a simple dashboard for the (open access) publication output of research institutions using Quarto, an open-source publication system. Previous knowledge of the R programming language or Quarto is not required, but helpful. Please bring a laptop and create a <a href="https://posit.cloud/plans/free">Posit Cloud account</a> in advance.</p>
<p>The lecture titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/presentations/273">Recording of publication costs at scientific institutions in Germany</a>’ will take place on June 27th from 11 to 11:30 in the Focke-Wulf Saal. Dorothea Strecker, Heinz Pampel and Jonas Höfting will present the results of a survey conducted in 2024 as part of the OA Datenpraxis project. The survey investigated how data on publication costs are currently recorded at scientific institutions in Germany. Representatives of universities, universities of applied sciences, institutes of non-university research organisations (Fraunhofer Society, Helmholtz Association, Leibniz Association and Max Planck Society) and federal departmental research institutions were addressed.</p>
</section>
<section id="infra-wiss-blogs" class="level1">
<h1>Infra Wiss Blogs</h1>
<p>The lecture titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/presentations/307">Mapping German scholarly blogs - results and impulses</a>’ will take place on June 26th from 11 to 11:30 in Hall 4.1/Room II. Catharina Ochsner, Heinz Pampel and Jonas Höfting from the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement">Chair of Information Management</a> of the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de">Institute of Library and Information Science</a> at <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/de">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a> (HU Berlin), will present the results of a data collection of over 800 German scholarly blogs, which were analysed for infrastructural aspects. In addition, impulses will be given for academic libraries to make a contribution to ensuring the long-term accessibility of blogs.</p>
<p>The Hands-on Lab titled ‘<a href="https://bid2025.abstractserver.com/program/#/details/sessions/84">Libraries as operating and preserving institutions for scholarly blogs</a>’ will also take place on June 26th from 2 to 4 pm in the Salon Oslo. In the hands-on lab, participants will discuss the role of libraries in the development, dissemination and preservation of scholarly blogs under the organisation and moderation of experts from the scholarly blog landscape. Aspects of technology, organisation and framework conditions for safeguarding blogs will be discussed in round tables. The Hands-on Lab will be led by <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/teaminfomanagement">Catharina Ochsner</a> (HU Berlin) and supported by <a href="https://heinzpampel.de/">Heinz Pampel</a> (HU Berlin), <a href="https://verfassungsblog.de/author/elena-di-rosa/">Elena Di Rosa</a> (<a href="https://verfassungsblog.de/">Verfassungsblog</a>), <a href="https://front-matter.io/team">Martin Fenner</a> (<a href="https://front-matter.%20io/">Front Matter</a>), Sven Ködel (<a href="https://www.dhi-paris.fr/home.html">German Historical Institute Paris</a>), <a href="https://www.gesis.org/institut/ueber-uns/mitarbeitendenverzeichnis/person/Charmaine.Voigt">Charmaine Voigt</a> (<a href="https://www.gesis.org/home">GESIS: Leibniz Institute for Social Sciences</a>) and <a href="https://www.dnb.de/SharedDocs/Kontaktdaten/DE/wolderingBritta.html">Britta Woldering</a> from the <a href="https://www.dnb.de/DE/Home/home_node.html">German National Library</a>. To register for the workshop, please send an E-Mail to Catharina Ochsner.</p>
</section>
<section id="other-work" class="level1">
<h1>Other Work</h1>
<p>Furthermore Heinz Pampel will be part of two lectures and a Hands-on-Lab. Together with <a href="https://vivo.tib.eu/fis/display/n0000-0001-5322-0478">Judith Luwdig</a> (<a href="https://www.tib.eu/de/">Technische Informationsbibliothek Hannover</a>) and <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/zb/kontakt/zb-leitung">Bernhard Mittermaier</a> (<a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de">Research Center Jülich</a>) Prof.&nbsp;Pampel will give a talk on ‘AI clauses in licence agreements’. The talk will take place on thursday June, 26th between 10 and 10:30 am in the Hanse Saal. Additionally Prof.&nbsp;Pampel will be part of the lecture ‘Strategic approaches to intensify the OA transformation: perspectives for science organisations’ alongside <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/team-und-kontakt/">Lea Maria Ferguson</a> (<a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a>), <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/team-und-kontakt/">Marc Lange</a> (<a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a>), <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/zb/kontakt/zb-leitung">Bernhard Mittermaier</a> (<a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de">Research Center Jülich</a>) and <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/team-und-kontakt/">Meistring</a> (<a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a>). The talk will take place on June 26th from 9 to 9:30 am in Room 5 in hall 4.1. Lastly Prof.&nbsp;Pampel will lead the Hands-on Lab ‘Sustainably financing open access infrastructures’ at the 26th of June from 4:30 to 6 pm in the Salon London. Together with <a href="https://www.zbw.eu/de/ueber-zbw/profil/mitarbeiterprofile/profil-olaf-siegert">Olaf Siegert</a> (<a href="https://www.zbw.eu/de/">ZBW - Leibniz Information Centre for Economics</a>), <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de/zb/kontakt/zb-leitung">Bernhard Mittermaier</a> (<a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/de">Research Center Jülich</a>), <a href="https://www.dfg.de/de/ueber-uns/geschaeftsstelle/personen/michael-geuenich-165456">Michael Geuenich</a> (<a href="https://www.dfg.de/de">German Research Foundation</a>), <a href="https://www.zib.de/members/rusch">Beate Rusch</a> (<a href="https://www.zib.de/index.php/">Zuse Institute Berlin</a>) and Silke Weisheit (<a href="https://www.uni-regensburg.de/bibliothek/startseite/index.html">University Library Regensburg</a>) the participants will discuss developments and practical reports on sustainable Open Access financing. To register for the workshop, please send an E-Mail to Heinz Pampel.</p>
<p>We look forward to seeing you at this year’s BID Congress and to discuss our projects with you. If you have any questions regarding the BID Congress or the events, please do not hesitate to contact Dorothea Strecker and Catharina Ochsner.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {The {Information} {Management} {Research} {Group} at the
    {BID} {Kongress} 2025},
  date = {2025-03-14},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/txet3-efm12},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, Dorothea Strecker, and Heinz Pampel. 2025.
<span>“The Information Management Research Group at the BID Kongress
2025.”</span> March 14, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/txet3-efm12">https://doi.org/10.59350/txet3-efm12</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-14-the-information-management-research-group-at-the-bid-kongress/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-14-the-information-management-research-group-at-the-bid-kongress/BID.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OA Datenpraxis Webinar: Erfassung von Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Wir laden Sie herzlich zur Veranstaltung “OA Datenpraxis Webinar: Erfassung von Publikationskosten an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland” ein, die am 28.03.2025 von 10:00 bis 11:00 CET über Zoom stattfindet.</p>
<p>In dem Webinar werden Ergebnisse einer Umfrage <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_datenpraxis_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span> vorgestellt, die im Rahmen des von der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) geförderten Projekts OA Datenpraxis <span class="citation" data-cites="strecker_survey_2024">(Strecker and Pampel 2024)</span> im Jahr 2024 durchgeführt wurde.</p>
<p>Die Umfrage, die im Dialog mit Vertreter:innen der DEAL-Untergruppe “Kommunikation” entwickelt wurde, erhob, wie Daten zu Publikationskosten aktuell an wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland erfasst werden. Adressiert wurden Vertreter*innen von Universitäten, Fachhochschulen, Instituten außeruniversitärer Forschungseinrichtungen sowie Ressortforschungseinrichtungen des Bundes. Von 583 eingeladenen Personen beteiligten sich 258 (44,3 %) an der Umfrage. Die Umfrage ist die erste umfassende Erhebung zur Erfassung von Publikationskosten in Deutschland.</p>
<p>Dieses Webinar richtet sich an Professionals, die sich für Open-Access-Monitoring, insbesondere die Erfassung von Open-Access-Publikationskosten, interessieren.</p>
<section id="programm" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="programm">Programm</h2>
<p>Nach einer Präsentation der Umfrageergebnisse haben Teilnehmende die Möglichkeit, Fragen zur Umfrage zu stellen. Anschließend werden einige zentrale Aspekte der Erfassung von Publikationskosten in einer Paneldiskussion mit Mitgliedern der DEAL-Gruppe erörtert.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Begrüßung durch Heinz Pampel (5 Minuten)</p></li>
<li><p>Vorstellung der Umfrageergebnisse durch Dorothea Strecker (30 Minuten)</p></li>
<li><p>Q &amp; A zur Umfrage (10 Minuten)</p></li>
<li><p>Paneldiskussion mit Mitgliedern der DEAL-Gruppe (15 Minuten)</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="anmeldung" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="anmeldung">Anmeldung</h2>
<p>Eine Anmeldung zum Webinar ist über den folgenden Link möglich: <a href="https://hu-berlin.zoom-x.de/webinar/register/WN_pKTlDzjsQwC7QspLxwMHCg">Link zur Anmeldung</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/logo_oa_datenpraxis(1).png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weitere-informationen-zu-oa-datenpraxis">Weitere Informationen zu OA Datenpraxis</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.oadatenpraxis.de">OA Datenpraxis</a> ist ein gemeinsames DFG-Projekt des <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de">Instituts für Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</a>, des <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> und der <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de">Niedersächsischen Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek Göttingen</a>.</p>
<p>Aktuelle Veranstaltungen von OA Datenpraxis finden Sie auf der <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/events.html">Projektwebseite</a>.</p>
<p>Weitere Informationen zum Lehrstuhl Information Management finden Sie auf unserer <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">offiziellen Webseite</a>.</p>
<p>Dieser Text - mit Ausnahme von Zitaten und anderweitig gekennzeichneten Teilen - ist lizenziert unter der <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_datenpraxis_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Najko Jahn, Roland Bertelmann, Wolfram Horstmann, Laura Rothfritz, Lea Maria Ferguson, Birgit Schmidt, and Anna Stisser. 2024. <span>“Datenpraxis Zur <span>Gestaltung</span> Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Transformation</span> - <span>Analyse</span>, <span>Empfehlung</span>, <span>Training</span> &amp; <span>Vernetzung</span> (<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span>).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10794298</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-strecker_survey_2024" class="csl-entry">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“Survey Announcement: <span>Recording</span> Publication Costs at Research Performing Institutions in <span>Germany</span>.”</span> <em>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/9z58m-vwv42">https://doi.org/10.59350/9z58m-vwv42</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz and Höfting, Jonas},
  title = {OA {Datenpraxis} {Webinar:} {Erfassung} von
    {Publikationskosten} an Wissenschaftlichen {Einrichtungen} in
    {Deutschland}},
  date = {2025-03-07},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/wnnk6-rzr69},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, Heinz Pampel, and Jonas Höfting. 2025. <span>“OA
Datenpraxis Webinar: Erfassung von Publikationskosten an
Wissenschaftlichen Einrichtungen in Deutschland.”</span> March 7, 2025.
<a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/wnnk6-rzr69">https://doi.org/10.59350/wnnk6-rzr69</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-03-07-OA-Datenpraxis-Webinar-Erfassung-von-Publikationskosten-an-wissenschaftlichen-Einrichtungen-in-Deutschland/logo_oa_datenpraxis(1).png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Critical Data Discourses: A Lecture Series on the Ethics of Research Data</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Katrin Frisch</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In a time when research data is increasingly at the heart of research integrity, discussions about data sharing, openness, and reusability have gained prominence. Yet, the ethical complexities surrounding research data—who collects it, how it is used, and whose interests it serves—are often sidelined. The <a href="https://critical-data-discourse.quarto.pub/">Critical Data Discourses</a> lecture series seeks to shift the focus from purely technical concerns to broader ethical, social, and political reflections on data.</p>
<p>Discussions about data in research are often dominated by principles like FAIR <span class="citation" data-cites="wilkinsonFAIRGuidingPrinciples2016">(Wilkinson et al. 2016)</span>, which aim to standardize and optimize the findability, accessibility, interoperability and reusability of research data. While these principles are important, they do not fully capture the ethical dimensions of data collection and use. Questions of fairness, responsibility, power dynamics, and care work in data practices are not covered by these principles.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/poster.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>At the same time, international discussions have introduced complementary frameworks, such as the CARE principles <span class="citation" data-cites="Carroll-2020">(Carroll et al. 2020)</span>—developed from Indigenous governance perspectives—which emphasize the social and relational aspects of data. These principles highlight how data is not just a neutral resource but deeply intertwined with historical, social, and ethical considerations.</p>
<p>With this lecture series, we aim to bring together data professionals and critical scholars to examine the evolving landscape of data ethics and adjacent questions about data politics and data justice. Through a series of expert talks, we are exploring issues that are often missing from mainstream research data discussions, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>The ethics of data collection and the ethical considerations behind it</li>
<li>The role of domain-specific ethical considerations in fields like humanities, medicine, and AI research</li>
<li>The limitations of existing data frameworks and their unintended consequences</li>
<li>Data gaps and missing data—what is left out of research and why</li>
<li>The influence of AI and automation on knowledge production and discrimination</li>
<li>The impact of historical injustices on contemporary data practices</li>
</ul>
<p>Our motivation for organizing this series stems from a shared interest in rethinking data practices beyond efficiency and compliance, and centering on issues of ethics, justice, transparency, and responsibility. More information is available <a href="https://critical-data-discourse.quarto.pub/">on our website</a>.</p>
<p>After a successful launch with over 100 participants in our first session, we are excited to continue the discussions in our upcoming talks on data ethics, AI, and power structures in research data.</p>
<p>Here is a look at what’s next (in German):</p>
<section id="session-3-04.03.2025-14-16-uhr-ethik-des-sammelns" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-3-04.03.2025-14-16-uhr-ethik-des-sammelns">Session 3: 04.03.2025, 14-16 Uhr Ethik des Sammelns</h3>
<p>The Dark Side of DNA: Exposing the Ethical Lapses That Threaten Human Genetics</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Yves Moreau, University of Leuven, Belgium</em></p>
<p>Unborn digital. Challenges in data publications on collections of human embryos and fetuses</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Michael Markert, FAU Erlangen-Nürnberg</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/56827" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/56827</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-4-20.03.2025-14-16-uhr-fachspezifische-datenethik" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-4-20.03.2025-14-16-uhr-fachspezifische-datenethik">Session 4: 20.03.2025, 14-16 Uhr Fachspezifische Datenethik</h3>
<p>Ethische Kontrollinstanzen für die Literaturwissenschaft? Über Freiheit und Verantwortung im literaturwissenschaftlichen Datenumgang</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Katharina Fürholzer, Universität Koblenz</em></p>
<p>Ethische Aspekte der Nutzung generativer KI in der Wissenschaft – ein medizinethischer Blickwinkel</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Theresa Willem, TU München &amp; Helmholtz Zentrum München - Deutsches Forschungszentrum für Gesundheit und Umwelt</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/85362" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/85362</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-5-03.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-gaps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-5-03.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-gaps">Session 5: 03.04.2025 14-16 Uhr Data Gaps</h3>
<p>Die Polizeiliche Kriminalstatistik (PKS) – belastbare Grundlage für gesellschaftspolitische Debatten oder verzerrtes Datensammelsammelsurium?</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Martin Thüne, FHVD - Fachbereich Polizei</em></p>
<p>Datenbank zu Rechtsterrorismus: Schwierigkeiten und Chancen bei der Datenerhebung.</p>
<p><em>Vortragender: Thilo Manemann, Center for Monitoring, Analyse und Strategie</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/37719" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/37719</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-6-10.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-agency-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-6-10.04.2025-14-16-uhr-data-agency-ai">Session 6: 10.04.2025, 14-16 Uhr Data Agency &amp; AI</h3>
<p>Die neue Unsichtbarkeit von Frauen: Von synthetischen Bildern und ethischen Folgen</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Eugenia Stamboliev, Universität Wien</em></p>
<p>More or less discrimination? Psychological (and other) AIs in personnel selection</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Helena Mihaljević, Hochschule für Technik und Wirtschaft, Berlin</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/64446" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/64446</a></p>
</section>
<section id="session-7-29.04.2025-14-16-uhr-abschlussveranstaltung" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-7-29.04.2025-14-16-uhr-abschlussveranstaltung">Session 7: 29.04.2025, 14-16 Uhr Abschlussveranstaltung</h3>
<p>Menschenrechtsbasierter Zugang zu Daten: der Monitor Gewalt gegen Frauen - Indikatoren, Arbeit mit administrativen Daten und ethische Implikationen</p>
<p><em>Vortragende: Jolanda Krok, Miriam Schroer-Hippel, Lilly-Allegra Hikisch</em></p>
<p>Anmeldung: <a href="https://hu.berlin/74686" class="uri">https://hu.berlin/74686</a></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Carroll-2020" class="csl-entry">
Carroll, Stephanie Russo, Ibrahim Garba, Oscar L. Figueroa-Rodríguez, Jarita Holbrook, Raymond Lovett, Simeon Materechera, Mark Parsons, et al. 2020. <span>“The <span>CARE</span> Principles for Indigenous Data Governance.”</span> <em>Data Science Journal</em>, November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2020-043">https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2020-043</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wilkinsonFAIRGuidingPrinciples2016" class="csl-entry">
Wilkinson, Mark D., Michel Dumontier, IJsbrand Jan Aalbersberg, Gabrielle Appleton, Myles Axton, Arie Baak, Niklas Blomberg, et al. 2016. <span>“The <span>FAIR Guiding Principles</span> for Scientific Data Management and Stewardship.”</span> <em>Scientific Data</em> 3 (March): 160018.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2025,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura and Frisch, Katrin},
  title = {Critical {Data} {Discourses:} {A} {Lecture} {Series} on the
    {Ethics} of {Research} {Data}},
  date = {2025-02-21},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/6dp70-2j455},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura, and Katrin Frisch. 2025. <span>“Critical Data
Discourses: A Lecture Series on the Ethics of Research Data .”</span>
February 21, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/6dp70-2j455">https://doi.org/10.59350/6dp70-2j455</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-21-Critical-Data-Discourses-A-Lecture-Series-on-the-Ethics-of-Research-Data/pic.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Promoting Open Science at the Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin as BUA Open Science Ambassadors</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/bua_logo.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The Ambassadors for Open Science program of the <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/index.html">Berlin University Alliance, BUA</a> aims to promote the knowledge and application of Open Science in various subjects. As Open Science experts and enthusiasts, the ambassadors show researchers, students and decision-makers at their institution how they can benefit from and make use of Open Science infrastructure <span class="citation" data-cites="berlin_university_alliance_auftakt_2024">(Alliance 2024a)</span>.</p>
<p>We are pleased to announce that <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/index.html">Dorothea Strecker</a> and <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Catharina Ochsner</a> from the Berlin School of Library and Information Science will serve as the Open Science ambassadors for the <a href="https://www.hu-berlin.de/en/institutions/faculties-and-departments/fac-arts-humanities/standardseite">Faculty of Arts and Humanities</a> at Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin (HU) until 31 July 2025.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/core/index.html">Center for Open and Responsible Research (CORe)</a> of the Berlin University Alliance (BUA) supports the ambassadors with financial resources for training and networking activities or for the organization of further education events for research colleagues, decision-makers and students <span class="citation" data-cites="berlin_university_alliance_open_2024">(Alliance 2024b)</span>. We will announce future activities on our <a href="https://infomgnt.org/">lab blog</a> and our <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events">official website</a>. We are looking forward to hosting events as part of the Open Science ambassador program and to facilitate the adoption of Open Science practices at the HU.</p>
<p>If you have questions or wishes you can reach us via e-mail under dorothea.strecker@hu-berlin.de or catharina.ochsner@hu-berlin.de. More detailed information on the Ambassadors for Open Science program can be found <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/os-botschafter-innen/index.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-berlin_university_alliance_auftakt_2024" class="csl-entry">
Alliance, Berlin University. 2024a. <span>“Auftakt Für Neu Ernannte <span>BUA</span> <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span> <span>Ambassadors</span>.”</span> <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/items/2024/240924-open-science-ambassadors.html">https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/items/2024/240924-open-science-ambassadors.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-berlin_university_alliance_open_2024" class="csl-entry">
———. 2024b. <span>“Die <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span> <span>Botschafter</span> Der <span>Berlin</span> <span>University</span> <span>Alliance</span>.”</span> <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/os-botschafter-innen/index.html">https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/commitments/research-quality/openx/os-botschafter-innen/index.html</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Strecker, Dorothea},
  title = {Promoting {Open} {Science} at the {Humboldt-Universität} Zu
    {Berlin} as {BUA} {Open} {Science} {Ambassadors}},
  date = {2025-02-05},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/ja4m1-92098},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Dorothea Strecker. 2025. <span>“Promoting Open
Science at the Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin as BUA Open Science
Ambassadors.”</span> February 5, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/ja4m1-92098">https://doi.org/10.59350/ja4m1-92098</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-Promoting-Open-Science-at-the-Humboldt-Universität-zu-Berlin-as-BUA-Open-Science-Ambassadors/Unbenannt.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="68" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What happens when public data infrastructures aren’t save? A look at past and current developments in the US</title>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-What-happens-when-public-data-infrastructures-arent-save/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In my PhD research, I look at DataRescue or Data Refuge movements, for example through the work of the <a href="https://envirodatagov.org/">Environmental Data and Governance Initiative</a> (EDGI) <span class="citation" data-cites="EnvironmentalDataGovernance">(<span>“Environmental <span>Data</span> &amp; <span>Governance Initiative</span>”</span> n.d.)</span> to understand how people respond when they fear data is at risk. I’m particularly interested in what these efforts reveal about how public data infrastructures actually work—not just as systems of information storage, but as objects of political struggle.</p>
<p>This research started quite some time ago with an overarching topic of trust and distrust in public data infrastructures <span class="citation" data-cites="rothfritzUnderstandingMistrustDistrust2024">(Rothfritz 2024a)</span>. I planned for the first iteration of the DataRescue movement to serve as a case study for this research <span class="citation" data-cites="rothfritzUnderstandingTrustDistrust2024">(Rothfritz 2024b)</span>. Of course, I did not anticipate that there would be another series of events which would lead to the loss of access to public information and data in the U.S. so soon.</p>
<section id="rescuing-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rescuing-data">Rescuing Data</h3>
<p>In 2016, a group of librarians, archivists, and environmental activists saw the writing on the wall: the incoming U.S. administration might threaten access to crucial federal climate data. What followed was a series of DataRescue events: community-led efforts to archive and preserve environmental datasets that many feared would be deleted, altered, or buried in bureaucratic obscurity <span class="citation" data-cites="janzMaintainingAccessPublic2017 currieBackupsFutureArchival2018">(Janz 2017; Currie and Paris 2018)</span></p>
<p>Fast forward to 2025. Another major political shift is unfolding in the U.S., and with it, new concerns about the integrity and accessibility of public data. This time around, large amounts of public federal information such as websites <span class="citation" data-cites="singerThousandsUSGovernment2025a">(Singer 2025)</span> and data <span class="citation" data-cites="koeblerArchivistsWorkIdentify2025a">(Koebler 2025)</span> are disappearing from public access again. The scale and breadth of which kind of information is disappearing is arguably larger though - it concerns not just environmental data and climate change mentions on websites, but also for example health data and information from the Centers for Disease and Control Prevention (CDC) <span class="citation" data-cites="sunCDCRemovesGender2025 coxLookFederalHealth2025">(Sun, Keating, and Nirappil 2025; Cox et al. 2025)</span>. Efforts seem to be more strategic and orchestrated.</p>
<p>The good news is that at least to a pretty far extent preparations were taking place before the Trump administration took office in January. For example, all federal websites were archived through the <a href="https://eotarchive.org">End-Of-Term Web Archive</a>, a project which routinely has been doing this for administration changes in the U.S. since 2008 <span class="citation" data-cites="EndTermWeb">(<span>“End of <span>Term Web Archive</span>”</span> n.d.)</span>. A dataset of CDC data uploaded before January 28th, 2025 <a href="https://archive.org/details/20250128-cdc-datasets">is available on the Internet Archive</a>. EDGI and the <a href="https://screening-tools.com">Public Environmental Data Project</a> have worked ahead to archive crucial environmental data <span class="citation" data-cites="edgiWhyEDGIArchiving2025">(EDGI 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>There are quite a few other initiatives taking place at the moment. A good overview resource is collected through IASSIST on this <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/15ZRxHqbhGDHCXo7Hqi_Vcy4Q50ZItLblIFaY3s7LBLw/edit?userstoinvite=spacific@gmail.com&amp;sharingaction=manageaccess&amp;role=writer&amp;tab=t.0">Google Doc</a>, which is constantly being updated.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-this-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h3>
<p>Public data infrastructures—the systems that store and provide access to government data—are often taken for granted. We assume that scientific reports, climate models, and environmental monitoring data will always be there when we need them. But these infrastructures are not just technical systems; they are deeply political. Decisions about what gets collected, what remains accessible, and what disappears are shaped by power, policy, and priorities.</p>
<p>The Data Rescue events of 2016–2017 brought together scientists, librarians, and civic tech communities to back up environmental datasets they feared could vanish under the Trump administration. At first glance, the movement looked like a technical project—downloading datasets, copying them to safer locations. But it was just as much an act of political resistance <span class="citation" data-cites="parisDatamirroringArchivalActivism2017">(Paris 2017)</span>.</p>
<p>Looking back, one of the most fascinating aspects of Data Rescue is that very little data actually disappeared. Yet the movement wasn’t a failure per se, even though most of the rescued data was not usable and the collection was far from complete <span class="citation" data-cites="lamdanLessonsDatarescueLimitations2017a">(Lamdan 2017)</span>. It revealed something crucial: it wasn’t just about saving data; it was about making government accountability visible <span class="citation" data-cites="dillonEnvironmentalDataJustice2017 dillonSituatingDataTrumpian2019">(Dillon et al. 2017, 2019)</span>. One theory might be that the fact that people felt the need to take matters into their own hands showed a loss of trust in official assurances represented by federal infrastructures.</p>
<p>Now, nearly a decade later, similar concerns are emerging. As the political landscape in the U.S. shifts once again. This time around,</p>
<p>I am currently speaking with people who were in one way or another involved in the first DataRescue events. Some of them have continued to monitor federal data policies and website changes over the years. Their work is a reminder that data loss isn’t always dramatic—sometimes, it’s a slow erosion of accessibility, funding cuts, or subtle changes to the language used in official reports.</p>
<p>If there’s one thing the past decade has taught us, it’s that data isn’t neutral and neither are the infrastructures they are connected to. Public data infrastructures are shaped by politics, and in turn, they shape what we know about the world. Understanding how these systems work—and how they can be protected—will be critical in the years ahead.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-CDCDatasetsUploaded" class="csl-entry">
<span>“<span>CDC</span> Datasets Uploaded Before <span>January</span> 28th, 2025 : <span>Centers</span> for <span>Disease Control</span> and <span>Prevention</span> : <span>Free Download</span>, <span>Borrow</span>, and <span>Streaming</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>Internet Archive</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://archive.org/details/20250128-cdc-datasets">https://archive.org/details/20250128-cdc-datasets</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-coxLookFederalHealth2025" class="csl-entry">
Cox, Cynthia, Matthew Rae, Jennifer Kates, Emma Wager, Jared Ortaliza, and Lindsey Dawson Published. 2025. <span>“A <span>Look</span> at <span>Federal Health Data Taken Offline</span>.”</span> <em>KFF</em>.
</div>
<div id="ref-currieBackupsFutureArchival2018" class="csl-entry">
Currie, Morgan E., and Britt S. Paris. 2018. <span>“Back-Ups for the Future: Archival Practices for Data Activism.”</span> <em>Archives and Manuscripts</em> 46 (2): 124–42. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/01576895.2018.1468273">https://doi.org/10.1080/01576895.2018.1468273</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-DataScreeningTools" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Data + <span>Screening Tools</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>Data + Screening Tools</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://screening-tools.com">https://screening-tools.com</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dillonSituatingDataTrumpian2019" class="csl-entry">
Dillon, Lindsey, Rebecca Lave, Becky Mansfield, Sara Wylie, Nicholas Shapiro, Anita Say Chan, and Michelle Murphy. 2019. <span>“Situating <span>Data</span> in a <span>Trumpian Era</span>: <span>The Environmental Data</span> and <span>Governance Initiative</span>.”</span> <em>Annals of the American Association of Geographers</em> 109 (2): 545–55. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/24694452.2018.1511410">https://doi.org/10.1080/24694452.2018.1511410</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dillonEnvironmentalDataJustice2017" class="csl-entry">
Dillon, Lindsey, Dawn Walker, Nicholas Shapiro, Vivian Underhill, Megan Martenyi, Sara Wylie, Rebecca Lave, Michelle Murphy, and Phil Brown. 2017. <span>“Environmental <span>Data Justice</span> and the <span>Trump Administration</span>: <span>Reflections</span> from the <span>Environmental Data</span> and <span>Governance Initiative</span>.”</span> <em>Environmental Justice</em> 10 (6): 186–92. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1089/env.2017.0020">https://doi.org/10.1089/env.2017.0020</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-edgiWhyEDGIArchiving2025" class="csl-entry">
EDGI. 2025. <span>“Why <span>EDGI</span> Is <span>Archiving Public Environmental Data</span>.”</span> <em>Environmental Data and Governance Initiative</em>. <a href="https://envirodatagov.org/why-edgi-is-archiving-public-environmental-data/">https://envirodatagov.org/why-edgi-is-archiving-public-environmental-data/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-EndTermWeb" class="csl-entry">
<span>“End of <span>Term Web Archive</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>End of Term Web Archive</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://eotarchive.org/">https://eotarchive.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-EnvironmentalDataGovernance" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Environmental <span>Data</span> &amp; <span>Governance Initiative</span>.”</span> n.d. <em>Environmental Data and Governance Initiative</em>. Accessed February 5, 2025. <a href="https://envirodatagov.org/">https://envirodatagov.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-janzMaintainingAccessPublic2017" class="csl-entry">
Janz, Margaret Miller. 2017. <span>“Maintaining <span>Access</span> to <span>Public Data</span>: <span>Lessons</span> from <span>Data Refuge</span>.”</span> <em>Against the Grain</em> 29 (6). <a href="https://doi.org/10.7771/2380-176X.7875">https://doi.org/10.7771/2380-176X.7875</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-koeblerArchivistsWorkIdentify2025a" class="csl-entry">
Koebler, Jason. 2025. <span>“Archivists <span>Work</span> to <span>Identify</span> and <span>Save</span> the <span>Thousands</span> of <span>Datasets Disappearing From Data</span>.gov.”</span> <em>404 Media</em>. <a href="https://www.404media.co/archivists-work-to-identify-and-save-the-thousands-of-datasets-disappearing-from-data-gov/">https://www.404media.co/archivists-work-to-identify-and-save-the-thousands-of-datasets-disappearing-from-data-gov/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-lamdanLessonsDatarescueLimitations2017a" class="csl-entry">
Lamdan, Sarah. 2017. <span>“Lessons from <span>Datarescue</span>: <span>The Limitations</span> of <span>Grassroots Climate Change Data Preservation</span> and the <span>Need</span> for <span>Federal Records Law Reform Essay</span>.”</span> <em>University of Pennsylvania Law Review Online</em> 166: 231–48.
</div>
<div id="ref-parisDatamirroringArchivalActivism2017" class="csl-entry">
Paris, Britt. 2017. <span>“Data-Mirroring as Archival Activism.”</span> <em>Datapower Conference Proceedings</em>, 1.2.4–4. <a href="https://doi.org/10.22215/datapower.v2017i0.22">https://doi.org/10.22215/datapower.v2017i0.22</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rothfritzUnderstandingMistrustDistrust2024" class="csl-entry">
Rothfritz, Laura. 2024a. <span>“Understanding Mistrust and Distrust in Public Data Infrastructures.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10663566">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10663566</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rothfritzUnderstandingTrustDistrust2024" class="csl-entry">
———. 2024b. <span>“Understanding Trust and Distrust in Public Data Infrastructures as Socio-Technical Systems.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11142410">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11142410</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-singerThousandsUSGovernment2025a" class="csl-entry">
Singer, Ethan. 2025. <span>“Thousands of <span>U</span>.<span>S</span>. <span>Government Web Pages Have Been Taken Down Since Friday</span> - <span>The New York Times</span>.”</span> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/02/upshot/trump-government-websites-missing-pages.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/02/upshot/trump-government-websites-missing-pages.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-sunCDCRemovesGender2025" class="csl-entry">
Sun, Lena H., Dan Keating, and Fenit Nirappil. 2025. <span>“<span>CDC</span> Removes Gender, Equity References in Public Health Material.”</span> <em>Washington Post</em>, February.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{rothfritz2025,
  author = {Rothfritz, Laura},
  title = {What Happens When Public Data Infrastructures Aren’t Save?
    {A} Look at Past and Current Developments in the {US}},
  date = {2025-02-05},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-rothfritz2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Rothfritz, Laura. 2025. <span>“What Happens When Public Data
Infrastructures Aren’t Save? A Look at Past and Current Developments in
the US.”</span> February 5, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70">https://doi.org/10.59350/6g3km-9w70</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-What-happens-when-public-data-infrastructures-arent-save/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-02-05-What-happens-when-public-data-infrastructures-arent-save/datarescue.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Perspective on Future Infrastructure for Scholarly Blogs in Germany</title>
  <dc:creator>Catharina Ochsner</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jonas Höfting</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-10-perspective-on-future-infrastructure-on-scholarly-blogs-in-germany/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On December 6th, 2024, we hosted the first workshop of our project <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">Infra Wiss Blogs</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="ochsner_research_2024">(Ochsner and Pampel 2024)</span>, funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG). The aim of the workshop was to bring together scholarly bloggers and experts from information infrastructure institutions, so they could exchange experiences, wishes and challenges concerning scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>In the following, we give a brief overview of the workshop, the talks and discussions, and outline how we will continue our work following the results of the workshop. Following the welcome address, we presented the initial results of a survey of German scholarly blogs that we conducted as a part of the Infra Wiss Blogs project. Afterward, the workshop was enriched by multiple presentations around the topic of scholarly blogs and their long term accessibility.</p>
<p><a href="https://blogs.helmholtz.de/augenspiegel/author/henning/">Henning Krause</a> from the Helmholtz Association began with an overview of the Helmholtz Blogs, the blog portal of Germany’s largest research organization. He talked about challenges and opportunities with science communication, using blogs as an example.</p>
<p>This talk was followed by a presentation from Martin Fenner from <a href="https://front-matter.io/">Front Matter</a>, on the topic of long term accessibility of scholarly blogs and the the <a href="https://rogue-scholar.org/">Rogue Scholar blog archive</a>.</p>
<p>Lastly, these presentations were followed by two inputs from practitioners within the field by <a href="https://www.gesis.org/institut/ueber-uns/mitarbeitendenverzeichnis/person/Charmaine.Voigt">Charmaine Voigt</a> from GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences, and <a href="https://www.dnb.de/SharedDocs/Kontaktdaten/DE/wolderingBritta.html">Britta Woldering</a> from the German National Library. Charmaine Voigt presented the results of a survey on science blogs and podcasts at scientific institutions in Germany in the GESIS Wi⁴impact project. Britta Woldering introduced the work of the German National Library (DNB) in the field of web archiving and described the DNB’s approach to handling blogs for the permanent accessibility of digital content.</p>
<p>The available presentations of the speakers were published on Zenodo and can be found below:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Fenner, M. (2024, December 6). Ansätze zur Sicherung der dauerhaften Zugänglichkeit von Wissenschaftsblogs. Infra Wiss Blogs Vernetzungsworkshop 2024, Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060</a></p></li>
<li><p>Voigt, C., &amp; Kuhle, B. (2024, December 6). Wi4impact: Befragung von Produzierenden deutscher Wissenschaftsblogs (und -podcasts). Infra Wiss Blogs Vernetzungsworkshop 2024, Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474</a></p></li>
<li><p>Woldering, B. (2024, December 6). Webarchivierung an der deutschen Nationalbibliothek. Infra Wiss Blogs Vernetzungsworkshop 2024, Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>The presentations and the results of the survey of German scholarly blogs were then discussed by the workshop organizers, the participants, and the speakers. To structure the discussion, we prepared a set of questions on the topic, e.g.&nbsp;“How can bloggers, libraries and archives work together to create standardized metadata and procedures for long-term accessibility for academic blogs?”. The main topic of discussion was how scholarly bloggers and infrastructure institutions can work together, to ensure the long term access of scholarly blogs.</p>
<p>The following challenges were identified concerning the standardization of scholarly blogs and their long term accessibility:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Insufficient provision of metadata</li>
<li>Insufficient licensing information</li>
<li>Dynamic contents, such as pictures or videos, comments, link rot pose technical and legal challenges</li>
<li>Bloggers’ lack of knowledge about the technical and legal requirements to ensure long term accessibility</li>
<li>Blogs and other knowledge transfer and science communication activities are usually not adequately recognized in the scientific reputation system and the evaluation of research performance</li>
</ol>
<p>The following strategies to enhance long term accessibility of scholarly blogs were proposed during the discussion:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>(Re-)using standardized formats (such as XML or JSON) that are already being used by blogs for the long term archiving</li>
<li>Including licensing information into metadata. Recommended for use is the CC BY license</li>
<li>Legal challenges of archiving comments could be solved through legal notice</li>
<li>Libraries as educational institutions can help educate bloggers on blog requirements</li>
<li>Universities and other research performing organizations can support bloggers through offering platforms or better maintaining existing ones and by recognizing blogging as part of knowledge transfer and science communication</li>
</ol>
<p>The discussion illustrated the diversity of the stakeholders. All participants agreed that there is a further need for stronger networking and collaboration on the topic. The participants also emphasized the need for support from universities and research institutions, as well as funding bodies, for their blogging researchers.</p>
<p>The workshop enabled us to bring together diverse perspectives from people involved in blogs, infrastructure, and science communication. We learned a lot and received numerous suggestions for the project. We thank all the speakers and participants for their contributions and the open discussions.</p>
<p>Building on the results of the survey of German blogs, we will start conducting in-depth interviews with scholarly bloggers to investigate the infrastructural challenges of scholarly blogs and possible solutions.</p>
<p>Additionally, We are currently working on publishing the results of our survey on German scholarly blogs. We will communicate the publication of the article through our <a href="https://www.listserv.dfn.de/sympa/info/infra-wiss-blogs">mailing list</a>. The subscription is possible <a href="https://www.listserv.dfn.de/sympa/info/infra-wiss-blogs">here</a>.</p>
<p>A German version of this blog post is available on the blog dedicated to the Infra Wiss Blog project and can be found <a href="https://infrawissblogs.org/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-fenner_ansatze_2024" class="csl-entry">
Fenner, Martin. 2024. <span>“Ansätze Zur <span>Sicherung</span> Der Dauerhaften <span>Zugänglichkeit</span> von <span>Wissenschaftsblogs</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354060</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ochsner_research_2024" class="csl-entry">
Ochsner, Catharina, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“Research <span>Group</span> <span>Information</span> <span>Management</span> @ <span>Humboldt</span>-<span>Universität</span> Zu <span>Berlin</span> - <span>Project</span> Launch: <span>Infra</span> <span>Wiss</span> <span>Blogs</span> - <span>Ensuring</span> <span>Permanent</span> <span>Access</span> to <span>Scholarly</span> <span>Blogs</span>.”</span> <a href="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-05-project-launch-infra-wiss-blogs/Index.html">https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-09-05-project-launch-infra-wiss-blogs/Index.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-voigt_wiimpact_2024" class="csl-entry">
Voigt, Charmaine, and Birte Kuhle. 2024. <span>“Wi⁴impact: <span>Befragung</span> von <span>Produzierenden</span> Deutscher <span>Wissenschaftsblogs</span> (Und -Podcasts).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14354474</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-woldering_webarchivierung_2024" class="csl-entry">
Woldering, Britta. 2024. <span>“Webarchivierung an Der Deutschen <span>Nationalbibliothek</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14355206</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{ochsner2025,
  author = {Ochsner, Catharina and Höfting, Jonas and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Perspective on {Future} {Infrastructure} for {Scholarly}
    {Blogs} in {Germany}},
  date = {2025-01-10},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/4fc41-6n753},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-ochsner2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Ochsner, Catharina, Jonas Höfting, and Heinz Pampel. 2025.
<span>“Perspective on Future Infrastructure for Scholarly Blogs in
Germany.”</span> January 10, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/4fc41-6n753">https://doi.org/10.59350/4fc41-6n753</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-10-perspective-on-future-infrastructure-on-scholarly-blogs-in-germany/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-10-perspective-on-future-infrastructure-on-scholarly-blogs-in-germany/IMG_5273.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Workshop ‘The state and prospects of open access reporting’ at Open-Access-Tage</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-09-workshop-the-state-and-prospects-of-open-access-reporting/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>At last year’s Open-Access-Tage, <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/en/">OA Datenpraxis</a> held a workshop together with the <a href="https://www.fz-juelich.de/en/zb/open-science/open-access/open-access-monitor-1">Open Access Monitor</a> at Forschungszentrum Jülich as well as the state-wide Open Access initiatives of Berlin (<a href="https://www.open-access-berlin.de">Open Access Büro Berlin</a>) and Brandenburg (<a href="https://open-access-brandenburg.de/en/">Vernetzungs- und Kompetenzstelle Open Access Brandenburg</a>). The workshop ‘The state and prospects of open access reporting’ outlined different approaches - qualitative and quantitative - to Open Access reporting and provided insights into examples for reporting procedures. Participants discussed opportunities and challenges of these reporting approaches in small groups before the results were briefly presented in plenary. The presentation slides have been published on Zenodo.</p>
<p>Barbers, I., Kindling, M., Stadler, H., Strecker, D., Kaden, B., Mittermaier, B., &amp; Pampel, H. (2024, September 10). Stand und Perspektive des Open-Access-Reportings. Open-Access-Tage 2024, Köln. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942</a></p>
<p>Recently, a new report documenting a workshop held by OA Datenpraxis and <a href="">Transform2Open</a> at the 25th annual meeting of DINI (Deutsche Initiative für Netzwerkinformation e. V.) was published. Participants discussed how the costs of providing access to scientific information can be made more transparent.</p>
<p>Ferguson, L. M., Pampel, H., Strecker, D., &amp; Meistring, M. (2025). Transparenz in der Wissenschaft: Strategien für offene Informationsversorgung. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423</a></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-barbers_stand_2024" class="csl-entry">
Barbers, Irene, Maxi Kindling, Heike Stadler, and Dorothea Strecker. 2024. <span>“Stand Und <span>Perspektive</span> Des <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Reportings</span>.”</span> Köln. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13831942</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ferguson_transparenz_2025" class="csl-entry">
Ferguson, Lea Maria, Heinz Pampel, Dorothea Strecker, and Marcel Meistring. 2025. <span>“Transparenz in Der <span>Wissenschaft</span>: <span>Strategien</span> Für Offene <span>Informationsversorgung</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14505423</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2025,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Workshop “{The} State and Prospects of Open Access Reporting”
    at {Open-Access-Tage}},
  date = {2025-01-09},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/r84e3-7s790},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2025. <span>“Workshop <span>‘The
State and Prospects of Open Access Reporting’</span> at
Open-Access-Tage.”</span> January 9, 2025. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/r84e3-7s790">https://doi.org/10.59350/r84e3-7s790</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-09-workshop-the-state-and-prospects-of-open-access-reporting/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2025-01-09-workshop-the-state-and-prospects-of-open-access-reporting/OAT.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="80" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
