<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</title>
<link>https://infomgnt.org/</link>
<atom:link href="https://infomgnt.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.555</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Perspectives on the future of community-driven Open Access publishing</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Marcel Wrzesinski</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ben Kaden</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Margo Bargheer</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Maxi Kindling</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dagmar Schobert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-08-05-community-driven-open-access-publishing/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The conversation about advancing the open access transformation has been revitalized by the “Council Conclusions on High-Quality, Transparent, Open, Trustworthy, and Equitable Scholarly Publishing” issued by the EU Science Ministries in May 2023 <span class="citation" data-cites="council_of_the_european_union_high-quality_2023">(Council of the European Union 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>In September 2023, we organized the conference “Community-Driven Open Access Publishing” as a satellite event of the Open Access Days 2023 <span class="citation" data-cites="institut_fur_bibliotheks-_und_informationswissenschaft_satelliten-konferenz_2023">(Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>During the conference, we discussed ten statements on the future of community-driven open access publishing. An initial version of the statements had been drafted in German by the conference program committee between early March 2023 and the end of July 2023. Attendees had the opportunity to comment on these theses on the PubPub platform during the conference <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_thesen_2023">(Pampel et al. 2023)</span>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The feedback collected on PubPub, at the conference, and on social media formed the basis for revising the statements, of which an updated version was published in April 2024 <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_thesen_2024-1">(Pampel, Bargheer, Bertelmann, Kaden, Wrzesinski, et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-08-05-community-driven-open-access-publishing/community-driven-open-access-publishing (2).png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Together with Margo Bargheer, Roland Bertelmann, Ben Kaden, Maxi Kindling, and Dagmar Schobert, we have since then published an article in German about the development of the statements in the journal Bibliothek Forschung und Praxis <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_thesen_2024">(Pampel, Bargheer, Bertelmann, Kaden, Kindling, et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>To mark the publication of the ten statements and also to broaden the conversation, this blog post documents the core elements in English:&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>1. Bridging the strategic gap</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures need backing from a comprehensive, large-scale strategy from research funding and infrastructure organizations. Only a high-profile initiative can ensure the necessary scientific policy support and financial commitment, thereby strengthening digital sovereignty in science.</p>
<p><strong>2. Acknowledging diversity in funding and business models</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures require varied funding and business models tailored to the specific requirements of each (subject) community. This process should be guided by maximum transparency on costs and service portfolio.</p>
<p><strong>3. Strengthening libraries as publication service providers</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures require a professional operation. Academic libraries, with their established services, expertise, and strong networks, are well-positioned to serve as active publication service providers for scholarly communities. Therefore, publication infrastructures within libraries should be systematically expanded.</p>
<p><strong>4. Ensuring quality, applying standards</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures such as journals are responsible for maintaining the content quality of publications. This should be ensured using recognized quality assurance procedures that align with good scientific practice. Formal and technical quality assurance should be implemented by applying open publishing standards for both publications and processes.</p>
<p><strong>5. Strengthening collaboration with disciplinary communities</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures need a strong foundation within scholarly subject communities and their organizational structures, such as learned societies. Collaboration should be participatory while allowing the publication infrastructures to remain autonomous. Libraries should engage more closely with subject communities and proactively shape services for the research community.</p>
<p><strong>6. Promoting experiments and innovation</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures have the potential to shape innovations in scholarly publishing. Experimentation with new publication formats, further development of processes and standards, and exploration of new collaborative approaches should be encouraged.</p>
<p><strong>7. Ensuring sustainability</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures require sustainable funding and business models.&nbsp;</p>
<p>To achieve this, a clear organizational integration is needed, a precisely defined mission and scope statement is essential, and funding organizations should express their commitment. Furthermore, the technical and legal sustainability of the infrastructures and their publications must be promoted by using open standards and open licenses.</p>
<p><strong>8. Orienting infrastructures towards the common good</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures should focus on the common good and base their activities on the principles and values of the <a href="https://www.unesco.org/en/open-science/about">UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="unesco_unesco_2021">(UNESCO 2021)</span>.</p>
<p><strong>9. Entering new collaborations</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures should explore innovative collaboration models, operate across institutional and national boundaries, and aim to increase their visibility and that of their publications. Collaborations with external service providers can be advantageous, provided that governance remains aligned with scholarly interests.</p>
<p><strong>10. Implementing Open Science</strong></p>
<p>Community-driven publication infrastructures should enable the publication of texts, data, software, and other resources, and support the recognition of open science practices in research evaluation. To achieve these goals, they should operate openly and interoperably whenever possible. Additionally, they should provide published texts, data, and software in a machine-readable format, and ensure long-term accessibility to the published material.</p>
<p>We thank the speakers and participants of the conference for sharing their expertise and contributing to the development of the statements. We also appreciate the valuable reflections and input from our commentators.</p>
<p>Those interested in more information about the conference can refer to the report published by <span class="citation" data-cites="meistring_satelliten-konferenz_2023">(Meistring and Ferguson 2023)</span>. All conference slides have been published on <span class="citation" data-cites="zenodo_konferenz_2023">(Zenodo 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-institut_fur_bibliotheks-_und_informationswissenschaft_satelliten-konferenz_2023" class="csl-entry">
Bibliotheks- und Informationswissenschaft, Institut für. 2023. <span>“Satelliten-<span>Konferenz</span> „<span>Wissenschaftsgeleitetes</span> <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Publizieren</span>“ Zu Den <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Tagen</span> 2023.”</span> <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/oat23ibi">https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/events/oat23ibi</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-council_of_the_european_union_high-quality_2023" class="csl-entry">
Council of the European Union. 2023. <span>“High-Quality, Transparent, Open, Trustworthy and Equitable Scholarly Publishing - <span>Council</span> Conclusions (Approved on 23 <span>May</span> 2023). 9616/23.”</span> Brussels. <a href="https://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-9616-2023-INIT/en/pdf">https://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-9616-2023-INIT/en/pdf</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-meistring_satelliten-konferenz_2023" class="csl-entry">
Meistring, Marcel, and Lea Maria Ferguson. 2023. <span>“Satelliten-<span>Konferenz</span> „<span>Wissenschaftsgeleitetes</span> <span>Open</span>- <span>Access</span>-<span>Publizieren</span>“ Zu Den <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Tagen</span> 2023 Am 26. <span>September</span> 2023.”</span> <em>O-Bib. Das Offene Bibliotheksjournal / Herausgeber VDB</em> 10 (4): 1–6. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5282/o-bib/6001">https://doi.org/10.5282/o-bib/6001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel_thesen_2023" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Margo Bargheer, Roland Bertelmann, Ben Kaden, Maxi Kindling, Sarah Dellmann, Dagmar Schobert, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2023. <span>“Thesen Zur <span>Zukunft</span> Des Wissenschaftsgeleiteten <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Publizierens</span>. <span>Version</span> 1.0, <span>September</span> 2023.”</span> <em>Open-Access-Büro Berlin</em>, September. <a href="https://oabb.pubpub.org/pub/mr9x0ptz/release/2">https://oabb.pubpub.org/pub/mr9x0ptz/release/2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel_thesen_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Margo Bargheer, Roland Bertelmann, Ben Kaden, Maxi Kindling, Dagmar Schobert, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2024. <span>“Thesen Zur <span>Zukunft</span> Des Wissenschaftsgeleiteten <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Publizierens</span> – <span>Entwicklung</span> Und <span>Diskussion</span> in Einem Partizipativen <span>Prozess</span>.”</span> <em>Bibliothek Forschung Und Praxis</em> 0 (0). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/bfp-2024-0027">https://doi.org/10.1515/bfp-2024-0027</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel_thesen_2024-1" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Margo Bargheer, Roland Bertelmann, Ben Kaden, Marcel Wrzesinski, Maxi Kindling, and Dagmar Schobert. 2024. <span>“Thesen Zur <span>Zukunft</span> Des Wissenschaftsgeleiteten <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Publizierens</span> (<span>Version</span> 2.0).”</span> <em>Open-Access-Büro Berlin</em>, March. <a href="https://doi.org/10.21428/986c5d43.77851a7c">https://doi.org/10.21428/986c5d43.77851a7c</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-unesco_unesco_2021" class="csl-entry">
UNESCO. 2021. <span>“<span>UNESCO</span> <span>Recommendation</span> on <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span>.”</span> <a href="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000379949">https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000379949</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-zenodo_konferenz_2023" class="csl-entry">
Zenodo. 2023. <span>“Konferenz „<span>Wissenschaftsgeleitetes</span> <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Publizieren</span>“.”</span> <a href="https://zenodo.org/communities/oat23ibi?q=&amp;l=list&amp;p=1&amp;s=10&amp;sort=newest">https://zenodo.org/communities/oat23ibi?q=&amp;l=list&amp;p=1&amp;s=10&amp;sort=newest</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz and Wrzesinski, Marcel and Kaden, Ben and
    Bargheer, Margo and Kindling, Maxi and Schobert, Dagmar},
  title = {Perspectives on the Future of Community-Driven {Open}
    {Access} Publishing},
  date = {2024-08-05},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/7evg5-jm930},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz, Marcel Wrzesinski, Ben Kaden, Margo Bargheer, Maxi
Kindling, and Dagmar Schobert. 2024. <span>“Perspectives on the Future
of Community-Driven Open Access Publishing.”</span> August 5, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/7evg5-jm930">https://doi.org/10.59350/7evg5-jm930</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Policy</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-08-05-community-driven-open-access-publishing/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-08-05-community-driven-open-access-publishing/community-driven-open-access-publishing (2).png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Research Data Publications Between Dynamism and Persistence - Insights from the #PIDsBUA Workshop</title>
  <dc:creator>Jens Klump</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Laura Rothfritz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-pidsbua-workshop/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Research is inherently dynamic, leading to equally dynamic data. This dynamic nature of research data raises numerous questions for professionals in information management at research institutions, libraries, and computing centers. Despite the conceptual establishment of research data citation through persistent identifiers (PIDs) in some communities, practical challenges remain. This is the case within the infrastructure of repositories and journals, particularly regarding their practices, guidelines, and standards.</p>
<p>Our team at the <a href="https://hu-berlin.de/infomgnt">Research Group Information Management</a> at the Berlin School of Library and Information Science is dedicated to understanding research data versioning as part of information management processes at research-performing organizations (RPOs). With the project “PID Reference Model for Research Data Versioning” (#<a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pidsbua">PIDsBUA</a>) funded by the “Advancing Research Quality and Value” fellowship program of the Berlin University Alliance (BUA), we address questions of dynamism and persistence in the context of the persistent identification of research data.</p>
<p>Our project benefits from the expertise of <a href="https://people.csiro.au/K/J/jens-klump">Jens Klump</a>, Senior Principal Research Officer at Australia’s national science agency <a href="https://www.csiro.au/">CSIRO</a>, who is working as a <a href="https://www.berlin-university-alliance.de/en/commitments/research-quality/forschung/fellowship/index.html">BUA Fellow</a> with our research group. Jens has extensive experience in this field, including contributions to the Research Data Alliance (<a href="https://www.rd-alliance.org/">RDA</a>) <a href="https://www.rd-alliance.org/groups/data-versioning-ig/">Data Versioning Working Group</a> <span class="citation" data-cites="klump_compilation_2020">(Klump et al. 2020)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="klump_versioning_2021">(Klump et al. 2021)</span>.</p>
<p>One question touching on the tension between the dynamic nature of data and the need for persistence on the side of infrastructures that can arise when dynamic research data is published in repositories is how these datasets should be recorded in publication management and research information documentation. Ensuring proper attribution of research performance for publishing dynamic datasets while addressing practical recording issues is a central concern of our project.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-pidsbua-workshop/pidsbua.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>To facilitate a broad discussion with experts from academia, infrastructure, and administration, and to enhance the transfer of our work within Berlin’s research landscape, we hosted a workshop on June 28, 2024, at the Einstein Center Digital Future (<a href="https://www.digital-future.berlin/">ECDF</a>) in Berlin. The event attracted around 40 experts from diverse scientific domains.</p>
<p>After an introductory session, discussions focused on four key themes and the associated questions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Revision and Release:</p>
<ul>
<li>When do we differentiate between a revision and a release in research data management?</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Time Series and Dynamic Data:</p>
<ul>
<li>How can we address the unique characteristics of time series and dynamic data in research data management?</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Granularity and Collections:</p>
<ul>
<li>How does versioning support recording the provenance of an object?</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Provenance, Citation, and Metadata:</p>
<ul>
<li>How should we handle provenance, citation, and metadata in the context of research data versioning?</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>These themes were discussed within the framework of the RDA’s work.</p>
<p><strong>Lessons Learned</strong></p>
<p>In a fruitful and lively discussion, we identified the following points</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Revision and Release:</p>
<ul>
<li>While many technological aspects of versioning are clear, definitional and coordination activities are still crucial. Establishing whether a change is a revision or a release requires developing conventions within user groups.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Time Series and Dynamic Data:</p>
<ul>
<li>Different practices are necessary depending on the use case, such as ensuring traceability or allowing ongoing machine access to a dataset. Solutions should be tailored to the specific user groups.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Granularity and Collections:</p>
<ul>
<li>Professional requirements significantly influence granularity and collections, posing challenges for infrastructures that organize and provide access to these collections.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Provenance, Citation, and Metadata:</p>
<ul>
<li>Discussions highlighted the importance of metadata and evolving citation practices in facilitating dataset provenance. These practices are often shaped by disciplinary publication cultures and require infrastructure-level support.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>We thank all participants for their enthusiasm and engaging discussions. The workshop offered a great platform for cross-institutional and cross-disciplinary dialogue, promoting valuable mutual learning.</p>
<p>Many thanks to the BUA for their funding and to the ECDF for their hospitality.</p>
<p>A workshop report in German is available <span class="citation" data-cites="klump_workshop_2024">(Klump 2024)</span>. The slides and posters are also published <span class="citation" data-cites="klump_dokumentation_2024">(Klump et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-klump_workshop_2024" class="csl-entry">
Klump, Jens. 2024. <span>“Workshop "<span>Forschungsdaten</span>-<span>Publikationen</span> Zwischen <span>Dynamik</span> Und <span>Persistenz</span>".”</span> Berlin. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12818783">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12818783</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-klump_dokumentation_2024" class="csl-entry">
Klump, Jens, Heinz Pampel, Laura Rothfritz, and Dorothea Strecker. 2024. <span>“Dokumentation Des <span>Workshops</span> "<span>Forschungsdaten</span>-<span>Publikationen</span> Zwischen <span>Dynamik</span> Und <span>Persistenz</span>",”</span> July. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12917465">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12917465</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-klump_compilation_2020" class="csl-entry">
Klump, Jens, Lesley Wyborn, Robert Downs, Ari Asmi, Mingfang Wu, Gerry Ryder, and Julia Martin. 2020. <span>“Compilation of <span>Data</span> <span>Versioning</span> <span>Use</span> Cases from the <span>RDA</span> <span>Data</span> <span>Versioning</span> <span>Working</span> <span>Group</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.15497/RDA00041">https://doi.org/10.15497/RDA00041</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-klump_versioning_2021" class="csl-entry">
Klump, Jens, Lesley Wyborn, Mingfang Wu, Julia Martin, Robert R. Downs, and Ari Asmi. 2021. <span>“Versioning <span>Data</span> <span>Is</span> <span>About</span> <span>More</span> Than <span>Revisions</span>: <span>A</span> <span>Conceptual</span> <span>Framework</span> and <span>Proposed</span> <span>Principles</span>.”</span> <em>Data Science Journal</em> 20 (March): 12. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2021-012">https://doi.org/10.5334/dsj-2021-012</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{klump2024,
  author = {Klump, Jens and Pampel, Heinz and Rothfritz, Laura and
    Strecker, Dorothea},
  title = {Research {Data} {Publications} {Between} {Dynamism} and
    {Persistence} - {Insights} from the {\#PIDsBUA} {Workshop}},
  date = {2024-07-26},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/6f7sw-etd43},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-klump2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Klump, Jens, Heinz Pampel, Laura Rothfritz, and Dorothea Strecker. 2024.
<span>“Research Data Publications Between Dynamism and Persistence -
Insights from the #PIDsBUA Workshop.”</span> July 26, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/6f7sw-etd43">https://doi.org/10.59350/6f7sw-etd43</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-pidsbua-workshop/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-pidsbua-workshop/pidsbua.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="107" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Die Bibliocon 2024 - ein studentischer Reisebericht</title>
  <dc:creator>Pia Kretschmar</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Christopher Onzie Khamis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-reisebericht-bibliocon/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Regardless of whether one is just starting out or has already arrived in the community, as young librarians and information scientists, there are many interesting fields and new developments. For example, there are discussions about the diverse potential of artificial intelligence in library environments, the currently developing discussion on how to handle library collections with a colonial history and context, how to incorporate comics into bibliographic data sets, or the evaluation of the major transformative agreements in Germany - just to name a few. But how can one experience all this without having to visit completely different events and locations? For instance, by attending Bibliocon.</p>
<p>This year’s 112th Bibliocon took place in Hamburg and welcomed more than 4,000 guests from 30 countries <a href="https://www.b-u-b.de/themen-dossiers/bibliocon/post/groesste-deutsche-fachkonferenz-des-bibliothekswesens-in-hamburg-gestartet">BuB</a> between June 4th and 7th 2024. Over three days, there were 240 events that covered every imaginable topic in the field of library and information science <a href="https://bibliocon2024.abstractserver.com/program/#/program/1/horizontal">Bibliocon program6136</a>. The presentations were organized by overarching theme areas, such as library-related topics, open-access-related topics, information science-related topics, etc. In addition, there were presentations from a wide range of companies, such as publishers like Elsevier, Springer Nature or service providers like Clarivate.</p>
<p>Among the many attendees were also two student employees from the Information Management department at the Berlin School for Library and Information Science (IBI) at Humboldt University Berlin who had the great opportunity to attend the congress. As “first-timers”, our attendance was naturally about collecting as many interesting experiences as possible - both in terms of information management to enrich our work in the research group and also in our own areas of interest. To coordinate this beforehand, we could even use an app provided by the event <a href="https://apps.apple.com/de/app/bibliocon-2024/id6483864875">Apple App Store</a> and of course also refer to a printed program with a detailed schedule.</p>
<p>Alongside an extremely enthusiastic and friendly staff, who gave us some useful tips for orientation in the massive Congress Center Hamburg (CCH), we would like to highlight the very accommodating first-timer event of the Professional Association of Information and Libraries (BIB - Berufsverband Information Bibliothek). For young trainees and students in the library sector, there was a lot of material and tips for the trade fair, as well as general guidance for navigating the profession.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-reisebericht-bibliocon/20240606_tripreport.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Unfortunately, we had to miss out on attending some events due to time overlaps with similar events or miscalculations regarding expected attendance numbers, which often was quite regrettable. Although there was a seated streaming offer on site, not all overcrowded events were streamed or could be streamed frequently. This was particularly evident at the AI panels, where there was high demand for events that focused on their practical applications and assistance functions.</p>
<p>Although the app unfortunately only catered to iOS users, Android users could still use a browser version (not optimal but okay), and despite having very few power outlets and corresponding charging options, Bibliocon provided a spacious and practical working area. However, it must be noted that food and drink prices were not student-friendly at all.</p>
<p>The general political discussion and development also found its way onto Bibliocon. For example, there was an interesting event about Czech libraries that dealt with their positioning in political debates in the country. <span class="citation" data-cites="petrak_positive_2024">(Petrak 2024)</span> Three projects from different libraries were presented that had caused a stir with events during Pride Month and a debate event on same-sex marriage.</p>
<p>Two libraries in Brno and Usti nad Labem were presented as examples of cooperation with local associations to organize Pride Month events. These included readings by drag queens for parents and children as well as an installation of a themed corner for young people featuring a “Rainbow Mailbox” similar to a complaint box where young people can anonymously express their fears, worries, or general their feelings. The drag queen readings sparked both enthusiasm and opposition in both cities; conservative parties from the regions even mobilized people to disrupt these events. What stood out about this event was how strongly they adapted their plans to suit local circumstances while also reflecting on failed approaches – such as how attention shifted mainly towards those opposed during debates divided into two evenings based on position due to higher attendance numbers among those opposing it. At the same time, speakers were open to suggestions from outside during discussions so they could incorporate them into future planning.</p>
<p>Several panels were dedicated to the historical reevaluation of colonialism and practical conclusions for today’s work. In addition to a stimulating podium discussion, “Challenges of Cultural Heritage from Colonial Contexts in Libraries” <span class="citation" data-cites="muller_zu_2024">(Müller et al. 2024)</span> et al., with literature and cultural scientist Albert Gouaffo (University of Dschang), who was cut in from Cameroon, library representatives at the State Library in Berlin (Staatsbibliothek Berlin) had organized a workshop for discussing a guide for handling these library collections with sensitivity <span class="citation" data-cites="schmid_entwicklung_2024">(Schmid and Scheibe 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>As student employees, we were naturally also interested in the various company presentations at the fair. However, there was only limited feedback after visiting several stands. We could still listen to an Elsevier presentation, where Max Vögler presented an international interview study on challenges for universities and research funding organizations, particularly research evaluation, research assessment, and the concept of the “4th Generation University”.</p>
<p>Various projects by or with involvement by the research and teaching group of Information Management (IBI) were also represented in this year’s Bibliocon program. In addition to the Hands-On Lab “Scenarios for further development of open-access repositories”(“Szenarien für die Weiterentwicklung von Open-Access-Repositorien”) <span class="citation" data-cites="beucke_research_2024">(Beucke et al. 2024)</span> in cooperation with DINI AG Elektronisches Publizieren (DINI working group Electronic Publishing), the research project “Professionalization of OAR Infrastructure in Germany” <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_open-access-repositorien_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span> was able to present itself and initial results on analyzing challenges for developing “Next Generation Repositories”.</p>
<p>Joshua Shelly (UB Potsdam) presented a study from Transform2Open <span class="citation" data-cites="ferguson_transform2open_2024">(Ferguson et al. 2024)</span> on “Process Optimization of Open Access Workflows in Academic Libraries”, which demonstrated that OA workflows need to be designed holistically and integrated into daily operations as well as various institutional departments to be sustainable, practice-oriented, and optimized. The study was developed with contributions from partner institutions such as Forschungszentrum Jülich, the Helmholtz Open Science Office, and the University of Potsdam. Additionally, the Hands-on Lab “Central Publication Cost Recording: When a Few Bucks Come Together in Science”(“Zentrale Publikationskostenerfassung: Wenn ein paar Kröten in der Wissenschaft zusammenkommen”) <span class="citation" data-cites="stein_zentrale_2024">(Stein et al. 2024)</span> highlighted the possibilities repositories offer for central publication cost recording. Cornelia Lang (UB Regensburg) and Lisa-Marie Stein (openCost) provided a very detailed discussion on workflow issues, centralization, and repository software. Another interesting contribution was made by Najko Jahn (SUB Göttingen), who discussed the status and development of the Open Access transformation in hybrid journals <span class="citation" data-cites="jahn_open-access-transformation_2024">(Jahn 2024)</span>. Among other things, he introduced the Hybrid Open Access Dashboard <a href="https://subugoe.github.io/hoaddash/">HOAD</a> and compared developments in the German scientific landscape with those in the international arena. Finally, we agreed that attending Bibliocon was a great enrichment and can only recommend the conference to interested students. There are many new contents and perspectives to discover that are not covered in everyday studies. However, it should be noted that the ticket, like many other conferences, is not particularly cheap, although there is a discount for students and early bookers. Therefore, it is worthwhile to book as early as possible and in conjunction with a job. In any case, the experiences are definitely worth it.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-beucke_research_2024" class="csl-entry">
Beucke, Daniel, Isabella Meinecke, Heinz Pampel, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2024. <span>“Research Group Information Management @ Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin - Report on the Hands-on Lab <span>‘Scenarios for the Development of Open Access Repositories’</span> at the 112th <span>BiblioCon</span>. Virtual Research Lab of the Research and Teaching Group Information Management at Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin.”</span> Blog. July 15, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/mg09a-5ma64">https://doi.org/10.59350/mg09a-5ma64</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ferguson_transform2open_2024" class="csl-entry">
Ferguson, Lea Maria, Margit Schön, Irene Barbers, Roland Bertelmann, Tobias Höhnow, Heinz Pampel, Peter Kostädt, Marcel Meistring, Bernhard Mittermaier, and Joshua Shelly. 2024. <span>“Transform2Open - Vernetzung in Der Open-Access-Transformation.”</span> Konferenzveröffentlichung (Vortragsfolien). Hamburg: Konferenzveröffentlichung (Vortragsfolien). <a href="https://urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-184914">urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-184914</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-jahn_open-access-transformation_2024" class="csl-entry">
Jahn, Najko. 2024. <span>“Open-Access-Transformation in Hybriden Zeitschriften: Stand Und Perspektiven.”</span> Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). Hamburg: Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). <a href="https://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-bib-info/frontdoor/index/index/searchtype/authorsearch/author/Najko+Jahn/docId/19046">https://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-bib-info/frontdoor/index/index/searchtype/authorsearch/author/Najko+Jahn/docId/19046</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-muller_zu_2024" class="csl-entry">
Müller, Lars, Romy Köhller, Albert Gouaffo, Achim Bonte, Irene Albers, and Kim Richter. 2024. <span>“Zu Wem Gehört Es? Herausforderungen von Kulturerbe Aus Kolonialen Kontexten in Bibliotheken.”</span> Podiumsdiskussion. Hamburg: Podiumsdiskussion. <a href="https://urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-188823">urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-188823</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel_open-access-repositorien_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Marcel Wrzesinski, Laura Rothfritz, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2024. <span>“Open-Access-Repositorien Auf Dem Prüfstand: Problemlagen Und Strategien Zur Professionalisierung.”</span> Konferenzveröffentlichung (Vortragsfolien). Hamburg: Konferenzveröffentlichung (Vortragsfolien). <a href="https://urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-190741">urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-190741</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-petrak_positive_2024" class="csl-entry">
Petrak, Ani. 2024. <span>“Positive, Negative or Neutral? The Highly-Charged Nature of Czech Librarianship at the Front Lines of European Culture Wars.”</span> Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). Hamburg: Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). <a href="https://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-bib-info/frontdoor/index/index/docId/18875">https://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-bib-info/frontdoor/index/index/docId/18875</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-schmid_entwicklung_2024" class="csl-entry">
Schmid, Larissa, and Michaela Scheibe. 2024. <span>“Entwicklung Eines Leitfadens Zum Umgang Mit Bibliotheksbeständen Aus Kolonialen Kontexten.”</span> Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). Hamburg: Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). <a href="https://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-bib-info/frontdoor/index/index/docId/18870">https://opus4.kobv.de/opus4-bib-info/frontdoor/index/index/docId/18870</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-stein_zentrale_2024" class="csl-entry">
Stein, Lisa-Marie, Cornelia Lang, Alexander Wagner, and Gernot Deinzer. 2024. <span>“Zentrale Publikationskostenerfassung: Wenn Ein Paar Kröten in Der Wissenschaft Zusammenkommen.”</span> Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). Hamburg: Konferenzveröffentlichung (Abstract). <a href="https://urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-187981">urn:nbn:de:0290-opus4-187981</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{kretschmar2024,
  author = {Kretschmar, Pia and Onzie Khamis, Christopher},
  title = {Die {Bibliocon} 2024 - Ein Studentischer {Reisebericht}},
  date = {2024-07-26},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/rhn65-25g40},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-kretschmar2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Kretschmar, Pia, and Christopher Onzie Khamis. 2024. <span>“Die
Bibliocon 2024 - Ein Studentischer Reisebericht.”</span> July 26, 2024.
<a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/rhn65-25g40">https://doi.org/10.59350/rhn65-25g40</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Students</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-reisebericht-bibliocon/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-26-reisebericht-bibliocon/20240606_tripreport.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Report on the Hands-On Lab ‘Scenarios for the Development of Open Access Repositories’ at the 112th BiblioCon</title>
  <dc:creator>Daniel Beucke</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Isabella Meinecke</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Marcel Wrzesinski</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-15-hands-on-lab-report/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the beginning of June 2024, Nature reported on the Japanese Ministry of Education’s plan to invest 10 billion yen in expanding institutional Open Access Repositories <span class="citation" data-cites="singh_chawla_japans_2024">(Singh Chawla 2024)</span>. This initiative provides a good opportunity to discuss the future of Open Access Repositories at the <a href="https://2024.bibliocon.de/" class="uri">https://2024.bibliocon.de/</a>.</p>
<p>In collaboration with the project “Professionalization of the Open Access Repositories Infrastructure in Germany” (<a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/de/forschung/infomanagement/projekte/pro-oar-de">Pro OAR DE</a>) <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_professionalisierung_2023">(Pampel and Rothfritz 2023)</span>, funded by the Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF), the Electronic Publishing Working Group (<a href="https://dini.de/e-pub">AG E-Pub</a>) of the German Initiative for Networked Information (<a href="https://dini.de">DINI</a>) organized a Hands-On Lab titled “Scenarios for the Development of Open Access Repositories” on June 6, 2024, during the 112th BiblioCon. The goal was to develop scenarios for the future orientation of institutional Open Access repositories with participants from academia, libraries, and other information infrastructures.</p>
<p>The methodological approach for this event was based on the Delphi concept <span class="citation" data-cites="hader_delphi-befragungen_2014">(Häder 2014)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="niederberger_delphi-verfahren_2019">(Niederberger and Renn 2019)</span>. Participants were asked to evaluate predefined statements on repositories in two consecutive rounds. This method aimed to reach a consensus on specific scenarios for the future of repositories. About 30 people participated in the lab and were divided into groups of four which simultaneously discussed the scenarios. The discussions were based on eight statements that were prepared by the organizers in advance and addressed aspects of the development of Open Access repositories.</p>
<p>First, each group assessed the eight statements with the aim of coming to a consensus about the topic. For example, participants were asked to discuss the following proposition: “Preprints play an important role in the informational expansion of repositories.” Each group needed to develop a joint position on this and the other seven statements, by rating them on a scale from “strongly disagree” to “strongly agree.”</p>
<p>In the following round, each group further explored three statements and discussed strategies and concrete measures to address the issues raised in each statements. The goal was to develop practical approaches to the topics, based on a shared understanding of the statements, focusing on the joint discussion of solution strategies.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-15-hands-on-lab-report/images/112th_bibliocon.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Lessons Learned</strong></p>
<p>The chosen method did not allow for in-depth examination and was not representative, but it enabled a focused and useful discussion of current issues facing institutional repositories. Reaching a consensus was challenging, as interpretations of the statements varied significantly among participants, and evaluations differed depending on perspectives and group compositions.</p>
<p>For the following three statements, approval ratings were identified in all four groups (grouped as “somewhat agree” and “strongly agree”):</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Repositories’ user interfaces should become more intuitive and modern.</p></li>
<li><p>Text and data repositories should intensify their exchange with each other.</p></li>
<li><p>Repositories should take more measures to increase the visibility of their content.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>In the second round, the following implementation strategies were discussed for these three statements:</p>
<p><strong>Repositories’ user interfaces should become more intuitive and modern:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Offer multilingual user interfaces that support languages beyond German and English.</p></li>
<li><p>Simplify uploads through data import via API integration (e.g., DOI queries via Crossref).</p></li>
<li><p>Eliminate mandatory fields that researchers must fill out.</p></li>
<li><p>Ensure responsiveness on various devices.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Text and data repositories should intensify their exchange with each other:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Ensure automatic data flows between research data repositories and institutional Open Access repositories.</p></li>
<li><p>Simplify uploads through data import via API integration (e.g., DOI queries via Crossref).</p></li>
<li><p>Evaluate local architecture to determine whether a generic repository for all object types or different repositories for each publication type is more practical.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Repositories should take more measures to increase the visibility of their content:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Display bibliographic data in the OPAC or Discovery System.</p></li>
<li><p>Index bibliographic data in search services .</p></li>
<li><p>Actively implement search engine optimization measures.</p></li>
<li><p>Enable automated data flows via persistent identifiers.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>The authors thank the participants for their open discussions and for sharing their experiences on strategies to further professionalize Open Access repositories.</p>
<p>The results will also be used for the further development of the DINI Certificate for Open-Access Publication Services and in the ongoing work of the Pro OAR DE project. Workshops on some aspects will be held in the further course of the Pro OAR DE project.</p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p><br>
Photo Credit: Melanie Seltmann, licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-hader_delphi-befragungen_2014" class="csl-entry">
Häder, Michael. 2014. <em>Delphi-<span>Befragungen</span>: <span>Ein</span> <span>Arbeitsbuch</span></em>. Wiesbaden: Springer Fachmedien Wiesbaden. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-658-01928-0">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-658-01928-0</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-niederberger_delphi-verfahren_2019" class="csl-entry">
Niederberger, Marlen, and Ortwin Renn, eds. 2019. <em>Delphi-<span>Verfahren</span> in Den <span>Sozial</span>- Und <span>Gesundheitswissenschaften</span>: <span>Konzept</span>, <span>Varianten</span> Und <span>Anwendungsbeispiele</span></em>. Wiesbaden: Springer Fachmedien Wiesbaden. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-658-21657-3">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-658-21657-3</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pampel_professionalisierung_2023" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, and Laura Rothfritz. 2023. <span>“Professionalisierung Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Repositorien</span>-<span>Infrastruktur</span> in <span>Deutschland</span> (<span>Pro</span>-<span>OAR</span>-<span>DE</span>).”</span> November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10173494">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10173494</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-singh_chawla_japans_2024" class="csl-entry">
Singh Chawla, Dalmeet. 2024. <span>“Japan’s Push to Make All Research Open Access Is Taking Shape.”</span> <em>Nature</em>, May. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-024-01493-8">https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-024-01493-8</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{beucke2024,
  author = {Beucke, Daniel and Meinecke, Isabella and Pampel, Heinz and
    Wrzesinski, Marcel},
  title = {Report on the {Hands-On} {Lab} “{Scenarios} for the
    {Development} of {Open} {Access} {Repositories}” at the 112th
    {BiblioCon}},
  date = {2024-07-15},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/mg09a-5ma64},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-beucke2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Beucke, Daniel, Isabella Meinecke, Heinz Pampel, and Marcel Wrzesinski.
2024. <span>“Report on the Hands-On Lab <span>‘Scenarios for the
Development of Open Access Repositories’</span> at the 112th
BiblioCon.”</span> July 15, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/mg09a-5ma64">https://doi.org/10.59350/mg09a-5ma64</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-15-hands-on-lab-report/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-15-hands-on-lab-report/112th_bibliocon.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Project launch: OA Datenpraxis- Data Practices for Shaping the Open Access Transformation</title>
  <dc:creator>Dorothea Strecker</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-01-Vorstellung-OA-Datenpraxis/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are excited to announce the launch of our new project, “Data Practices for Shaping Open Access Transformation - Analysis, Recommendation, Training &amp; Networking - OA Datenpraxis” funded by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG, German Research Foundation).</p>
<p>Together with our colleagues at the <a href="https://os.helmholtz.de/">Helmholtz Open Science Office</a> and the <a href="https://subugoe.github.io/scholcomm_analytics/">Scholarly Communication Analytics Team</a> at the <a href="https://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/sub-aktuell/">Lower Saxony State and University Library Göttingen</a> (SUB), we, the research group Information Management at the <a href="https://www.ibi.hu-berlin.de/en/about-us">Berlin School of Library and Information Science</a> (IBI), will work towards strengthening structures for the use of data on the open access transformation at research institutions in Germany.</p>
<p>The project supports practitioners in research administration, libraries and other service institutions in professionalizing their data practices through various activities. As a first step, the team at IBI will conduct a comprehensive study on how research institutions handle publication costs. Our research will build on existing research and previous work of the project partners. Our goal is to get a better understanding of current practices and challenges associated with managing data on Open Access publications and associated costs.</p>
<p>In strengthening the abilities of research institutions to leverage data to monitor publication output and associated costs, we are addressing some of the recommendations of the German Council of Science and Humanities for fostering the Open Access transformation in Germany <span class="citation" data-cites="wissenschaftsrat_empfehlungen_2022">(Wissenschaftsrat 2022)</span>. Additional information about the project and its goals can be found in the project proposal (in German) <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_datenpraxis_2024">(Pampel et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>At this year’s Open-Access-Tage in Cologne, we are organizing a workshop with <a href="https://www.open-access-berlin.de/">Open-Access-Büro Berlin</a>, <a href="https://open-access-brandenburg.de/">Vernetzungs- und Kompetenzstelle Open Access Brandenburg</a> and <a href="https://open-access-monitor.de/">Open Access Monitor</a> at Forschungszentrum Jülich (FZJ). If you are interested in Open Access reporting and are attending, please feel free to approach us at the conference or contact us via <a href="info.oa-datenpraxis@listserv.dfn.de">email</a>.</p>
<p>We will report on current activities and project outputs on the <a href="https://oa-datenpraxis.de/">project website</a> and <a href="https://openbiblio.social/@oa_datenpraxis">Mastodon</a>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-01-Vorstellung-OA-Datenpraxis/logo_oa_datenpraxis.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Further information about the research group can be found on our <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt">official website</a>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labeled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_datenpraxis_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, Najko Jahn, Roland Bertelmann, Wolfram Horstmann, Laura Rothfritz, Lea Maria Ferguson, Birgit Schmidt, and Anna Stisser. 2024. <span>“Datenpraxis Zur <span>Gestaltung</span> Der <span>Open</span>-<span>Access</span>-<span>Transformation</span> - <span>Analyse</span>, <span>Empfehlung</span>, <span>Training</span> &amp; <span>Vernetzung</span> (<span>OA</span> <span>Datenpraxis</span>).”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10794298">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10794298</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wissenschaftsrat_empfehlungen_2022" class="csl-entry">
Wissenschaftsrat. 2022. <span>“Empfehlungen Zur <span>Transformation</span> Des Wissenschaftlichen <span>Publizierens</span> Zu <span>Open</span> <span>Access</span>.”</span> <a href="https://doi.org/10.57674/FYRC-VB61">https://doi.org/10.57674/FYRC-VB61</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{strecker2024,
  author = {Strecker, Dorothea and Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Project Launch: {OA} {Datenpraxis-} {Data} {Practices} for
    {Shaping} the {Open} {Access} {Transformation}},
  date = {2024-06-19},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/es0dc-vhb02},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-strecker2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Strecker, Dorothea, and Heinz Pampel. 2024. <span>“Project Launch: OA
Datenpraxis- Data Practices for Shaping the Open Access
Transformation.”</span> June 19, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/es0dc-vhb02">https://doi.org/10.59350/es0dc-vhb02</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-01-Vorstellung-OA-Datenpraxis/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-07-01-Vorstellung-OA-Datenpraxis/logo_oa_datenpraxis.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Recommendations for Funding Organizations on Open Science Infrastructures</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2026-06-11-recommendations-on-open-science-infrastructures/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I had the great opportunity to be part of the <a href="https://home.cern/news/news/knowledge-sharing/cern-and-nasa-join-forces-commit-research-future-open-and-accessible">CERN-NASA</a> working group “Infrastructure for Open Scholarship”. This working group was established following the 2023 CERN-NASA Summit “Accelerating the Adoption of Open Science”. As a result of the summit, a closing statement was published, outlining key areas of action for Open Science <span class="citation" data-cites="tananbaum_sowing_2023">(Tananbaum et al. 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>Under the umbrella of the Open Research Funders Group (<a href="https://www.orfg.org/news/2023/11/01/cern-nasa-summit">ORFG</a>) and with financial support from the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation, key topics from the closing statement were further developed in working groups. One of these working groups focused on the advancement of open science infrastructures. Our working group has now published its results in the form of a set of recommendations for funding organizations <span class="citation" data-cites="arancio_science_2024">(Arancio et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2026-06-11-recommendations-on-open-science-infrastructures/wg.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Excerpt: “These recommendations for funders are accompanied by a set of principles for open infrastructure projects that complements the first set and aims to increase the quality of service provided to researchers and institutions. The group aims to emphasize that the principles for infrastructure initiatives do not have a prescriptive approach; instead, the goal should be to foster good practices in the field. This work intends to add and build on the corpus of work that has been undertaken globally in this area, some of which is referenced at the end of this document. As with any global framework, it will need to be regionally situated to ensure feasibility, efficacy, and sustainability in a diversity of contexts.”</p>
<p>Recommendations for funding agencies based on a set of core principles were created. These principles encompass the topics of infrastructure in open scholarship policies, recognizing work, funding and support, capabilities, and transparency.</p>
<p>Many thanks to <a href="https://www.orfg.org/news/2023/10/02/orfg-welcomes-julieta-arancio-as-open-accelerator-fellow">Julieta Arancio</a> for her effective and cooperative leadership of the working group, and to all participants for their openness.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-arancio_science_2024" class="csl-entry">
Arancio, Julieta, Claudia Alarcón-López, Heinz Pampel, Sherry Lake, César Pallares, Esther Plomp, Miho Funamori, Tanja Friedrich, Emmy Tsang, and CERN-NASA Working Group "Infrastructure for Open Scholarship". 2024. <span>“Science <span>Funders</span>: <span>Commitments</span> Towards <span>Open</span> <span>Infrastructure</span>,”</span> June. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11444361">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11444361</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-tananbaum_sowing_2023" class="csl-entry">
Tananbaum, Greg, Chelle Gentemann, Kamran Naim, Christopher Marcum, Eric Emsellem, Eunice Mercado-Lara, Tanja Friedrich, et al. 2023. <span>“Sowing the <span>Seeds</span> of <span>Global</span> <span>Open</span> <span>Science</span> <span>Coordination</span>,”</span> November. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10059154">https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.10059154</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Recommendations for {Funding} {Organizations} on {Open}
    {Science} {Infrastructures}},
  date = {2024-06-11},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/n1143-h4119},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2024. <span>“Recommendations for Funding Organizations on
Open Science Infrastructures.”</span> June 11, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/n1143-h4119">https://doi.org/10.59350/n1143-h4119</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Policy</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2026-06-11-recommendations-on-open-science-infrastructures/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2026-06-11-recommendations-on-open-science-infrastructures/wg.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome</title>
  <dc:creator>Heinz Pampel</dc:creator>
  <link>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-03-25-welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Welcome! This is the first post in our new group blog.<sup>1</sup> We, the research group Information Management at Humboldt University’s Berlin School of Library and Information Science, explore the role of digital research and information infrastructures in science within the context of digital transformation.</p>
<p>The focus of our research is on information infrastructures that enable the collection, indexing, accessibility, and re-use of information objects for the purpose of Open Science.</p>
<p>Our work considers processes of digital scholarly communication and related practices, standards, and policies. These aspects are addressed from the perspective of information and library science, with a focus on libraries, computing centers, and other service facilities supporting research at scientific organizations.</p>
<p><img src="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-03-25-welcome/ibi.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Current topics of our research and teaching group include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Information infrastructures for Open Science</p></li>
<li><p>Research data management</p></li>
<li><p>Open Access and developments in digital scholarly communication</p></li>
<li><p>Research software and digital services for information and knowledge production</p></li>
<li><p>Management of research information</p></li>
<li><p>Science policy and Open Science</p></li>
<li><p>Academic libraries in the context of changing information and knowledge practices</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Further information about our work can be found on our official website: <a href="http://hu.berlin/infomgnt" class="uri">http://hu.berlin/infomgnt</a></p>
<p>If you’re interested in learning more about our research, you might want to check out a guest post we published a few days ago about our Pro OAR DE project on the DINI colleagues’ blog <span class="citation" data-cites="pampel_open_2024">(Pampel and Wrzesinski 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>This text – excluding quotes and otherwise labelled parts – is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.de">CC BY 4.0 DEED</a>.</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-pampel_open_2024" class="csl-entry">
Pampel, Heinz, and Marcel Wrzesinski. 2024. <span>“Open <span>Access</span> <span>Repositories</span> in <span>Transition</span>: <span>Strategies</span> for <span>Professionalization</span>.”</span> <em>Blog Der DINI AGs FIS &amp; EPUB</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.57689/dini-blog.20240311">https://doi.org/10.57689/dini-blog.20240311</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Sure, in this blog, there will also be footnotes ;)↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{pampel2024,
  author = {Pampel, Heinz},
  title = {Welcome},
  date = {2024-03-25},
  url = {https://doi.org/10.59350/yfaq3-ha496},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-pampel2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Pampel, Heinz. 2024. <span>“Welcome.”</span> March 25, 2024. <a href="https://doi.org/10.59350/yfaq3-ha496">https://doi.org/10.59350/yfaq3-ha496</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Lab Life</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-03-25-welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://infomgnt.org/posts/2024-03-25-welcome/ibi.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
